<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id: PatchManager.xml 1374 2005-03-04 11:43:02Z schneide $
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="PatchManager">
    <title>Patch Manager (deprecated)</title>

    <para><tip><title>** The Patch Manager is DEPRECATED
      **</title> <para>In CodeX version 2.4 and above, the Patch Manager
      has been discontinued. It is now replaced by the CodeX
      Tracker Service (see <xref linkend="TrackerService"/>). This chapter
      is included in the CodeX User Guide for projects that originally
      used the legacy Patch Manager.</para></tip></para>


    <section id="HowToSubmitSourceCodeContribution">
      <title>How To Submit Source Code Contribution</title>

      <para>CodeX gives you an unparalleled ability to learn from the source
      code of others by making source code sharing a common practice at &SYS_ORG_NAME;.
      When you re-use a piece of code from CodeX, the Code eXchange Policy
      specifies that any modification you&#39;ve made to the original source
      code must be returned to the original team.</para>

      <para>This is the role of the Patch Manager to facilitate this process.
      The Patch Manager allows for:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>The submission of source code modifications by CodeX users</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>The management of these submissions by the project team</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>On how to generate source code patches see the CVS chapter (<xref
      linkend="VersionControlWithCVS" />).</para>

      <note><para><emphasis role="underline">A note to the project team</emphasis></para>
      <para>Receiving
      source code modifications or other contributions from other CodeX users
      does not imply that you have to accept the new code and insert it in
      your main source tree. It is up to the project team to decide what to do
      with it. One of the interesting features of the Patch Manager is that
      submitted patches are available to anybody at all time regardless of the
      final decision of the project team. Therefore any CodeX visitor is free
      to download any submitted patch and apply it onto its own version of the
      software even if the project team has decided not to apply the patch on
      the main source tree.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="PatchBrowsing">
      <title>Patch Browsing</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members and CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>To access the Patch Manager select the &#34;Patches&#34; item from
      the Project Menu at the top of the screen of the Project Summary page.
      The welcome page of the Patch Manager allows you to browse all the
      patches that have been submitted to this project.</para>

      <para>Patches can be selected by Assignee, Status and Category.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Assignee</emphasis>: this is the name of
          the project member in charge of this specific patch</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: status of the patch.
          It is one of:</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Open</emphasis>: the patch has
              been submitted and is being processed by the project team</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Deleted</emphasis>: the project
              team rejected the patch. It is marked as deleted but it is still
              visible to the CodeX users and it can be downloaded</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Closed</emphasis>: the patch
              was integrated in the main source tree.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Postponed</emphasis>: patch
              considered interesting but integration in the main source tree
              is postponed</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Category</emphasis>: project
          administrators can define categories for patches. Classifying
          patches in various categories makes patch selection and browsing
          easier. The categories generally correspond to high-level modules or
          functionalities of the software.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure id="FigurePatchBrowsing">
        <title>Patch browsing</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_patchbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The Patch Manager menu offers 2 shortcuts to quickly select all
      patches with status value at Open (&#34;Open Patches&#34; link) and
      those that have been assigned to you (&#34;My Patches&#34; link). This
      is mostly for project members.</para>

      <para>To download a patch, click on the Patch ID number in the first
      column of the result list (<xref linkend="FigurePatchBrowsing" />) and
      then click on the &#34;View raw patch&#34; link in the next screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="PatchSubmission">
      <title>Patch Submission</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members and CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>In most cases, registered users who are not part of the project
      team submit source code patches. However this service can also be used
      by the project members if, for some reason, they were not granted write
      access to the CVS repository.</para>

      <para>Before you submit a patch you must first generate it. This has
      been discussed in the CVS chapter. For more information please refer to
      section <xref linkend="ContributingyourChanges" />.</para>

      <para>To submit a patch, click on the &#34;Submit a Patch&#34; item in
      the Patch Manager menu bar (see <xref linkend="FigurePatchBrowsing" />).
      Give a one-line description in the &#34;Summary&#34; field. Please be
      accurate. Then choose a category (if any) and then attach the patch.
      Attaching the patch can either be done by pasting the source code of the
      patch in the HTML form or by using the upload facility. To validate the
      submission click on the &#34;Submit Patch&#34; button at the end of the
      screen.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="PatchProcessing">
      <title>Patch Processing</title>

      <para>To process submitted patches, first use the Patch Browsing
      facility to select the patches you are interested in and click on the
      Patch ID number in the first column of the result list (<xref
      linkend="FigurePatchBrowsing" />).</para>

      <para>Processing a patch consists in:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Assigning new incoming patches to project members for
          evaluation and recommendation on what to do with it and when</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Changing the status of the patch as the project team makes
          progress in the evaluation of the contributed code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Changing the Category and possibly the Summary to better
          reflect the nature of the contribution (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Adding a follow-up comment to the patch (e.g. why it is a good
          one, when to include it into the source code or in which release of
          the software it has been integrated...)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can also submit a new version of the patch thus overriding
          the old one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Don&#39;t forget to click on the &#34;Submit Changes&#34; button
      to validate your modifications.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="PatchManagerE-mailNotification">
      <title>E-mail Notification</title>

      <para>Like other CodeX services the CodeX Patch Manager is equipped with
      an e-mail notification system. The e-mail notification system follows
      very simple rules. Each time a patch is submitted or updated - whether
      with an additional follow-up comment, with a change in any of the patch
      field or with a new version of the patch - an e-mail notification is
      sent to the following people:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The patch submitter (the person who initially submitted the
          patch)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The patch assignee (the project member to whom the patch is
          assigned)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The e-mail addresses specified in the &#34;Other Configuration
          Settings&#34; screen of the Patch Administration module (see <xref
          linkend="PatchManagerOtherConfigurationSettings" />). These e-mail
          addresses can be any email address you want including a distribution
          list that was created with the CodeX Mailing List manager (see <xref
          linkend="MailingLists" />) or via MS-Exchange.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The e-mail notification consists of the Patch ID number, Summary,
      Category and Status plus all follow-up comments sorted by date (most
      recent first).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="PatchManagerAdministration">
      <title>Patch Manager Administration</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>Project members that have been granted Administrative rights on
      the Patch Manager can configure the Patch Manager in a number of ways.</para>

      <section id="DefiningCategories">
        <title>Defining Categories</title>

        <para>The Patch Manager allows you to define Patch categories. These
        categories can be used to characterize the nature of the patch when it
        is submitted. To add or delete Patch categories click on the
        &#34;Admin&#34; item in the Patch Manager menu at the top of the
        screen (<xref linkend="FigurePatchBrowsing" />).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="PatchManagerOtherConfigurationSettings">
        <title>Other Configuration Settings</title>

        <para>This Patch Manager configuration module allows you to define the
        following configuration parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>An introductory message that we&#39;ll show up at the top of
            the Patch submission form. This is a convenient way to give
            directions and recommendations to the patch submitter. The text
            must use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great flexibility
            to shape the content of this preamble (you can use bold, italic,
            embed URL...)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A series of comma separated email addresses to which new
            patch submission and patch updates will be sent. If you want a
            (group of) person to be systematically aware of new item
            submission you can add his/her e-mail address in this text field.
            Checking the &#34;Send on all updates&#34; check box will cause
            e-mail notification to be sent on all updates in addition to the
            initial submission.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

