<!--
//
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, Codendi 2007-2008.
// This file is licensed under the GNU General Public License version 2. See the file COPYING. 
//
//
//
-->
  <chapter id="CommunicationServices">
    <title>Communication Tools</title>

    <para>One of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; objectives is to provide developers with
    efficient software development and project management tools. In
    addition, the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; site should quickly become the favorite
    communication channel of all users as it is pivotal for the
    project teams and their community of users to communicate
    efficiently.</para>

    <para>To this end, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; offers a series of communication services that
    can be customized by the project team. These include mailing lists, the
    News service, the Web Forums and a Instant Messaging Plug-in.</para>

    <section id="MailingLists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>

      <section id="MailingListsCreation">
        <title>Creation</title>
        
      <para>Each project can create as many mailing lists (ML) as
      needed. To create a mailing list click on the &#34;Lists&#34;
      item in the Project Main menu, then click on the &#34;Admin&#34;
      link in the mailing list menu bar.</para>

      <para>Adding a ML is just a matter of giving it a name, a one-line
      description, and to specify whether it is a public or a private list. A
      private list won&#39;t show up on the welcome screen of the Mailing List
      service and is therefore only known to the project team. This will
      prevent other people from subscribing or posting messages to it.</para>

      <para>In order to minimize naming conflicts between the many MLs created
      by the various &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; projects, the mailing list follows the following
      naming pattern:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
projectname-listname@&SYS_LISTS_HOST;
</programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>projectname</literal>
           is your project short name as defined during project
          registration.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>listname</literal> is the name
          you have chosen for your mailing list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note><para>Creating a mailing list implies that you are the
      mailing list administrator, at least at the beginning. As the ML
      administrator, you&#39;ll receive some additional instructions via
      e-mail shortly after the creation of the ML. This is an important mail
      message that contains the URLs for the ML administration and information
      pages and the default ML administration password generated by &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.
      Keep it in a safe place!</para></note>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Create at least one Mailing List</title><para>A
      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; hosted project should at least create one mailing list (or a web forum) where all
      users can post questions and comments. This list is typically called
      <literal>projectname-interest@&SYS_LISTS_HOST;</literal>. We
      strongly encourage you to follow this well established practice.</para></tip></para>
      </section>

      <section id="MailingListsAdministration">
        <title>Administration</title>

        <para>The ML administration is also entirely Web based. You can access
        the ML administration page by using the URL that you received when you
        first created the ML. In case you have misplaced the original message
        you can access the ML administration page at the following URL:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
http://&SYS_LISTS_HOST;/mailman/admin/listname
</programlisting>

        <para>The Administration page allows you to tune many ML parameters,
        manage list members, and administrators, privacy, new member welcome
        messages, etc. GNU/Mailman, the ML manager used by &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;, is an extremely
        capable software and we invite you to visit the administration page at
        least once to get an idea about the feature set.</para>

        <note><para>Note that project administrators are not
        automatically made administrators of project mailing lists, and the
        administrative password for the mailing list is distinct from any of
        the other &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; user passwords.</para></note>
      </section>

      <section id="UnSubscriptionArchiveandPreferences">
        <title>(Un)Subscription, Archive and Preferences</title>

        <para>Unless its owner marks a ML as private, any &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; user can
        subscribe to a project Mailing List (ML). To subscribe to a mailing
        list click on the &#34;Lists&#34; item in the Project Main menu. From there click on the
        &#34;Subscribe/Unsubscribe/Preferences&#34; link of the appropriate
        ML. Then follow the instructions presented.</para>

        <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; ML system (GNU/Mailman) also archives all the messages
        posted on a mailing list. Following the &#34;Archive&#34; link on the
        same page as before will bring you to archived messages grouped by
        month. Note that the current archiving software is not MIME-aware and
        does not support the archiving of attachments.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="NewsService">
      <title>News Service</title>

      <para>The News service complements your mailing lists. This service
      allows you to publish pieces of news related to your project. Any event
      in the life of your project is a good candidate for a news release: new
      people in the team, new software release, information on related
      technologies and why not your wedding announcement or the birth of your
      sixth child ? . Do not keep your project concealed behind a veil. Make
      your project life public for the benefit of all employees and for
      your faithful community of users.</para>

      <para>News publishing is very easy. Simply click on the &#34;News&#34;
      item in the Project Main menu and then on the &#34;Submit&#34; link in
      the News Service menu at the top of the page. From there type the title
      of the news and its text body. You can type URLs in the body. &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; will
      detect them and transform them into a hyperlink in the published
      version. You can also choose whether you want the news to be public this means
      visible on your Project Dashboard for all &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; users or private 
      which means visible for your project members only.</para>

      <para>
      Any &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; visitor can attach a follow-up comment to the news visible for
      her on your project page making each
      piece of news a potential forum of discussion<footnote><para>Behind the
      scene, each piece of news is actually managed exactly like a &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Web
      Forum.</para></footnote>. In addition the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team sees all the public news
      published by all &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; projects and can decide that a project news is
      worth publishing on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; front page. A big splash indeed!!
      When submitting a news, you can request a promotion for the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; front
      page to the administrator.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="WebForums">
      <title>Web Forums</title>

      <para>This is the third form of communication offered by &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;. Web
      Forums are more or less equivalent to mailing list except that the
      message-posting takes place via a Web interface rather than email. Therefore you need to
      have a connection to the site to participate in the discussion because
      you can&#39;t prepare your message off-line, as you can with an ML.</para>

      <para>To access the Web Forums of a &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; project, click on the
      &#34;Forums&#34; item in the Project Main menu. When a &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
      project is created, it is given three Web forums: Open
      Discussions, Help and Developers. These Forums and all others
      are open to all &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; users both for reading and posting unless
      you decide to make them private (see below). A user can also
      decide to monitor a Web Forum. Monitoring a Forum will cause
      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; to automatically forward all the posted messages via e-
      mail thus avoiding repeated visits to the Forum Web page.</para>

      <para>Project administrators can create other Forums on demand by using
      the Forum Administration module that can be accessed via the
      &#34;Admin&#34; link in the News Service menu. Administrators can follow
      the links on this page to Add Forum, Delete Message, and Update Forum
      Info/Status. The Update Forum Info/Status page lets administrators make
      forums public or private, edit the name and description of the forum, or
      even delete the forum.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="IMPlugin">
        <title>Instant Messaging Plug-in</title>
        
        <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; is bundled with a Jabber server and an Instant Messaging (IM)
        Plug-In that allows a certain level of integration between them.</para>
        
        <para>If this plug-in is active, an IM account will be automatically
        available to each &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; user and they will be able to log into the Jabber
        server using their &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; credentials. Furthermore, users participating in
        a project will be grouped together in the Jabber server, whose will 
        automatically add this group to each of the participants' roster.</para>
        
        <para>For each project the plug-in will create a multi-user chat room (MUC)
        where the members of a project can chat together. Only members of a project
        can join its respective MUC, but once a member has joined the room he or she
        can invite external users.</para>
        
        <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; IM plug-in comes with a Jabber client integrated
        into the web interface of your project. This client lets you chat into the project
        MUC Room (see <xref linkend="MUCRoomsIntegration" />).
        Of course, each user can choose the client that best fits his or her needs. Several
        open source (and/or free) clients are available for the most common platforms,
        and you can find a list (non-exhaustive) of them at 
        <ulink url="http://www.jabber.org/clients">http://www.jabber.org/clients</ulink>.
        Note that some clients, like Coccinella for instance, allow you to do shared whiteboard.
        </para>
        
        <para>The status of a user using a Jabber client (online, busy, away) is 
        displayed in &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.</para>
        
        <section id="JabberOnWebPage">
        <title>Jabber Related Information on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Web Page</title>
        
        <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; provides several bits of information regarding the Instant 
        Messaging on its web interface. Thus, each user has access to his roster 
        (contact list) and the status of each of his contacts directly on his personal page.
        In order to do this, simply visit the page "My Personal Page". If the widget 
        displaying the contact list is not visible it must be added. To do so, click on the 
        link "Add widgets" and add the widget corresponding to "My IM Roster".
        </para>
        
        <para>Next to each user name &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; displays a colored icon (gray, green, yellow 
        or red) that indicates the status of the user: gray for "offline", green for "online",
        yellow for "away", and red for "busy". Users can change their status through their 
        Jabber client.</para>
        
        <para>Any new approved project implies the creation of a corresponding shared group
        and chat room.</para>
        
        <para>Any new member added to the project is also added to the corresponding shared
        group and chat room. This new member will be automatically invited to join the 
        project's chat room as soon as he or she connects to the Jabber server.</para>
        
        <para>If a member is removed from a project then he or she will also be removed 
        from its corresponding shared group and chat room.</para>
        
        <para>If a project is suspended or awaiting validation, its corresponding chat 
        room will be made unavailable (locked) and the shared group will not be visible on 
        the roster of project members.</para>
        
        <para>If a project is deleted, the corresponding chat room and shared group will 
        be destroyed as well.</para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="JabberClientConfiguration">
            <title>Jabber Client Configuration</title>
            
            <para>Configuring a Jabber client to use your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; account is 
            straightforward. In case you are using a multi protocol client the first 
            thing you need to do is setting the communication protocol to Jabber (or XMPP). 
            Three other pieces of information are essential for connecting to your Jabber 
            account: your username, your password, and the address of the Jabber server you 
            will connect to. Some Jabber clients refer to the JID (or Jabber ID) which is 
            simply your username and the Jabber server address connected by a @ sign 
            (eg. username@jabberhost.com), others ask explicitly for your username and the 
            Jabber server address. You can find your JID at your personal area on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; 
            web page by logging into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; and clicking on the link “Account Maintenance” on 
            the tab  “My Personal Page”, or simply by accessing your “Developer Profile”. 
            There you can find your “Instant Messaging Login”, which is  formed by your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; 
            username and the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Jabber server address. Use the same password you use to 
            sign in to your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; account.</para>
            
            <para>In addition to these parameters the client may ask you a name for 
            the resource you are using to connect to your Jabber account. This is handy 
            when you are connected to the same Jabber account through different devices 
            and so, for example, a message can be delivered to you@yourhost.com/pda instead 
            of you@yourhost.com/office (in this case “pda” and “office” are the resources).
            You can fill it with any alpha-numeric string.</para>
            
            <para>Finally, the client needs to know the port number the Jabber server 
            is listening to. The default value for this parameter is 5222, and most of 
            the Jabber clients use it by default.</para>
            
            <para>Some other “advanced” parameters can be configured, but it is out 
            of the scope of this guide to talk about them, so please refer to your Jabber 
            client documentation for further information on this topic.      
            </para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section id="MUCRoomsIntegration">
            <title>Multi-User Chat Room (MUC)</title>
            <para>As stated before, the IM plug-in creates a multi-user chat
            room for each project. This room is named after the project name 
            and is opened only for project members.</para>
            <para>
                You can access the MUC Room in the web interface of your project, 
                or with a IM client.
            </para>
            
            <section id="MUCRooms">
             <title>MUC Room with the web interface</title>
             <para>
             To enter the chat room of your project, you just need to clic on
             the IM tab of your project. This will automatically connect you
             to IM, and you will be able to start chating with the other 
             connected members.
             </para>
             <para>
             The web interface of the chat room is composed of several areas:
             <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
               <para>
                    The main window shows you the messages of all participants.
                    The names of the participants are written beside the messages,
                    to let you better follow the discussion.
                    The system messages (like who arrived in the room, who left)
                    are displayed in bold.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Messages are displayed without specific format, but you can
                    add some if you want (see <xref linkend="MUCRoomsMessagesTips" />
                    for that).
                    URLs are displayed as hyperlinks (and are opened in another window).
                    Project references are also displayed as hyperlinks (for instance, 
                    if you write the message bug #23 in the chat room, a click on the word
                    'bug #23' will open a new window and will lead you to the bug details
                    page). The system does not check that bug 23 really exist in your
                    project. it is possible to make references to other projects,
                    but only with the pattern keyword #projectID:itemNumber.
                    The pattern with project name is not recognized by IM.
                    For more details about cross-references, see <xref linkend="ReferenceOverview" />.
                </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                <para>
                    Just below the main window, is the writing message area.
                    To send a message to all chat room members, select this area
                    with the mouse, write your message, and then either click on
                    the 'Send' button, either press the 'Enter' key.
                    Your message will show up in the flow, preceed by your name.
                </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                <para>
                    The area on the right is the list of the room members, which
                    means the users connected to the chat room.
                    This list is updated in real time.
                 </para>
                 <para>
                    There is a concept of private messages. If you want to talk to
                    someone, but don't want the other to see it, you can click on
                    the name of the person, and then write your message (the name
                    of the user is now just below your message, which indicate
                    he will be the only one to receive it). To come back to the
                    usual way of doing (chat with eveybody) you just need to
                    click again on the name of the person in the writing area, 
                    which will make the buddy name disappear.
                </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                <para>
                    Above the main area, the name of the chat room is written
                    (it is the name of the project, you can not change it).
                    Just below, you can find the topic of the room.
                    You can update this topic by writing the special command as 
                    a message:
                    <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
/topic The new topic of the room
                    </programlisting>
                </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                <para>
                    Below the writing area is located a status zone, corresponding to
                    your IM status. This status can be useful to tell the other
                    if your are free to chat, or busy, etc.
                    You can also add a free text, to express your mood of the day,
                    or anything else!
                </para>
                <para>
                    On the right, there is a small icon which lets you switch off/
                    swith on the sound.
                    You need a Flash plugin in your browser to have sound.
                </para>
               </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
             </para>
             
             <figure id="FigureWebMucRooms">
              <title>Multi-User Chat Room in the web interface of &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;</title>
              
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                 <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_webmucrooms.png" />
                 </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
             </figure>
             
             <para>
              <tip id="MUCRoomsMessagesTips">
               <title>Tips: formatting and special commands</title>
               <para>
                    When you type some text in the chat window, the client
                    interprets some commands to format the text. These commands
                    can be interpreted depending on the IM client, but most of them
                    are working the same way.
                    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Write in bold:</emphasis>
                        you must surround your text with a star.
                        <para>Example: I will call you *tomorrow at 2 o'clock*</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Underlign:</emphasis>
                        you must surround the text with underscore.
                        <para>Example: I will call you _tomorrow at 2 o'clock_</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Write a hyperlink:</emphasis>
                        the system will detect hyperlinks if they are starting with http://
                        <para>Example : You can read http://tuleap.net and see what I mean</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Make a cross-reference to a item of your project:</emphasis>
                        You can make a reference to any item of your project (artifact, bug, document, wiki page, etc.)
                        For that, just write the reference to the item respecting the pattern
                        keyword #itemnumber
                        <para>Example : You can read the document doc #185 for more details.</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Change the chat room topic:</emphasis>
                        you must write the specific command /topic followed by the new name of the topic.
                        <para>Example: /topic Monthly Meeting</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Change your nickname:</emphasis>
                        You can change your nickname during the session.
                        The other users will then see you as this new name.
                        This feature can seem funny, but remember that the 
                        the discussion will be hard to follow if everybody change 
                        his nickname often. We recommand you to use this feature 
                        if it makes sens only (to differenciate two people with 
                        a close name for instance).
                        Please note that nickname changes won't appear in chat room
                        logs. Messages will always be alloted to their real user.
                        To change the nickname, the command is /nick followed by
                        your new nickname.
                        <para>Example: /nick Tom - at home</para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                      <para>
                       <emphasis role="bold">Smileys:</emphasis>
                        You can use smileys. The web client doesn't have an interface
                        to insert smileys, but you can add them in a textual way.
                        They will appear like an image for the clients (even for
                        the web one).
                        Each client implements its own smileys, so use the more 
                        commons ones, and you shouldn't have any problem.
                       <para>
                        Example: the text :-) will display a beautiful smile!
                       </para>
                      </para>
                     </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
               </para>
              </tip>
             </para>
             
            </section>
            
            <section id="MUCWithClient">
             <title>Join a MUC Room with a client</title>
                <para>You need to inform your Jabber client the address of the conference
                server it must query for chat rooms. This address is simply 
                conference.server_address, i.e. the word “conference”, a dot, and the 
                Jabber server address. Then you will be able to retrieve the list of available
                chat rooms on the server. Just find the chat room corresponding to your project
                and join it.</para>
                
                <para>Of course the steps described above are very generic, and each 
                Jabber client has its own specific process. Please check your Jabber client 
                documentation for further information about its support on multi-user chat 
                (group chat, conferences, or simply chat rooms).</para>
            
                <para>Once inside the room you can invite non-members to join it.
                Once the user accepts the invitation he or she becomes member of
                the chat room.</para>
            
                <para>For further information on how to invite external users to chat
                rooms using your Jabber client please refer to its documentation.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section id="MUCRoomLogs">
             <title>MUC Room Logs</title>
             <para>
                Conversations in chat rooms are logged (private conversation are not).
                To access the log, select the link 'Logs' in the IM tab of your project.
                Every member of the project has access to the project room logs.
             </para>
             <para>
                By default, conversation logs of the 7 last days are displayed.
                You can of course change the search period, thanks to the
                calendar. If you don't want to specify dates, leave the field 
                blank. Blank for start date means "from the beginning", blank for
                end date means "until now".
             </para>
             <para>
                Conversation logs are grouped by day.
                You will find the time of the message (hour and minute),
                the author of the message (username on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
                server), and of course the message itself.
                Nickname changes are not logged. System messages are present. 
                This is very useful to know who was in the room when what thing
                has been told.
                URLs and cross-references will appear as hyperlinks, but special
                commands (see <xref linkend="MUCRoomsMessagesTips" />) won't be
                interpreted.
             </para>
             <para>
                A light horizontal line will separate conversations. Two conversations
                are considered as different if there has been no activity during
                at least 10 minutes.
             </para>
             <para>
                You can export the room logs, in CSV format.
                To do this, click on the Export button at the end of the logs.
                The export will use your user preferences for CSV separator and
                date format (see <xref linkend="UserPreferences" />).
             </para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

