<!--
//
// Portion of this file is inspired from the  GForge Command-line Interface
// contained in GForge.
// Copyright 2005 GForge, LLC
// http://gforge.org/
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
//
// $Id$
//
// Written by Marc Nazarian 2006, CodeX Team, Xerox
//

-->
  <chapter id="Installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>In order to install CodeX's Command Line Interface (CLI), 
    you must have PHP installed on your local machine. The latest 
    PHP4 version or PHP 5 is highly recommended. Also, PHP must be 
    compiled without the --disable-cli parameter in order to create 
    the PHP binaries.</para>

    <para>You must check in which directory you have your PHP binary 
    installed. The directory is the prefix that was specified when 
    compiling PHP (if no prefix was defined, it defaults to /usr, 
    so the PHP binary is located in /usr/bin/php).
    <tip>
        <title>How to know where PHP binary is located ?</title>
        <para>You can check in which directory it is installed by 
            issuing the following command:
            <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
# which php
/usr/bin/php
            </programlisting>
            In this case, the PHP binary is /usr/bin/php.
        </para>
    </tip>
    </para>

    <para><note>If you intend using the CLI for administering a CodeX 
    installation via an HTTPS connection, you must compile PHP with 
    the CURL extension (using the --with-curl option in the configure 
    script).</note></para>

    <para> Once you have PHP properly installed, you must download 
    and uncompress the CLI to a directory in your local machine.</para>

    <para>Once you've uncompressed the CLI, you must edit $PREFIX/codex.php 
    (where $PREFIX is the directory in which the CLI was uncompressed) 
    using your favorite editor and change the following:
    <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Change the first line which says: 
            <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
#!/usr/bin/php -q
            </programlisting>
            to make it point to the path of the PHP binary in your machine 
            (if it is different from /usr/bin/php)
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Find the Configuration section in the script (marked between comments) 
                and change the following constants:
                <para>
                <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                 <listitem>
                    <para>NUSOAP_DIR: Points to the installation directory of the 
                        NuSOAP PHP Library. A copy of the library is located in 
                        $PREFIX/nusoap/.
                    </para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
                    <para>CODEX_CLI_DIR: Points to the directory where the CLI 
                        auxiliary files are to be found. It usually is 
                        $PREFIX/include/.
                    </para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
                    <para>WSDL_URL (optional): URL of the WSDL of your CodeX's SOAP server. 
                        It is probably located in http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/index.php?wsdl. 
                        You can see if the URL is correct by entering it in your browser, 
                        you should get an XML file from the server as the result. If this variable 
                        isn't set, the CLI will try to use the WSDL specified in the CODEX_WSDL 
                        environment variable.
                    </para>
                 </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                </para>
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Make sure the codex.php script has execution permissions. 
                If not, set the permission by issuing the following command:
                <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
chmod +x $PREFIX/codex.php
                </programlisting>
          </para>
        </step>
    </procedure>
    
    <para>
        After everything is properly set up, you must test the installation 
        works correctly. For this, try logging into the server by issuing a 
        "login" command. For this, change your current working directory to 
        the directory in which you uncompressed the CLI and execute the following:
        <example>
            <title>login command</title>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
[mnazaria@linux codex cli ]$ ./codex.php -v login --username=(your user) --password=(your password)
CodeXSOAP::Connecting to the server http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/index.php?wsdl...
CodeXSOAP::Connected!
CodeXSOAP::Executing command login...
Logged in as user (your user) , using session string MTAyLSotMTEyMzA4Mjg5My0qLTEyNy4wLjAuMS0qLU51U09BUC8wLjYuOSAoMS4xLjEuMSk=824c9f9010931f7872f4b9826c460ed3
Logged in.
            </programlisting>
        </example>
     </para>
    </para>

    <para>The message you see may vary depending on the configuration of your server.
        If you get an error like "Fatal error: wsdl error: HTTP ERROR: Couldn't open 
        socket connection to server http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN; prior to connect().",
        it means that your computer can't connect to the CodeX server. In this case, 
        you must make sure the address is written correctly and that you can access 
        the server from your computer.
    </para>

  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_CLI.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

