<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="BecomingACodeXCitizen">
    <title>Becoming a CodeX Citizen</title>

    <section id="ClassesOfCitizens">
      <title>Classes of Citizens</title>

      <para>Before we go further into the user registration process it is
      worth reviewing the various types of CodeX citizens. There are basically
      4 of them:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Anonymous Users</emphasis>: when you
          first visit the CodeX site you are typically an anonymous user. To
          make an analogy with DocuShare you are a guest user by default.
          Anonymous users can browse the CodeX site but many of the CodeX
          services or CodeX resources cannot be used or accessed by an
          anonymous user (e.g. source code access is not possible, all the
          monitoring facilities aren&#39;t either, etc.). So we strongly
          advise you to become a registered user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Registered Users</emphasis>: once you
          have created your own account (see below) you can use your
          login/password to authenticate yourself with CodeX. Registered users
          have access to all CodeX projects including source code. And since
          the system knows about you, it enables you to customize your view of
          the system through your Personal Page, monitor Forums, software
          release, receive support request follow-ups, site updates and many
          other useful things.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis>: users who
          are actively working on a CodeX hosted project. To become a project
          member, you must first become a registered user and then ask a
          project administrator to include you in the project members. Most of
          the time project members are part of the project team but are not
          limited to software developers. They can be in charge of the support
          activity, the project documentation or the project management.
          Project members can be granted different rights by the Project
          Administrator according to their role in the team (see <xref
          linkend="ProjectAdministration" /> for more details).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Administrators</emphasis>:
          registered users who create a new CodeX project are elected as the
          first Project Administrators. Project Administrators have full
          rights over their projects except project deletion - a very unusual
          operation - that can only be done by a CodeX Team member. In the
          course of the project life, the initial project administrator can
          grant (or revoke) the status of project administrator to any project
          member.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section id="UserRegistration">
      <title>User Registration</title>

      <para>As suggested above, the first thing to do for a newcomer is to
      create her own account on CodeX. Becoming a registered CodeX user
      doesn&#39;t imply any commitment on your part to host any of your
      software projects on CodeX. It simply gives you more freedom when you
      browse the site and allows CodeX to serve you with personalized
      information.</para>

      <para>Registering on CodeX is quick and easy:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Select the &#34;New User&#34; item at the top of the CodeX
          Main Menu</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Give the following information (all items marked with an
          asterisk are mandatory):</para>

          <substeps>
            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Login Name</emphasis>: lowercase only
              please!</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Password</emphasis>: 6 characters
              minimum and repeat it twice to make sure you didn&#39;t make any
              typo in the first occurrence</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Full Real Name</emphasis>: what&#39;s
              your name again?</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">E-mail Address</emphasis>: your Xerox
              e-mail. E-mail that does not belong to the xerox.com domain (or
              Xerox affiliated domains) is not allowed. Unless you explicitly
              ask for permission, using an external e-mail forwarding address
              is strictly forbidden</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Time Zone</emphasis>: choose the time
              zone you live in. Choosing the correct time zone is really
              important. Behind the scene CodeX stores all time stamps in GMT
              time. Choosing the right time zone allow s CodeX to translate
              all time stamps to your local time on the Web pages.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Site Updates</emphasis>: check this
              box if you want to receive site updates from the CodeX Team.
              This is a low traffic distribution list and we strongly advise
              you to check this box (default). You&#39;ll receive e-mail from
              us about the site maintenance, the important event in the life
              of the site, CodeX presentation/training announcement and the
              CodeX newsletter.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Additional Community Mailings</emphasis>: check
              this box if you want to receive notification about less
              important events. You can safely check this box as well if you
              want because we seldom use it. So we assure you that you
              won&#39;t be overwhelmed with tons of e-mail.</para>
            </step>
          </substeps>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Shortly after you validate the registration form you will
          receive a message in your mailbox which includes a URL. Clicking on
          this URL will bring you to a CodeX form asking for your
          login/password again. If they match then your account is validated
          and you are now logged into the CodeX site.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>This 2-step registration process has been put in place for
      security reasons. Assuming people create their account with an alien
      e-mail address while they have access to the Xerox Intranet, they
      won&#39;t be able to validate their account from the outside because the
      CodeX machine is behind the Xerox firewall. Therefore, an account cannot
      be validated from outside of the Xerox network.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip: What if I loose my password or my login name?</title>

        <para>Don&#39;t Panic and, above all, do not create a new account! Go
        to the CodeX Login Page and click on the [Lost your password?] link.
        You&#39;ll be asked your login name and from that CodeX will send you
        an e-mail message with an embedded URL. Click on this URL and give
        your new password.</para>

        <para>And what if I loose both my login and password? Gee! In this
        case use the search box and, assuming that you gave your full real
        name when you first registered, search for your last name and see if
        you can find your login again in the list of selected users. If so,
        apply the previous procedure. If not then contact us!</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="LoginAndPersonalPage">
      <title>Login and Personal Page</title>

      <para>To log into the CodeX site, go to the CodeX Site at <ulink
      url="http://codex.xerox.com/">http://codex.xerox.com</ulink> and click
      on the &#34;Login&#34; item in the upper part of the CodeX Main Menu. If
      you typed your login and password OK, CodeX presents you with your
      Personal Page (<xref linkend="FigureThePersonalPageOfACodeXUser" />). At
      any point in time you can return to your CodeX Personal Page by
      selecting the &#34;My Personal Page&#34; in the upper part of the CodeX
      Main Menu.</para>

      <para>Your Personal Page is a crossroad from which you can quickly go to
      CodeX workplaces and information spaces. In the upper part of the screen
      you can see bugs and tasks assigned to you in the various projects you
      belong to. In addition the bug section also shows those bugs that you
      have submitted including to foreign projects. By doing so, CodeX allows
      you to follow the evolution of bugs that you have reported and you might
      be impatient to see fixed.</para>

      <para>Another section is dedicated to the Discussion Forums and the
      Software packages that you are currently monitoring. To cancel any of
      the monitored items just click on the trash icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
      format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/trash.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>)
      next to the item label.</para>

      <para>On the right hand side of the screen you&#39;ll see the bookmark
      sections. These are bookmark to your favorite pages in CodeX. Note that
      in many cases CodeX uses URL with enough embedded information to
      bookmark sophisticated items like Software Map browsing, typical search
      in your project Bug or Task database, etc ... Bookmarked items can be
      edited which means that both the title of the bookmark and its
      destination URL can be modified. Finally, the list of projects you
      belong to is listed in the lower right corner. Selecting any if these
      projects brings you to the corresponding Project Summary page.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="AccountMaintenance">
      <title>Account Maintenance</title>

      <para>You provided a certain amount of demographic information to CodeX
      when you first registered on the CodeX site. This and other information
      can be modified at any time by selecting the &#34;Account
      Maintenance&#34; item in the upper part of the Codex Main Menu.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip: Use your canonical e-mail address</title>

        <para>The CodeX site is connected to the Xerox People Directory
        (MS-Exchange database), which has the advantage of showing useful
        information about Xerox users like their physical location,
        organization, phone/fax number, etc. For this feature to work you must
        give CodeX your e-mail address as it appears in the Xerox Directory.
        You can check that the Directory access is working for your account by
        going to your &#34;Account Maintenance&#34; page, select &#34;View my
        developer profile&#34; and then &#34;More from the Xerox
        Directory&#34;.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Most of the items on the &#34;Account Maintenance&#34; page will
      look obvious to you. However, we would like to draw your attention on
      some of them:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Edit My Skills Profile</emphasis>: a
          user can make his resume available on CodeX. The intent here is to
          let people know about you, your technical background and your domain
          of expertise. Very useful to get to know each other.</para>

          <figure id="FigureThePersonalPageOfACodeXUser">
            <title>The Personal Page of a CodeX user</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_mypersonalpage.png" width="13.2cm"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Remember my Login/Password</emphasis>:
          by default your current login session on CodeX is terminated
          whenever you stop your Web browser. When you restart your browser
          and visit CodeX you will be asked for your login/password again. By
          checking this box you ask CodeX to remember about your
          login/password forever or at least until you explicitly select the
          &#34;Logout&#34; item in the CodeX Main Menu. For security reasons
          we do not recommend using this feature unless you are lazy (like me)
          or your desktop environment or Web browser crashes
          <footnote><para>In fact this feature was implemented at the request
          of CodeX users that were having exactly this kind of problem while
          using an operating system that is also used by over 90% of users on
          this planet.</para></footnote> once, twice or (horror) ten times a
          day ...</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">SSH shared keys</emphasis>: this one has
          to do with the Shell Account service. When you are a registered
          user, the CodeX server gives you a personal shell account with the
          same login/password as for the Web interface. To automate the shell
          login you can share a public encryption key with CodeX and use the
          secure shell SSH to access CodeX instantly without having to type a
          password. More on that in <xref linkend="ShellAccount" /></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->