<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
//	Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
      
<chapter id="BugTrackingSystem">
  <title>Bug Tracking System</title>

  <para>The CodeX Bug Tracking System (BTS) is one of the most powerful
    services offered to CodeX hosted projects. It is also one of the most
    popular along with CVS, the default Version Control System offered on
    CodeX. The CodeX BTS has been improved over time based on the constant
    flow of feedback received from CodeX users and we think that it is now on
    the par with many expensive commercial products.</para>

  <para>In improving the CodeX BTS, the CodeX Team also tried to maintain a
    fair balance between sophistication and ease of use. As a consequence, a
    fairly simple and straightforward BTS is configured by default for all new
    hosted projects. Then it is up to the project members to decide how much
    information they want to see attached to a bug and modify their BTS
    configuration accordingly. The BTS Administration module is here to help
    in this respect.</para>

  <section id="CodeXBTSPrinciples">
    <title>CodeX BTS Principles</title>

    <para>Before we enter into the bug submission process by itself
      let&#39;s spend some time on some of the CodeX basic principles. CodeX
      is about source code sharing. It also has as an objective to make it
      easy for anybody in the Corporation to contribute something to software
      development projects. Contributions are diverse: it can be feedback from
      integrators or end-customers, it can be (localized) documentation or
      patches but it can also be bug reports.</para>

    <para>One of the golden rules in a source code-sharing environment is to
      display your code to make your community of users grow and have as large
      as possible a beta-tester community. In order for this community to work
      efficiently they must be free to submit bugs to any project. And this is
      the CodeX philosophy: bug submission is open to all users and it is up
      to the project team (also known as the Core Team) to decide what to do
      with this bug.</para>

    <para>This is a pervasive principle throughout CodeX. Patches and
      documentation contribution follows exactly the same principle: the
      community has the freedom to contribute, the Core Team then decide what
      to do with the contributions.</para>

    <para>The term bug typically refers to a problem, or something that
      doesn&#39;t work as expected. The BTS was developed with this in mind.
      However, many projects have decided to use the BTS for not only
      reporting and managing bugs, but also for reporting and managing
      requests to enhance the code or even requirements management. The BTS
      works nicely in all cases.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="BugSubmission">
    <title>Bug Submission</title>

    <para>To submit a bug report to a given project, first go to the Project
      Summary page (see <xref linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />) and
      then select either the &#34;Bugs&#34; item from the Project Main Menu in
      the upper part of the page or the &#34;Bug Tracking System&#34; item
      from the Public Area.</para>

    <para>From there you enter the project BTS and the first screen you are
      faced with is the bug selection and browsing screen (more about this
      facility in <xref linkend="BugBrowsing" />). For now let&#39;s click on
      the &#34;Submit a Bug&#34; item from the BTS Menu Bar in the upper part
      of the welcome screen (see <xref
				       linkend="FigureASampleBugTrackingSystemWelcomeScreen" />).</para>

    <figure id="BugSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject">
      <title>Bug submission screen from the CodeX project</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugsubmission.png" width="14.5cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><xref linkend="BugSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" /> shows a
      sample submission screen from one of the CodeX hosted projects. Because
      of the BTS high level of customizability no two bug submission screens
      look alike. Depending on the project more or less fields may appear on
      the bug submission form but expect most of them to be close to the one
      shown on <xref linkend="BugSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" />.</para>

    <para>In the example provided on <xref
					   linkend="BugSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" />, the user is asked
      to choose a bug Category, a bug Group, a Priority and an Assignee from a
      series of pull down menus. Then comes a one-line description for the bug
      and a longer piece of text where you can fully characterize the bug.
      When submitting a new bug, make the Bug Summary as explicit as possible.
      Do not use a clueless summary like: &#34;Service X doesn&#39;t work&#34;
      or &#34;Blocking problem in Document Mgr&#34;. Explain the nature of the
      bug. Giving an explicit Bug Summary and Description is immensely helpful
      to the project members in charge of the bug classification and
      characterization. A unique Bug ID is automatically assigned to the
      submitted bug.</para>

    <para>Bug submission forms vary from project to project but they also
      vary according to the citizen class the user belongs to. Depending
      whether you are a project member or an ordinary registered user the bug
      field displayed on the screen may differ. As an example, on <xref
									linkend="BugSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" />, the bug submitter
      using the form is probably a project member because giving access to the
      &#34;Assigned to&#34; field to an ordinary registered user doesn&#39;t
      make much sense. It is very unlikely that users external to the project
      team know enough about the project organization to correctly assign the
      bug. Therefore bug fields shown to project members and registered users
      on the submission form can be configured in the BTS Administration
      module (see <xref linkend="BTSAdministration" />)</para>

    <para>In any case don&#39;t forget to click on the &#34;Submit&#34;
      button when you are finished !</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: make sure your bug hasn&#39;t yet been submitted</title><para>About
      to submit a bug to a CodeX Project? Before you do that, make sure that
      others haven&#39;t yet submitted a similar bug. To do so you can either
      browse the bug database through the Bug Selection and Browsing facility
      or you can use the search box in the CodeX Main Menu and search by
      keywords.</para></tip></para>
  </section>

  <section id="BugBrowsing">
    <title>Bug Browsing</title>

    <para>CodeX provides project members, ordinary registered users and even
      anonymous users with the ability to browse the bug database according to
      a variable set of criteria.</para>

    <section id="SelectionCriteria">
      <title>Selection Criteria</title>

      <para>The upper part of the Bug browsing screen is devoted to the
        selection criteria. <xref
				  linkend="FigureASampleBugTrackingSystemWelcomeScreen" /> shows the
        default set of selection criteria that is available when a new project
        is created. You can select bugs by Category (the module in which the
        bug occurred), Group (nature of the bug like Crash, Documentation
        Typo, ...), Status (e.g. Open, Closed, ...) and Assignee (the person
        in charge of the bug). Other projects may show more, less or different
        selection fields depending on the configuration put in place by the
        project administrators.</para>

      <para>How selection criteria are filled out depend on their field type. The BTS currently has 6 different types of field used as search criteria:</para>

      <section id="BugSelectBoxField">
	<title>Select Box Field</title>

	<para>A select box field can take its value in a set of
	predefined values. If you are using the simple search
	interface only one value can be selected at a time. If you
	want to select multiple values at once use the Advanced Search
	facility.</para>

	<para>There might be 2 specific values in the list of choices:
	'Any' matches any value in the list and 'None' matches the
	items where no value has been assigned yet</para>
      </section>

      <section id="BugTextField">
	<title>Text Field</title> <para>A Text field can contain any
	kind of text . There are two ways to query an text
	field:</para>


	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Keyword
	    search</emphasis>: you can type a series of space
	    separated keywords that will ALL be searched for in the
	    text field (including as subtring in
	    words)</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline"></emphasis>Regular
	    expression: You can also specify a <ulink
	    url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	    Extended Regular Expression</ulink> as a matching criteria
	    (mind the surrounding /.../ !)</para>

	    <para>Examples:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para>/^[Aa]ddition/ : matches any text field starting
		with either 'addition'or 'Addition'</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>/foo|bar|dim/ : matches text fields containing the string 'foo', 'bar' or 'dim'</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="BugDateField">
	<title>Date Field</title>

	<para>A date criteria follows the following pattern:
	YYYY-MM-DD where YYYY is the year number, MM is the month
	number and DD is the day number.</para>

	<para>Examples: 1999-03-21 is March 21st, 1999, 2002-12-05 is
	Dec 5th, 2002. </para>

      </section>

      <section id="BugIntegerField">
	<title>Integer Field</title>

	<para>An integer field can take positive or (possibly)
	negative values and has no decimal part.</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1, +2, -100&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an integer field. Here
	are the values you can specify in a integer query field:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Integer</emphasis>: if you type a single integer the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 610)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &ge; or &le; followed by an integer
	    the search will look for integer values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120 , &lt; -30)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the 'integer1-integer2' notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. 800 - 900 for integers
	  between 800 and 900, -45 - 12 for integers between -45 and
	  +12)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be used as a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all integer
	  values starting with a '4', ending with an '8' with any
	  number of digits in between.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="BugFloatingPointNumberField">
	<title>Floating Point Number Field</title><para>A floating
	point number field can take positive or (possibly) negative
	values, may have a decimal part or use the exponential
	notation for large values.. .</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1.23, -2.456, 122.45E+12&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an floating point number
	field. Here are the values you can specify in such a
	field:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Number</emphasis>: if you type a single number the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 2.35)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &ge; or &le; followed by a number
	    the search will look for all values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120.3 , &lt; -3.3456E-2)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the 'number1-number2' notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. -1.2 - 4.5 for integers greater than or equal to -1.2 and lesser than or equal to 4.5)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be usedas a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all integer
	  values starting with a '4', ending with an '8' with any
	  number of characters in between including the decimal point.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="BugQueries">
      <title>Favorites and Predefined Bug Queries</title>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: save and re-use your bug database query</title><para>If
        you often run the same bug database query with the same set of
        selection criteria, it is probably a good idea to save this query for
        later re-use. To do this: select the appropriate bug report, then
        choose your search criteria, click on the &#34;Browse&#34; button to
        run the query. Finally click on the &#34;Bookmark this Page&#34; item
        in the CodeX Main Menu. A new bookmark will show up in your Personal
        Page. A click on this bookmark will run the exact same query again.</para></tip></para>

      <para>Your favorite bug queries can be saved via the CodeX
      bookmark mechanism as explained in the Tip box but there are
      also shortcuts in the Bug Menu Bar for the most common
      queries. They are:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Bugs</emphasis>: display all the
            bugs that are not yet closed for this project.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">My Bugs</emphasis>: display the bugs
            assigned to you (based on the CodeX account you are currently
            using)</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Also notice that CodeX always keeps track of the last ran bug
        query. Next time you enter the bug welcome screen, CodeX will use the
        same set of selection criteria in the selection boxes and update the
        bug report accordingly.</para>

      <section id="AdvancedSearchMode">
	<title>Advanced Search Mode</title>

	<para>At any time during the search phase, you can toggle the search
          mode from Simple to Advanced and vice-versa (see the Advanced Search
          link). The Advance Search mode allows you to select multiple values
          for each selection criteria. Using this mode you could search for
          both open and suspended bugs assigned to project members A and B.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="BugSearchResults">
      <title>Bug Search Results</title> 
      
      <para>After you have submitted the bug selection, CodeX runs a
      query against the bug database, select the matching bugs and
      displays them right below the selection criteria. Columns
      displayed in the bug list are entirely configurable by the
      project team (see <xref linkend="BugReports" />). Therefore, the
      bug browsing screen might look completely different from the one
      shown in <xref
      linkend="FigureASampleBugTrackingSystemWelcomeScreen" />.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleBugTrackingSystemWelcomeScreen">
	<title>A sample Bug Tracking System welcome screen (bug browsing)</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Bug priority is color coded, red being the highest
      priority and gray the lowest (see Priority color coding at the
      bottom of the screen).  Finally, bugs are listed by chunks of N
      bugs where N is user-definable. If more than N bugs are
      retrieved from the bug database you are invited to click on the
      navigation bar to display the next or previous chunk of
      bugs.</para>

      <para>To access a given bug from the bug list, simply click on
      the corresponding &#34;Bug ID&#34; number listed in the first
      column of the bug list.</para>

      <section id="BugListSorting">
	<title>Bug List Sorting</title>

	<para>By default, bugs are sorted by Bug ID which happens to
	be the chronological order in which bugs have been
	submitted.</para>

	<para>The bug list can be sorted by any of the columns
	displayed on the screen by clicking on the column
	heading. Clicking twice on the same heading reverses the sort
	order from ascending to descending and vice-versa.  The
	sorting direction is shown by a small up or down arrow next to
	the sort criteria right above the bug list. One exception to
	this rule is for sorting by Priority. Priority being shown as
	such but as a color code, there is a special link at the
	bottom of the screen to sort the bug list by Priority.</para>

	<para>For more sophisticated processing you can also activate
	the multi-column sort.  In this mode sort criteria cumulates
	as you click on column headings.  So you can for instance
	click 'Severity' first and 'Assigned To' second to see who in
	the team is assigned critical bugs and how many.At any point
	in the multi-column sort process, a click on one of the sort
	criteria displayed in the list (criteria 1 > criteria 2 >
	criteria 3...)  will bring you backward in the sort criteria
	list. Using this feature you can easily test various sorting
	strategies.</para>

	<note><para>Note:Sorting criteria, like selection criteria,
	are also saved into your preferences and the same sorting
	criterion is re-used in subsequent bug queries.</para></note>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: keep an eye on unassigned
	bugs</title><para>In most cases when a bug is submitted by a
	person external to the project team, the bug assignee is given
	the value &#34;None&#34;. In other words the bug has been
	submitted but it is awaiting an assignment by the project
	member in charge of the bug dispatch. Since nobody is in
	charge, the bug can be completely overlooked by the project
	team. Two solutions can help with this problem: 1) Use a an
	e-mail address where all new submissions are sent (see <xref
	linkend="BugReportManagement" />) and/or 2) Assign somebody in
	the team the responsibility to run a bug query once or twice a
	day to collect the bugs which Assignee field is &#34;None&#34;
	and give him/her the responsibility to assign the
	bugs.</para></tip></para>

      </section>


      <section id="PrinterFriendlyVersion">
	<title>Printer Friendly Version</title>

	<para>At any point in the process of browsing the bug database
	you can click on the &#34;Printer Version&#34; link to display
	a simplified and non-decorated bug list that will print
	nicely. For better readability we strongly advise you to print
	the bug list in landscape format.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="BugReports">
	<title>Bug Reports</title>

	<para>Bug reports allows for the definition of a specific
	layout of the bug browsing screen where one can choose the
	selection criteria and the columns used in the bug matching
	list. Depending on the project, users may enjoy the ability to
	choose from several bug reports by using the upper pull-down
	menu of the bug browsing screen. If no project or user
	specific bug report has been defined, the CodeX
	&#39;Default&#39; report is the only one available.</para>

	<para>Project members and project administrators can define
	their own bug report either for personal use or for
	project-wide use. See <xref linkend="BugReportManagement" />
	for more details on managing bug reports.</para>	
      </section>

    </section>
   
  </section>
  
  <section id="BugUpdate">
    <title>Bug Update</title>

    <para>Once you have selected a given bug from the bug report generated
      by the Bug Browsing module a new screen appears showing all of the bug
      details. If you are a member of the project the bug belongs to, the
      detailed view is made of text fields and menus that you can update with
      new values. On the other hand, if you are an anonymous user or a
      registered user that does not belong to the project team, all the fields
      will appear as immutable text. Non-project members cannot edit any of
      the bug fields. They can only submit a follow-up comment to a bug.</para>

    <para>All the screen shots used in this section assume that the CodeX
      user is part of the project team. For non-project members the screen
      layout is basically the same but the information shown on the screen
      cannot be changed.</para>

    <para>The Bug Update screen is divided in several parts: <emphasis role="bold">Headers,
      Comments, CC List, Bug Attachments, Dependencies and History.</emphasis></para>

    <section id="BugHeaders">
      <title>Headers</title>

      <para>This is where you&#39;ll find all the bug fields associated with
        a bug description. As shown on <xref
					     linkend="FigureHeaderOfBugUpdateScreen" />, many of these fields are
        assigned a set of predefined values (Status, Category, Resolution)
        while some others have a number format (Effort) or a free text format
        (Summary). The set of fields used in your project BTS, as well as the
        related set of predefined values can be configured by project members
        with appropriate permissions. (see <xref linkend="BTSAdministration" />
        for more details on the BTS configuration)</para>

      <figure id="FigureHeaderOfBugUpdateScreen">
	<title>Header of Bug Update screen (bug fields)</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugupdateheader.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="BugComments">
      <title>Comments</title>

      <para>As many follow-up comments as needed can be attached to any
        given bug. Follow-up comments are free text fields where virtually any
        kind of information or comment can be typed in. The &#34;Original
        Submission&#34; field filled out by the bug submitter can actually be
        considered as the first follow-up comment in a bug life.</para>

      <para>Follow-up comments have two interesting extensions:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Canned Response</emphasis>: It is not
            infrequent to see the project members in charge of the bug
            classification and dispatch process to post the same follow-up
            comments again and again. Typical examples of repeatedly posted
            comments are: a thank you message to the originator, a request for
            the originator to provide commonly missing information like
            version numbers or type of machine used, etc. Rather than typing
            the same comments all the time, CodeX allows project members to
            create a predefined set of responses. After these canned responses
            have been defined, posting a follow-up comment is just a matter of
            selecting the appropriate response from the pull down menu and
            submitting the changes. Defining a new Canned Response can be done
            on the fly from the bug submission form by clicking on the
            &#34;define a new Canned Response&#34; link</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Comment Types</emphasis>: In order to
            avoid the exponential growth of new bug fields to store all sorts
            of free text information, CodeX offers an interesting mechanism
            called Comment Types. The project team has the ability to define a
            list of labels that can then be used to categorize the nature of a
            follow-up comment. This is a very helpful feature to characterize
            the nature of the information contained in a follow-up comment and
            to quickly identify these comments in the long list of follow-up
            comments. Typical examples of such comment types are
            &#34;Workaround&#34; for a comment where you explain how to work
            around a bug, &#34;Impacted Files&#34; to give the list of source
            files impacted by the bug resolution, &#34;Test case&#34; to
            document how to test the code in the future to make sure that this
            case will be tested in the future test suite, etc. Comment types
            are defined in the Bug Administration module (see <xref
								    linkend="BTSAdministration" />)</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <figure id="FigureFollowupCommentsAttachedToABug">
	<title>Follow-up comments attached to a bug</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugupdatecomments.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
    </section>

    <section id="BugCCList">
      <title>CC List</title>

      <para>As explained later in this chapter (see <xref
      linkend="BugEmailNotification" />) the CodeX BTS offers a powerful
      email notification system for those users who, at some point,
      were involved in the life of the bug whether as a submitter, an
      assignee or as a person who posted a follow-up comment
      (commenter).</para>

      <para>Sometimes it is however useful to involve other people in
      the email notification process even if they did not play an
      explicit role in the bug so far. For instance, you may want a QA
      contact or the originator of the bug when different from the
      submitter to receive a carbon-copy (CC) of the email
      notifications. This is precisely what the CC List is intended
      for. Inserting CC names in the CC list will allow these people
      to receive bug updates for this specific bug.</para>

      <section id="BugCCNames">
        <title>CC Names</title>

        <para>The CC names can be either email addresses or a
        CodeX login name if the user has a CodeX account.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX login name</emphasis>:
            when the person you want involve in the notification
            process has a CodeX account use it in place of her email
            address. Using the CodeX login name give to the recipient
            the ability to customize the kind of bug update events she
            wants to receive. For more information on how to customize
            notification preferences for a given project see <xref
            linkend="BugEmailNotificationSettings" />.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Email Address</emphasis>:
            there is no restriction on the type of email address you
            can type. It can either individuals or mailing list - see
            <xref linkend="MailingLists" />. Unlike CC names entered
            as login names, CC names added in the form of email
            addresses have no customization capabilities and 
            receive all bug updates.</para>
          </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="BugAddingDeletingCCNames">
        <title>Adding and Deleting CC Names</title>

        <para>Several CC names can be added at once by separating them
        with commas in the 'Add CC' field. Using the comment field,
        one can also explain why these CC names were added and/or who
        they are.</para>

        <para>CC names addition and deletion is subject to a number of
        permission rules:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Adding a CC name: Anonymous users cannot add CC
            names. Any other CodeX user who is logged in can add CC
            names and the CC list will clearly show who added this
            entry and when.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Deleting a CC name: users with Bug Administrator
            permissions in a given project (see <xref
            linkend="UserPermissions" />) can delete any entry in
            the CC list for any bug of this project. All other users
            can delete CC entries that were either added by themselves
            or entries where the CC name matches their own name or
            email address in any CodeX projects. In other words a
            CodeX user has the right to undo what she has done or
            remove herself from a CC list in any project. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="BugAttachments">
      <title>Bug Attachments</title>

      <para>In addition to comments, the CodeX Bug Tracking System
      allows you to attach virtually any piece of information to a bug
      in the form of a file. Typical examples of bug attachments are
      application screen shots in PNG, GIF, JPEG or whatever image
      format is appropriate; it can also be core dumps, a binary image
      of program that crashed or even a simple text file showing a
      stack trace or an error message.</para>

      <para>Bug attachments can be of any type (image, video, sound,
      text, binary&hellip;) and a comment field can be optionally used
      to annotate the attachment. The maximum size of a file is 512
      KByte.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="BugDependencies">
      <title>Bug Dependencies</title>

      <para>The next section on the bug update screen deals with bug
      dependencies (see <xref linkend="FigureBugDependencies"
      />). CodeX users have the ability to establish a dependency link
      from a bug to one or several other bugs or from a bug to one or
      several other tasks of the same project.</para>

      <para>The CodeX system does not impose any semantic on the
      nature of these dependency links. However the following meanings
      are commonly accepted and used by the CodeX community for
      dependency links:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>When a bug is closed with Resolution field set to
            &#34;Duplicate&#34; then a bug-to-bug dependency for this bug
            means the bugs it depends on is considered as the &#34;master&#34;
            bug by the project members. All other bug submissions that are
            actually a duplicate of this master will be made dependent on the
            master bug (probably the first one that was submitted)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>In all other cases a bug-to-bug dependency link means that a
            bug cannot be resolved as long as the bug it depends on is not
            resolved itself.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>A bug-to-task dependency means that a task has been created
            to cover or encompass the work required to resolve the bug.
            Creating a task to fix a bug generally happens when the bug fix
            implies a major rework or because the work that is being done in
            the related task will resolve the bug as a side effect.</para>

	  <figure id="FigureBugDependencies">
	    <title>Bug Dependencies</title>

	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata format="PNG"
			   fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugupdatedependencies.png" width="15.3cm" />
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To create a bug-to-bug or task-to-task dependency, click on the
        corresponding bugs and tasks listed in the &#34;Dependent on Bug&#34;
        and &#34;Dependent on Task&#34; list boxes. To delete a bug or task
        dependency simply unselect the appropriate bug or task from the same
        list boxes and validate the changes by clicking on the &#34;Submit
        Changes&#34; button either at the top or at the bottom of the screen</para>

      <para>The dependency section shows the bug-to-bug dependencies in both
        ways (cross-reference): it shows the list of bug(s) the displayed bug
        depends on but also the list of bugs that depend upon the displayed
        bug.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="BugHistory">
      <title>Bug History</title>

      <para>The last part of the bug update screen is devoted to bug state
        history (see <xref linkend="FigureBugHistory" />). Thanks to this
        section you can review the entire history of a bug. The bug history
        keeps track of all the changes that occurred on all bug fields since
        the bug creation.</para>

      <para>The bug history shows what fields changed, what was the old
        value before the change took place, who changed it and when. Since the
        bug history only shows the old value of a bug field it requires a bit
        of exercise to determine what the new value was right after the change
        took place. Let&#39;s take an example: assuming that the current value
        of the Priority field for the bug displayed in <xref
							     linkend="FigureBugHistory" /> is currently &#34;9-Major&#34;, by
        reading the history list from the top you can say that the current
        value of 9 was given on March 15th, 2001 at 9am by L. Julliard and the
        previous Priority level was &#34;3&#34;. Looking further down in the
        history list, the value &#34;3&#34; was given to the Priority field on
        March 15th, 2001 at 5:35am and before that date it was at level
        &#34;5&#34;. And since there is no other Priority item in the history
        list you can safely assume that &#34;5&#34; was the Priority value
        assigned to the bug when it was first created.</para>

      <figure id="FigureBugHistory">
	<title>Bug History</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bughistory.png" width="13.5cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="BugCreateTask">
      <title>Deriving a New Task from a Bug</title>

      <para>When a bug submitted to a project happens to be a big work
      to fix it is not unusual to create a new task in the CodeX Task
      Manager to plan and track this work.</para>

      <para>CodeX makes it very easy to derive a new task from an
      existing bug. Just click on the 'Create Task' item in the CodeX
      BTS menu bar at the top of the screen. A new task form will show
      up with  some fields  pre-filled with values derived from
      the bug form. You can then modify the proposed values, and
      validate the new task.</para>
    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section id="BugEmailNotification">
    <title>E-mail Notification</title>

    <para>The CodeX BTS is equipped with a powerful and flexible
    e-mail notification system. Unless otherwise instructed by the
    project administrators or the users themselves, the e-mail
    notification system follows simple default rules. Whenever a bug
    is created or updated - whether with an additional follow-up
    comment, a new attachment or a change in any of the bug fields -
    an e-mail message is sent to the following actors:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
	<para>The bug submitter (the person who initially submitted the bug)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The bug assignee (the project member to whom the bug is
          currently assigned)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The people on the CC list if any (the persons who are
	listed in the CC list of a given bug)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Beside these simple rules, the Administration module of the
    CodeX BTS allows CodeX users to customize the email notification
    process. For further information see <xref
    linkend="BugEmailNotificationSettings" />). </para>

    <para>The e-mail message generated by the BTS first shows the most
    recent changes that occurred on the bug if this is a bug update. It
    is then followed by a complete snapshot of the bug. Web pointers
    are also included in the message to quickly and easily access the
    bug form on CodeX.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="BugReporting">
    <title>Bug reporting</title>

    <para>As explained earlier in this document (<xref
						       linkend="ProjectDataExport" />), CodeX can export your project data
      outside of the CodeX system for re-use in another tool or document.
      However for simple statistics, you can also use the Bug Reporting
      module. This function can be accessed from the Bug Menu Bar via the item
      &#34;Reporting&#34;.</para>

    <figure id="FigureValueDistributionOfTheBugCategoryFieldForTheCodeXProject">
      <title>Value distribution of the Bug Category field for the CodeX
        project</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugreporting.png" width="13cm"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Bug reporting mechanism allows you to see how your project
      bugs (open only or all of them) are distributed across the set of
      predefined values used in the various pull-down menu fields. For
      instance you might want to see how your bugs are distributed across the
      possible status, category or resolution values (see <xref
								linkend="FigureValueDistributionOfTheBugCategoryFieldForTheCodeXProject" />
      for an example of how the bugs of the CodeX project are distributed
      across the various CodeX modules also known as the Bug Category field).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="BTSAdministration">
    <title>BTS Administration</title>

    <para>As we went through the description of the CodeX BTS features, we
      referred several times to the flexibility of this system and how easy it
      is to customize your own project Bug Tracking System. The BTS
      Administration is accessible by clicking on the item &#34;Admin&#34; in
      the Bug Menu bar.</para>

    <para>Depending on your level of permissions you'll be given
    access to various parts of the BTS Administration module. Access
    permissions are summarized in the table below:</para>


       <table frame="all">
          <title>BTS Administration Access Levels</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="200pt" />

            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="250pt"  />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>BTS Administration Sub-modules</entry>
                <entry>Access Permission</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="BugFieldUsageManagement">Field Usage Management</link></entry>
                <entry>Only available to project administrators and
                project members with Bug Admin. permission on the
                BTS.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link linkend="BugFieldValuesManagement">Field Values Management</link></entry>
                <entry>Same as above.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link linkend="BugReports">Bug Reports</link></entry>

	        <entry>Only Project administrators can define project
	        wide bug reports that will be available to
	        all users. All other CodeX users (except anonymous
	        users) can define personal bug reports.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link linkend="BugEmailNotificationSettings">Email Notification Settings</link></entry>

	        <entry>Only Project administrators can add email
	        addresses in the global email notification
	        field. Project members must at least have Bug
	        Tech. permission on the BTS to watch bugs of other
	        team members. Any registered CodeX user can customize
	        her notification preferences.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><link linkend="BugOtherConfigurationSettings">Other Configuration Settings</link></entry>

	        <entry>For project administrators and project members
	        with Bug Admin. permission on the BTS</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>



    <section id="BugFieldUsageManagement">
      <title>Field Usage Management</title>

      <para>When a project is first created, its bug tracking system
      comes pre-configured with a set of bug fields
      that are probably enough for the majority of projects hosted on
      CodeX. However CodeX has a much longer list of bug fields
      available for use in your own project BTS. Conversely you can
      also decide that the default BTS comes with too many fields and
      you can remove fields from your project BTS and make it even
      simpler.</para>

      <para>The CodeX Bug Tracker offers a list of about 30 fields
      that you can choose from to customize your project BTS. They are
      called 'Standard Fields'. Although the list of standard fields
      is quite rich, there might still be cases when one would like to
      use other fields in their own bug tracker. Should this happen,
      there are two ways to solve the problem:</para>

      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Ask the Site
	Administrator</emphasis>: if you think that the missing field
	is not specific to your project and should be part of a good
	bug tracking system, then we urge you to contact the CodeX
	Site Administrators and ask them to create the new field. By
	doing so CodeX will over time offer a richer and more
	pertinent set of standard fields.</para>
	</step>
	
	<step>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Use the Custom
	Fields</emphasis>: in addition to the list of standard fields,
	CodeX offers 'Custom fields'. These are generic fields
	(either text, date or select box fields) that can be entirely
	customized by the project team. If the fields you are thinking
	of adding are really specific to your project then you should
	definitely use the custom fields.</para>
	</step>
      </procedure>


      <section id="BugFieldList">
	<title>Bug Field List</title>

	<para>To decide what field to use and what field not to use
	select the item &#34;Manage Field Usage&#34; on the welcome
	page of the BTS Administration module. The Field Usage screen
	(<xref linkend="FigureBugFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject"
	/>) shows you the full list of bug fields available on
	CodeX. The list is divided in 3 parts:</para>

	<procedure>
	  <step>
	    <para>the list of bug fields currently used by this
	specific project</para>
	  </step>
	  
	  <step>
	    <para>the list of unused standard fields</para>
	  </step>
	  
	  <step>
	    <para>the list of unused custom fields</para>
	  </step>
	</procedure>


	<para>Information displayed on the Bug Field list page are as follows:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>: the
	    name of the field.  To change the Status of a field
	    (Used/Unused) as well as other parameters simply click on
	    the field name.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis>:bug fields can be of several types:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Select
		Box</emphasis>: this field will take its value from a
		predefined list of values that can be defined by the
		Project Adminstrator</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Text Field</emphasis>
		and <emphasis role="underline">Text Area</emphasis>:
		allows the user to enter free text either in a
		one-line text field or in a multi-line text
		area.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Date Field</emphasis>:
		fields that only accept ISO formatted dates (YYYY-MM-DD)</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	    </itemizedlist>

	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Important
	    Remark</emphasis>: Some fields appear twice in the
	    list. Although they have the same name they actually come
	    with a different type. Choose the type that best suits
	    your needs: predefined values ('Select Box') or free text
	    ('Text Field').</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on Screen</emphasis>: the
	    rank number allows you to place the field with respect to
	    the others both in the bug submission form and in the bug
	    update form. The fields with smaller values will appear
	    first on the screen. The rank values doesn't have to be
	    consecutive values. It is a good idea to use values like
	    10,20,30,... so that it is easy for you to insert new
	    fields in the future without having to renumber all the
	    fields.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis>:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">System</emphasis>:
		these fields have a limited level of
		customization. System fields of type 'Select Box' have
		a fixed number of values defined globally for the
		entire site. You can only change the label and the
		rank of these existing values but you can't create any
		new one.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Project</emphasis>:
		these fields are fully customizable. You can
		create/delete field values, make it appear or not on
		the bug forms, etc.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Required</emphasis>: required fields are always in use. They are often fields considered vital for a Bug Tracking System  like Bug ID, bug submitter,etc.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Used</emphasis>: the field is used by your project.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Unused</emphasis>: the field is not used by your project.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>


	<figure id="FigureBugFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject">
	  <title>Field Usage screen of a CodeX hosted project</title>

	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugfieldusage.png" width="15.3cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>


      <section id="StandardBugFields">
	<title>Standard Bug Fields</title>

	<para>Standard bug fields are common to all CodeX
	projects. You can customize them to a certain extent but not
	all standard fields have the same degree of
	customizablity. For instance, fields with status
	&#34;Required&#34; are mandatory fields (e.g. Priority,
	Resolution, ...). You cannot remove them from the list of used
	fields but you can still tune some of their settings.</para>

	<para>To change the status of a field from used to unused (or
	vice-versa) and tune the field settings click on the
	corresponding field label and set the bug field parameters as
	you wish.</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on screen</emphasis>: this
            arbitrary number allows you to define the position of this field
            on the screen relative to other fields. The fields with smaller
            numbers are displayed first. This placement information has an
            impact on the bug fields showing on the bug submission form, the
            bug selection criteria and the bug report columns.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Used or Unused.
            Changing the status in either direction can be done at any time in
            the life of the project without negative impact on the existing
            set of bugs. Newly used bug fields will appear with value
            &#34;None&#34; in old bugs and bug fields becoming unused will
            simply be hidden from the user view but are still present in the
            bug database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Display this field
	    ...</emphasis>: you can decide if you want to see this
	    field to appear on the bug submission form for project
	    members and non project members. In general non project
	    members are given access to restricted set of fields when
	    they submit a bug. As an example they are not supposed to
	    know how critical a bug is ('Severity' field), how to
	    prioritize it ('Priority' field) (or whom a bug should be
	    assigned to ('Assigned To' field). Therefore these fields
	    should probably not appear on non project members submission
	    form.</para>

	    <para>Finally, some fields have fixed display settings and
	    they always or never appear on the submission form. For
	    instance the 'Bug ID' field never appears on the bug
	    submission form because by definition a bug not yet
	    submitted has no Bug ID.</para>
	    
	    <figure id="FigureBugFieldUsageSettings">
	      <title>Bug field usage settings</title>
	      
	      <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata format="PNG"
			   fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugfieldusagesettings.png" width="8cm" />
		</imageobject>
	      </mediaobject>
	    </figure>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="CustomBugFields">
	<title>Custom Bug Fields</title>

	<para>Custom fields are generic fields that go one step beyond
	in terms of flexibility. They allow for a full customization
	including a name change. When a project is first created it
	comes with the following list of unused custom fields:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>10 Text Fields: text fields are one line text fields</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>10 Text Areas: text areas are multi-line text
	  fields</para>
	  </listitem> 

	  <listitem>
	    <para>10 Select Boxes: select boxes are fields which
	  possible value is chosen from a list of user definable values</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>5 Date Fields: fields accepting ISO formatted dates (YYYY-MM-DD).</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Compared to standard bug fields (see <xref
	linkend="StandardBugFields" />), custom field settings offer
	additional customization capabilities:</para>
      
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>:
	  define the name of the new custom field.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field size</emphasis>: for
	    one-line text fields you can define the size (in
	    characters) the field will have on the screen as well as
	    the maximum number of characters that can be typed in this
	    field. For text areas (multi-line fields) it's the number
	    of rows and columns (in characters) that the field will
	    show on the screen when displayed. </para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Allow Empty Value</emphasis>:
	    determines whether leaving the field blank in the bug form
	    is allowed or not. If unchecked the bug tracker won't
	    accept the bug form unless the field is given a
	    value.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Keep Change
	    History</emphasis>: determines whether changes made to
	    this field will be kept in the bug history (see <xref
	    linkend="BugHistory" /> )</para></listitem>
 	</itemizedlist>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: Use Standard Fields
	First!</title><para>At any time in the life of your project
	you can enrich your bug tracking system with new custom
	fields. However before you decide to use a custom field make
	sure that there isn't a standard field that already plays the
	same role. By using standard fields whenever possible, you'll
	contribute to keep the global CodeX environment consistent and
	make it easier for visitors, contributors or new team members
	to switch from project to another.</para></tip></para>
	
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="BugFieldValuesManagement">
      <title>Field Values Management</title>

      <para>Once the list of bug fields to be used in your project BTS
      has been defined, the next step is to define a set of predefined
      values for the fields of type 'Select Box'. These values will
      show up in the pull-down menus when a bug is submitted or
      updated.</para>

      <section id="BugFieldValuesFieldList">
	<title>Bug Fields with Customizable Values</title>

	<para>To configure values assigned to your used bug fields
	select the item &#34;Manage Field Values&#34; on the welcome
	page of the Bug Administration or select the &#34;Field
	Values&#34; item from the Bug Administration menu bar at the
	top of the screen.</para>

	<figure id="FigureBugFieldListWithUserDefinableValues">
	  <title>Bug field list  with user definable values</title>

	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugfieldvaluesmgt.png" width="13cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>The list of used (and required) fields which type is a
	pull-down menu will appear on the screen. Other field types
	like number fields or text fields (e.g.  Effort or Summary) do
	not appear in this list because setting a list of predefined
	values for these field types doesn&#39;t make any sense.  In
	addition you&#39;ll always see required bug fields like
	&#34;Comment Type&#34; and &#34;Canned Response&#34; items in
	the list. (See <xref linkend="FigureBugFieldListWithUserDefinableValues"/>)
        </para>

	<para>Information displayed on this page are as follows:</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>: the
	    name of the field. Click on this name to view the list of
	    values for this field.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: what
	    this field is about</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis>:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">System</emphasis>:
		these fields have a limited level of
		customization. System fields of type 'Select Box' have
		a fixed number of values defined globally for the
		entire site. You can only change the label of system
		defined values but you cannot create new ones.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Project</emphasis>:
		these fields are fully customizable. You can create
		new field values as well as hide/unhide existing
		ones.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>


      <section id="BugBrowsingBugFieldValues">
	<title>Browsing Bug Field Values</title>

	<para>A click on any of the bug fields with user-definable
	values (see <xref linkend="BugFieldValuesFieldList" />) will
	bring you to the list of existing values for this field (see <xref
	linkend="FigureListOfValuesForBugFieldStatus" />).</para>

	<para>The table of values shows tha following inormation:</para>


	<itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis> (optional): the ID
	    column is only shown for fields which have
	    a 'System' scope. For this type of field the ID often
	    carry a semantic meaning and if you redefine the label of
	    a value associated with a given ID it is important
	    that you know about the ID.</para>

	    <para>As an example the 'Severity' field has 9 possible
	    values and the bugs with the highest ID are always
	    considered as the most critical bug by the system. So it
	    would be a bad idea to redefine the value label for ID 9
	    to something like 'Very Minor' :-) but it is ok to
	    redefine it as 'Fatal'</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Value Label</emphasis>: text
	    label of the value as shown in the select box. Click on
	    this label to modify the value settings (see <xref
	    linkend="BugUpdatingaBugFieldValue" />)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>:
	    meaning of the value</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank</emphasis>: defines the
	    order of the field values in the select box. The smaller
	    values appear first in the select box.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Active</emphasis>:
		the value is currently visible in the pull-down menus
		and can be assigned to the corresponding bug
		field.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Hidden</emphasis>:
		the value is currently not visible in the pull-down
		menu. However if this value was used in the past by
		any of your project bugs, it will continue to show up
		OK for this specific bug.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Permanent</emphasis>:
		this value has been defined for the entire CodeX
		system and it cannot be hidden.  It is active for all
		CodeX projects and will remain as is forever.  Well,
		at least until the CodeX Team decides otherwise</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
 
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para><xref linkend="FigureListOfValuesForBugFieldStatus" />
	shows the list of available values for the Status bug
	field. The status field was chosen on purpose. Not only is the
	Status field a required field of the CodeX BTS, but it also
	comes with set of predefined values that are available to all
	CodeX projects. By default only &#34;Open&#34; and
	&#34;Closed&#34; values are active (and permanent in this
	case) but there is a series of 7 other values (Accepted,
	Analyzed, etc.)  that you can choose from if you want to have
	a finer grain Status field.</para>

	<para>Of course you are free to add your own values to the
	Status field. This is actually what has been done for this
	particular project: the Status value &#34;Assigned&#34; as
	been added to the list of active values. However, in order to
	keep a certain harmony from one CodeX project to another, we
	highly recommend that you use the list of predefined status
	values as much as you can before creating new ones.</para>

	<figure id="FigureListOfValuesForBugFieldStatus">
	  <title>List of values for the 'Status' bug field</title>
	  
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugfieldvalues.png" width="13cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section id="BugCreatingaBugFieldValue">
	<title>Creating a Bug Field Value</title>
	
	<para>To add a value use the form right below the list of
	field values (not shown on <xref
	linkend="FigureBugFieldListWithUserDefinableValues" />).</para>

      </section>

      <section id="BugBindingFieldToValueList">
	<title>Binding a Field to a List of Values</title>
	
	<para>Not only does the CodeX BTS allows you to create a list
	of values for a select box but it also offers the ability to
	associate a select box with a list of predefined values that
	is actually dynamically generated by the CodeX system. A
	typical example of this is when one would like to create a new
	select box showing the list of project members. You could also
	create it manually but such a list would be tedious to create
	and maintain.</para>

	<para> So instead of creating your own set of values you can
	bind a select box to such a list of predefined values that
	CodeX will keep current for you. Note that if you decide to
	bind a select box to a list of dynamically generatedc values
	you can no longer create your own values. The following lists
	are currently available (others may be added in the
	future):</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis> :
	    list of people belonging to the project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Administrators</emphasis> :
	    project members who have been granted the status of
	    project administrators.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug Technicians</emphasis>: project
	    members who have been granted the permission to process
	    bugs (see <xref linkend="UserPermissions" /> for more
	    information on user permissions).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug Submitters</emphasis>: the full list
	    of people who once submitted a bug to the
	    project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="BugUpdatingaBugFieldValue">
	<title>Updating a Bug Field Value</title>
	
	<para>From the screen showing the list of values for a given field (see <xref
	linkend="FigureBugFieldListWithUserDefinableValues" />) screen you can change the properties of a bug field value:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis>: change the value
            itself. The value typed here will appear as is in the pull-down
            menu.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank</emphasis>: a number that allows
            you to specify where you want this value to appear in the list of
            all active values. The values with smaller rank are displayed
            first. When the &#34;None&#34; value is available for this bug
            field it has a rank number of 10. This number is deliberately
            small because by convention &#34;None&#34; always appear at the
            top of the pull-down menu. Please be a good CodeX citizen and
            choose rank numbers higher than 10 for your own values.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Active or Hidden.
            As explained above going from one to the other in the course of
            the project life has no negative impact on the bug database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: says a bit
            more about the meaning of this value.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureUpdatingABugFieldValue">
	  <title>Setting a Bug field value</title>
	  
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugfieldvalueupdate.png" width="12cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: Leave some space between rank
	numbers</title><para>Whether for Fields or Field Values
	remember to use large numbers (in the hundreds or the
	thousands like 100, 200, 300,..) when you create new
	values. By doing so you&#39;ll make your life easier if you
	ever want to insert new values in between existing ones in the
	future. And avoid a tedious renumbering of the existing
	items.</para></tip></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="BugReportManagement">
      <title>Bug Report Management</title>

      <para>Knowing that project administrators, project members and other
        CodeX users may have different needs in searching the project bug
        database, CodeX offers the ability to define project or user specific
        bug reports.</para>

      <para>Choosing a bug report consists in deciding what bug fields you
        want to use as search criteria and what fields you want to see in the
        bug table where the results of the search are displayed. You can also
        define the order in which the search criteria and the column in the
        result table will appear on the screen.</para>

      <para>Project Administrators have the ability to define bug reports
        that will be usable by all project members whereas non-project
        administrators can only define reports for their personal use.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Bug Reports specifies the report layout not the
        report content</title><para>If you use the Bug Report Manager you
        probably noticed that it does not allow you to define the values to
        match for the search criteria. This is on purpose. Defining a report
        template and filling the bug search template with content (values) are
        2 distinct operations on CodeX. So once a bug report is defined (e.g
        &#39;Simple Report&#39;, &#39;QA report&#39;, &#39;Daily report&#39;
        ...) you can go to the bug browsing module and use it for all sorts of
        queries. Select the bug report you want, fill the search criteria with
        the values you are interested in, click on the browse button and then
        save the entire query with the CodeX bookmarking mechanism (see tip in
        <xref linkend="SelectionCriteria" />). And voila!</para></tip></para>

      <section id="BugReportBrowsing">
	<title>Browsing Bug Reports</title>

	<para>Clicking on the 'Bug Reports' item in the Bug
	Administration menu bar at the top of the page displays the
	list of available bug reports (see <xref
	linkend="FigureBugReportBrowsing" />) with the following
	information:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis>: a number that
	    uniquely identify the bug report. A click on the report ID
	    brings you to the bug report configuration screen (see <xref linkend="BugReportSetting" />).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Report Name</emphasis>: the
	    report short name as it will appear in the bug report
	    select box when you'll be using the bug browsing screen
	    (e.g. Simple Report, QA report, Monthly Report&hellip;).</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a longer description of the bug report.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis>:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Project</emphasis>:
		this report will be usable by all project
		members. Only project administrators can define
		project-wide reports.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis
		role="underline">Personal</emphasis>: this report will
		be usable by its creator only.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete?</emphasis>: click the
	    trash icon to delete the report. Project-wide reports can
	    only be deleted by project administrators.</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureBugReportBrowsing">
	  <title>List of bug reports from the CodeX project</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugreportbrowsing.png" width="14.3cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section id="BugReportSetting">
	<title>Bug Report Setting</title>

	<para>After you click on a report ID in the bug report list
	(see <xref linkend="BugReportBrowsing" />, the bug report
	setting screen appears (see <xref
	linkend="FigureBugReportSetting" />). This screen allows you
	to define what bug fields you'd like to see in your bug report
	and at what place, both as search criteria and in the list of
	bugs retrieved from the database (called bug search results
	table) .</para>

	<para>Information available on this screen are as follows:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		      spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: each report
	    must be given a name. This name must not be too long as it
	    will appear in a select box in the bug browsing module
	    when you are asked to choose what bug report you want to
	    use to query your bug database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis> (optional):
	    project administrators can define project-wide reports
	    that will be made available to all users. Non project
	    administrators can only define personal bug report.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a longer description of the report.</para>
	  </listitem
>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field selection</emphasis>:
	    the bug field table shows all the bug fields that are
	    currently in use in your project Bug Tracking System. For
	    each field you can set up the following parameters:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Use as a Search
		Criteria</emphasis>: If you check this box the field
		will appear as one of the selection criteria when you
		search the bug database.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Rank on
		Search</emphasis>: A number can be entered in this
		field. The rank number allows you to place the field
		with respect to the others. The fields with smaller
		values will appear first on the list of selection
		criteria displayed on the screen. These number doesn't
		have to be consecutive numbers.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Use as a Report
		Column</emphasis>: If you check this box the field
		will appear as one of the column in the bug search results 
		table.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Rank on
		Report</emphasis>: A number can be entered in this
		field. The rank number allows you to place the field
		with respect to the others. The fields with smaller
		values will appear first in the bug search results
		table (from left to right). These number doesn't have
		to be consecutive numbers.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Column
	    Width</emphasis>(optional): In case you want to impose a
	    specific width to the column in the report table you can
	    specify a column width in percentage of the total page
	    width. This is optional and our recommendation is to leave
	    it blank unless your Web browser doesn't make a good job
	    at formatting your table. If you want a column to be as
	    narrow as possible while preserving word boundaries enter
	    a very small percentage like 1 or 2 in the column width
	    field.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: it is
	perfectly OK to use a field as a search criteria and not as a
	column in the bug report and vice versa. For the fiels you
	don't want to use at all in the report leave all boxes and
	text fields blank.</para></note>

	<figure id="FigureBugReportSetting">
	  <title>Setting a  bug report</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugreportsetting.png" width="14.2cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	
      </section>

    </section>


    <section id="BugEmailNotificationSettings">
      <title>Email Notification Settings</title> <para>As explained
      earlier in <xref linkend="BugEmailNotification" /> the BTS comes
      with a predefined set of rules to keep people involved in bug
      management aware of the bugs life. The default rules can however
      be complemented or tuned in a number of ways:</para>

      <section id="BugGlobalEmailNotification">
	<title>Global Email Notification</title>

	<para>In addition to the default notification rules, the
	project administrators have the ability to specify a list of
	comma separated email addresses to which new bug submissions
	(and optionally all bug updates) will be systematically
	sent. Note that email notification will be sent to users
	regardless of their personal preferences (see <xref
	linkend="BugEventRoleBasedEmailNotification" />).</para>

	<para>This feature is typically used to send new bug
	submissions to a number of well identified persons in the team
	who are in charge of qualifying and dispatching the
	bugs.</para>

	<para><tip>
	  <title>Tip: Create a Distribution List to notify several people</title>
	  
	  <para>If you want to notify many people at once, we suggest
	  that you use the CodeX Mailing Lists service to create a
	  distribution lists (see <xref linkend="MailingLists"
	  />). Once the Mailing List is up and running type the e-mail
	  address in the Global Email Notification field.</para>

	  <para>Creating a Mailing List on CodeX has several
	  advantages: first individuals can (un)subscribe by
	  themselves and second all messages sent to a CodeX mailing
	  list are kept in an archive that can serve as an audit
	  trail for your bug tracking system.</para>

	  </tip>
        </para>

      </section>


      <section id="BugWatchers">
	<title>Bug Watchers</title>

	<para>The BTS offers to all project members the ability to be
	carbon-copied on all bug notifications sent to some other
	project members. If you use this feature you'll be able to
	watch at others' email notifications exactly like if you were the
	person you are watching. </para>

	<para>Here are a couple of examples where the bug watch
	feature can be extremely useful:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Backups</emphasis>: when a
	    team member is away from the office it is often convenient
	    to delegate her bug management activity to another person
	    in the team acting as a backup. Becoming the backup of
	    another team member is as easy as inserting her name in
	    the Bug Watchers field of the backup person when the team
	    member quits and remove it when the team member
	    returns.</para>

	    <para>As soon as you specify a person name in the bug
	    watchers field you'll start receiving all the bug
	    notification of this person and you can act accordingly on her
	    behalf.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">QA Contacts</emphasis>:
	    another possible use is for the QA team members to fill
	    the bug watcher field with the names of the software
	    engineers whom QA activity they are responsible for.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><para>Remark: The goal of the bug watch feature is not to spy on
	you. To make sure that you are only watched by authorized persons,
	CodeX always shows you the list of CodeX users who are
	currently watching your bug notifications.</para></note>

      </section>

      <section id="BugEventRoleBasedEmailNotification">
	<title>Event/Role Based Notification Settings</title>

	<para>This is the most sophisticated part of the customization
	process. It allows any user to specify what types of events
	she wants to be notified by email. Note that these settings
	are project specific so you can tune your email notification
	settings for each project you are involved with.</para>

	<para>The customization matrix (see <xref
	linkend="FigureBugNotificationMatrix" />) presents you with a
	series of check boxes. Each check box allows you to specify
	what kind of bug events you want to be aware of depending on
	the role you play in this bug.</para>

	<para>There are 4 roles defined with respect to a bug:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Submitter</emphasis>: the person
	  who initially reported the bug by filling the bug submission
	  form.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Assignee</emphasis>: the person
	  who is responsible for managing the bug.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">CC</emphasis>: the person
	  is mentioned in the list of CC names.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Commenter</emphasis>: the person
	  once posted a follow-up comment in the bug.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>For each of these roles you can instruct the BTS to send
	email notification to you only when some specific events
	occur. Nine different events (see the right most column on
	<xref linkend="FigureBugNotificationMatrix" />) are monitored
	by the BTS. The description of the events is self explanatory
	and only appeal one comment: the first 8 events in the list
	can only occur on bug updates. Only the last event relates to
	the submission of a new bug.</para>

	<para>Let's review the sample matrix shown on <xref
	linkend="FigureBugNotificationMatrix" /> and see, step by
	step, how this user has configured her notification
	settings:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>First let's look at the Commenter column. The
	  Commenter column says that this user has decided that if she
	  was involved in a bug as a Commenter (she just posted a
	  follow-up comment at some point in time) then she is only
	  interested in receiving email notification when the status
	  of the bug goes to 'Closed' or when any of the fields
	  Priority, Status and Severity is modified. All other events
	  will be ignored by the BTS and no notification will be sent
	  to this user.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Second, looking at the matrix by row, one can see
	  that the user said that when she makes a modification to a bug
	  herself (Event 'I am the author of the change') she doesn't
	  want to receive any email notification whatever is role 
	  in this bug is.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Finally, the user also said that when a new
	  bug is submitted to the project and is immediately assigned
	  to her (Assignee role) she wants to be notified. However if
	  she is the submitter of the new bug then she is not
	  interested in receiving the notification.</para> <para>Note
	  that CC and Commenter roles are meaningless for event 'A new
	  bug has been submitted' because CC names and Commenters can
	  only be added in bug updates.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureBugNotificationMatrix">
	  <title>Personal Notification Settings</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
			 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_bugnotificationmatrix.png" width="12.5cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="BugOtherConfigurationSettings">
      <title>Other Configuration Settings</title>

      <para>This module allows you to define the following configuration
        parameters for the CodeX Bug Tracking System:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>An introductory message that displays at the top of
            the Bug submission form. This is a convenient way to give
            directions and recommendations to the bug submitter. The text must
            use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great flexibility to
            shape the content of this preamble (you can use bold, italic,
            embedded URL, ...)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Other items may be added in the future.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

