<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="CodeXSiteOverview">
    <title>CodeX Site Overview</title>

    <para>CodeX is a &SYS_ORG_NAME; <emphasis role="underline">internal</emphasis> Web
    Site available at <ulink url="&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/.</ulink>
    To browse the CodeX site use your favorite Web Browser
    <footnote><para>CodeX uses standard HTML and only a little bit of
    Javascript. It is known to work well with Netscape 4.x, Netscape 6.x and
    Mozilla as well as IE 4 or 5. Other Web Browsers like Opera or Konqueror
    work as well. CodeX uses very little graphic material and is therefore
    browsable by specific text only browser like those used by visually
    impaired people.</para></footnote>. CodeX is a rich site and the CodeX
    User Guide is going to guide you through all the services that the CodeX
    site has to offer. In order to help you find your way in the CodeX
    services gallery, <xref linkend="FigureCodeXWebPageFlowChart" /> gives a
    broad overview of the services available as well as a flow chart showing
    how to access a given service.</para>

    <section id="CodeXHomePage">
      <title>CodeX Home Page</title>

      <para>The Home Page is divided in 4 parts (see <xref
      linkend="FigureTheCodeXHomePage" />):</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The CodeX Main Menu</emphasis>: on the
          left hand side of the screen</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX Short Introduction</emphasis>: the
          upper central part gives you a brief but pivotal introduction to the
          CodeX initiative and a series of links to must read documents</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX Latest News</emphasis>: The lower
          central part shows the last 10 pieces of news related to CodeX
          hosted projects or to the CodeX site.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The CodeX Dashboard</emphasis>: The
          right hand side of the home page shows a series of statistics about
          the overall activity of the CodeX Site</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section id="TheCodeXMainMenu">
      <title>The CodeX Main Menu</title>

      <para>The CodeX main menu is a permanent piece of information that
      you&#39;ll always see on your screen wherever you are in the CodeX site.
      Its content can vary according to where you and who you are. In other
      words it is context sensitive. Let&#39;s take 2 examples:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>If you are visiting the CodeX site as an anonymous user the
          upper part of the menu invites you to login or to create a new
          account whereas if you are logged in you&#39;ll be given access to
          other functions like Logout, Account Maintenance, Personal Page,
          etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Similarly if you decide to visit a given project hosted on
          CodeX, the menu will offer an additional section giving access to
          the Project Summary page (the public face of a project) or to the
          Project Administration page (A reserved view for project members
          only)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In the rest of this section we only review those items that are
      permanent and context independent. Other menu items are described later
      in the document in the related service description.</para>

      <figure id="FigureCodeXWebPageFlowChart">
        <title>CodeX Web Page Flow Chart</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../slides/en_US/Sitemap.png" width="15.5cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>


      <section id="SoftwareMap">
        <title>Software Map</title>

        <para>The Software Map is a pivotal service in CodeX that you can
        (should) use to determine if there are some pieces of software that
        you can re-use for your own work. The Software Map is one of the 2
        ways by which you can search for existing software projects. The other
        one relies on the Search Facility (See <xref
        linkend="ProjectHelpWanted" />).</para>

        <figure id="FigureSoftwareMapSampleBrowsing">
          <title>Software Map sample browsing</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_softwaremap.png" width="13.2cm"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>When a project is created it is classified by the project
        creator according to 7 criteria:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Development Status</emphasis>: How
            mature your project is (alpha, beta, stable,...)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Environment</emphasis>: in which
            environment your software is being used (Web, Win32, X Window,
            text mode,...)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Audience</emphasis>: The target
            audience of your software (developers, end-users, system
            administrators,...)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">License</emphasis>: License of
            your software. In most cases this is going to be the
            &SYS_ORG_NAME; Code exchange Policy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Operating System</emphasis>: Operating
            system(s) your software runs on</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Programming Languages</emphasis>: the
            programming languages you used to develop your software</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Topic</emphasis>: The field of use of
            your project. This criteria describes the area in which your
            software operates (Printing, Scanning, Information Technology,...)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Each criterion can have up to 3 values for a given project (e.g.
        you can select up to 3 programming languages for a given project).
        Values of the various criteria are taken from a list of predefined
        values and most of them are not expected to change in a foreseeable
        future except for the &#34;Topic&#34; criterion. The &#34;Topic&#34;
        criterion reflects the domain covered by your project (Printing,
        Scanning, Information Technology, etc.) and it follows a hierarchy of
        domains and sub-domains that the CodeX Team constantly refines as more
        projects are coming.</para>

        <para>Using the Software Map you can browse CodeX hosted projects
        according to any of these criteria. As you explore the map, projects
        matching the criteria are listed on the screen with their name,
        description, creation date, activity percentile, and other
        information. The values of the 7 criteria for a given project are
        listed right after the project name and description. Notice that next
        to each criteria value is a [Filter] hyperlink. Clicking on any of
        these filters will result in restricting the project list to those
        that match the filter.</para>

        <para>A Software Map browsing sample is shown on <xref
        linkend="FigureSoftwareMapSampleBrowsing" />. In this example, the
        user has first opened the Programming Languages Criteria and then
        selected C as a language of choice. This probably led to a large
        number of projects and so she then decided to narrow the set of
        projects by specifying 2 additional filters: the first one specifies
        that the Development Status must be Production-Stable and the second
        one requires that the projects runs on the SunOS/Solaris operating
        system.</para>

        <para>As a result of this multi-criteria screening, the user ends up
        with a list of 9 projects (only the first one is shown on <xref
        linkend="FigureSoftwareMapSampleBrowsing" /> to save space). Filters
        have another interesting property: they are sticky. It means that if
        you decide to browse the projects from another angle (say by opening
        the Topic folder), the selected filters will constantly apply. In
        order to release the search constraint you must explicitly remove the
        filter by clicking on the [Remove this Filter] link in the upper part
        of the screen.</para>

        <para><tip><title>TIP</title><para>If you repeatedly execute the same
        browsing operation on the Software Map you can save it in your
        Personal Page. To do this, first execute your software map request as
        explained above and when you are happy with the selection criteria,
        click on the Bookmark This Page item in the CodeX Main Menu. This will
        make a new link appear in your Personal Page that you can then edit to
        give it an appropriate description.</para></tip></para>
      </section>

      <section id="TheCodeSnippetLibrary">
        <title>The Code Snippet Library</title>

        <para>A project hosted on CodeX has the ability to use a large
        spectrum of services. However not all pieces of software worth sharing
        require such a rich environment. Sharing a very short piece of source
        code like a macro, a function or a shell script has to be quick and
        easy. This is precisely the role of the Code Snippet Library.</para>

        <para>The Code Snippet Library can be accessed via the CodeX Main Menu
        on the left hand side of the screen under the Software section (see
        <xref linkend="FigureTheCodeXHomePage" />)</para>

        <section id="CodeSnippetBrowsing">
          <title>Code Snippet Browsing</title>

          <para>The welcome page of the Code Snippet Library classifies the
          code snippets by category and by programming languages. The figures
          next to each label indicate the number of code snippets available in
          each category.</para>

          <para></para>
          <para>You can browse code snippets in 2 different ways:</para>

          <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                        spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Navigate through the categories or programming languages
              classification</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use the Search box in the CodeX Main menu on the left hand
              side of the screen. Keywords typed are search in the code
              snippet title and in the code snippet description.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Matching snippets are shown in a list along with their code
          snippet ID number, title and detailed description as well as the
          author&#39;s name. Please note that by clicking on the author&#39;s
          name you can immediately send a question or a suggestion to the
          author of the code snippet.</para>

          <figure id="FigureListOfCodeSnippetsInTheHTMLManipulationCategory">
            <title>List of Code Snippets in the &#39;HTML Manipulation&#39;
            category</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_codesnippetsearch.png" width="14.2cm"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section id="CodeSnippetSubmission">
          <title>Code Snippet Submission</title>

          <para>To submit a new code snippet click on the &#34;Submit a new
          Code Snippet&#34; link in the Code Snippet Menu at the top of the
          screen. Provide the code snippet title and description. You can use
          Web locations (URLs) in these two fields. CodeX will automatically
          turn them into hyperlinks in the final version. Also provide the
          code snippet type, programming language and category as requested.
          Should a category or a programming language be missing when you
          submit a new code snippet please contact the CodeX team by clicking
          on the link right below the pull-down menus.</para>

          <para>It is highly recommended that you provide a version number as
          well. This version number is a free text field and can have any kind
          of value. Using a version number is useful if you want to post a
          newer version in the future. We also recommend that you indicate the
          same version number in the source code associated with the snippet
          so that CodeX users can determine whether they already have the
          latest version the next time they visit the Code Snippet Library.</para>

          <para>The code snippet itself can be submitted either by simply
          copy-pasting the source code in the text area or by uploading a
          file. We do recommend that you copy-paste the source code to make it
          directly visible when users browse the Code Snippet library.</para>

          <para>However there are cases where it is ok to upload non human
          readable files. Typical examples are when your code snippet is a
          made of several files that you may want to deliver in the form of an
          archive (zip or compressed tar). Another example is when the code
          snippet is not human readable: simulation software (e.g. LabView)
          use proprietary and non human readable format for their source
          files. In any case <emphasis role="underline">do not</emphasis>
          post pure binary code like compiled C, C++,Java,... The Code Snippet
          Library, like CodeX, is about sharing and reusing software code not
          binary.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="UpdatingACodeSnippet">
          <title>Updating a Code Snippet</title>

          <para>To update a code snippet with a newer version of the source
          code, select the original code snippet either by browsing the code
          snippet category or by using the search mechanism. Click on the Code
          Snippet in the result list and proceed to the &#34;Submit a new
          version&#34; link at the end of the screen. Provide a change
          description, a new version number and copy-paste the source code
          associated with the new version.</para>

          <note><para>Please note that even though this is still the
          same code snippet, CodeX assigns a new code snippet ID number to
          each version. So referencing a new version in a Code Snippet Package
          (see section Grouping Code Snippets below) will require that you
          delete the old version and add the new one.</para></note>
        </section>

        <section id="DeletingACodeSnippet">
          <title>Deleting a Code Snippet</title>

          <para>Select the code snippet as indicated above. Then click on the
          appropriate code snippet in the result list. From here you can click
          on the waste basket icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/trash.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>)
          next to the code snippet version to delete one or several versions
          of the code snippet.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="GroupingCodeSnippets">
          <title>Grouping Code Snippets</title>

          <para>If you have submitted several code snippets that relate to the
          same topic, are written in the same language and belong to the same
          code snippet category it might be a good idea to group them together
          under a common umbrella. This is what Code Snippet Packages are for.</para>

          <para>To create a code snippet package click on the &#34;Create a
          Package&#34; item in the Code Snippet Menu at the top of the screen.
          Provide a title, a description, type, category and version as
          requested. After you submit the form, a new window will pop up
          asking you for the ID numbers of the Code Snippets that must be
          added to the package. So before you create a package make sure you
          have the code snippet ID numbers available.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="UpdatingACodeSnippetPackage">
          <title>Updating a Code Snippet Package</title>

          <para>Like code snippets, packages can be updated. To update a
          package just proceed as for an ordinary code snippet. First search
          for it, select it and finally click in the Edit icon. From here you
          can add/delete code snippet to/from the package. If you want to
          update the package with a new version of a code snippet, first
          delete the old version and add the new one which has its own
          specific code snippet ID (see &#34;Updating a Code Snippet&#34;
          above).</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="NewReleases">
        <title>New Releases</title>

        <para>Click on this menu item to see a list of the most recent
        software releases (also known as new versions) that have been posted
        on the CodeX site by the various projects. If you want to keep aware
        of new incoming releases visit this page on a regular basis. CodeX
        also allows you to monitor the new software releases posted by a given
        project. To do so go to the Project Summary page of this project by
        clicking on the project title and then select the monitor icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
        format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/mail16d.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>)
        next to the release name. Once you monitor a project release, e-mail
        notification will be sent to you whenever the project team
        posts a new software release.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="SiteDocumentation">
        <title>Site Documentation</title>

        <para>The Site Documentation pointer is the entry point to the
        CodeX documentation. The CodeX documentation is entirely
        managed via the Document Manager (see <xref
        linkend="DocumentManager" />) service of the CodeX project,
        which is of course hosted on CodeX. The documents on this page
        cover all the CodeX site. It includes presentation material,
        the user guide and other important documents. Read them
        carefully.</para>

        <important>
          <title>** Important Note **</title>

          <para role="">The <emphasis role="bold">&SYS_ORG_NAME; Code exchange Policy</emphasis>

          [XCEP] is available in the Must Read Documents section. This
          2-page Corporate Policy governs the act of Software Sharing
          at &SYS_ORG_NAME;. All CodeX users must read, understand and
          apply this policy before re-using software or hosting any of
          their projects on the CodeX site. CodeX gives you direct
          access to the Intellectual Property of your company and you
          must therefore make sure that you and your group strictly
          conforms to the Code eXchange Policy for the benefit of the entire
          company. Failing to comply with the terms of the Code
          eXchange Policy can lead to severe disciplinary actions
          including prosecution and contract termination.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>CodeX Developers Channels</title>

        <para>One of the top priority objectives of the CodeX site is
        to become a discussion forum for the software developers
        regardless of the organization they belong to and the country
        they work in.</para>

        <para>To this end the CodeX Team has created a series of mailing lists
        (called Developers Channels) where anybody, including non-CodeX users,
        can subscribe. Each channel is dedicated to a given software related
        topic. The creation of a new channel is under the responsibility of
        the CodeX Team. If you want to create a new developers channel please
        contact the CodeX Team at <email>codex-contact@&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;</email>.</para>

        <para>The Developers Channels managed on CodeX have a certain number
        of advantages over conventional distribution lists:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Subscription and Un-subscription are entirely user driven
            and it can be done through the CodeX Web interface without any
            assistance.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All messages posted to the channel are archived forever and
            can be browsed at any time. (In the future they will probably be
            searchable as well)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Subscribers can decide to receive digests from the mailing
            list rather than individual messages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="CodeXDiscussionForums">
        <title>CodeX Discussion Forums</title>

        <para>Discussion Forums are an alternate way to keep in touch with the
        CodeX community. The CodeX Discussion Forums were created primarily as
        a communication vehicle between the CodeX users and the CodeX Team.
        These are general purpose Forums where you can ask for Help with
        CodeX, suggest new features, new categories for the software map, etc.</para>

        <para>These Forums are entirely Web based which means that you have to
        use the CodeX Web interface to post and read user messages. However
        Forums also offer the ability to be monitored, which means that all
        traffic will be sent to you via e-mail.</para>

        <tip>
          <title>Tip: Don&#39;t let your software licenses take the dust</title>

          <para>One of the Forums available on CodeX is called Software
          Bazaar. This Forum was put in place to buy or sell unused 3rd party
          software from other project teams. It is often the case that software
          packages acquired by a project team are no longer needed after some
          time. We wanted to give other people  a chance to get the
          unused license rather than buying yet another one. Similarly this
          Forum is the place to announce an Enterprise-Wide license obtained
          by your group and that other people could benefit from.</para>
        </tip>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section id="ProjectHelpWanted">
        <title>Project Help Wanted</title>

        <para>As you will see later in this document, each CodeX project has
        the ability to post jobs. This minimal job posting system is
        particularly well suited to publish call for expertise. By clicking on
        this item you&#39;ll see all job posting requests awaiting help from
        the community. Visit this section on a regular basis if you want
        to help others in the corporation solve their technical problems.</para>

        <para>For more details on how to post jobs see <xref
        linkend="Post-EditJobs" />.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="ContactUs">
        <title>Contact Us</title>

        <para>In addition to the Discussion Forums, you can always use the
        &#34;Contact Us&#34; link at the bottom of the CodeX Main Menu to get
        in touch with the CodeX Team. Our team works in 3 distinct time zones
        so it is very likely that whatever time of the day it is, you&#39;ll
        have a quick reply to your message.</para>

        <para>Do not hesitate to bug the &#34;Contact Us&#34; link. We are
        here to help.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="TheSearchFacility">
        <title>The Search Facility</title>

        <para>This is the last item in the CodeX Main Menu but not the least.
        CodeX allows you to search almost any piece of CodeX information
        through a keyword search mechanism. When you are on the CodeX Home
        Page you can search for keywords in the following resources:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Software Projects</emphasis>: a match
            is attempted with project names as well as their short and long
            description. This search mechanism is very complementary with the
            Software Map.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Code Snippet Library</emphasis>: Code
            snippets are small pieces of code that you can post on CodeX (see
            <xref linkend="TheCodeSnippetLibrary" />) along with a
            description. You can search this description by keywords are see
            if there are code snippets that you can re-use to ease your job.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para role=""><emphasis role="bold">People</emphasis>: keywords
            will be searched in the CodeX user database and matched against
            the user&#39;s login name, real name and e-mail address.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Bugs</emphasis>: If you enter the bug
            tracking system if any CodeX project, the Bugs item will show up
            in the search box, allowing you to actually search the bug
            database of this project.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="TheCodeXDashboard">
      <title>The CodeX Dashboard</title>

      <para>The CodeX Dashboard resides on the right hand side of the CodeX
      Home Page. It is a sort of a fish-eye view of the global CodeX activity.
      Several indicators are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX Statistics</emphasis>: give the
          total number of hosted projects (excluding those that have a private
          status), the total number of registered users, the total number of
          software packages downloaded and the total number of Web pages
          browsed by CodeX users since the site opening.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Top Project Downloads</emphasis>: shows
          which software projects were downloaded the day before (based on
          midnight EST time) and how many times.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Newest Projects</emphasis>: the last 10
          registered projects. Looking at this part of the dashboard on a
          regular basis will help you to keep informed on the new projects
          hosted on CodeX.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Most Active This Week</emphasis>: the 20
          most active projects over the past 7 days on a scale from 0 to 100%.
          The magic formula that we use behind the scene to compute this
          ranking is a weighted sum of the activity observed in the various
          projects services. It takes many things into account: the number of
          commits/updates on the CVS repository, the number of bugs and tasks
          submitted or modified, the number of file releases, etc. Looking at
          this list is an excellent way to see which projects are actively
          working on CodeX.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As a conclusion, we strongly advise you to visit the CodeX Home
      Page on a regular basis for it gives you an excellent idea of what is
      going in terms of software development across &SYS_ORG_NAME;.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="underline">Bottom line</emphasis>: Make CodeX your
      browser home page :-)</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

