<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="CommunicationServices">
    <title>Communication Services</title>

    <para>One of the CodeX objectives is to provide Xerox developers with
    efficient software development and project management tools. In addition,
    the CodeX Team also wants the CodeX site to become the favorite
    communication channel of all Xerox developers. We feel it is pivotal for
    the project teams and their community of users to communicate.</para>

    <para>To this end, CodeX offers a series of communication services that
    can be customized by the project team. These include mailing lists, the
    News service and the Web Forums.</para>

    <section id="MailingLists">
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>

      <section id="MailingListsCreation">
        <title>Creation</title>
        
      <para>Each project can create as many mailing lists (ML) as needed. To
      create a mailing list click on the &#34;Lists&#34; item in the Project
      Main menu on the Project Summary page. After the new page loads, then
      click on the &#34;Admin&#34; link.</para>

      <para>Adding a ML is just a matter of giving it a name, a one-line
      description, and to specify whether it is a public or a private list. A
      private list won&#39;t show up on the welcome screen of the Mailing List
      service and is therefore only known to the project team. This will
      prevent other people from subscribing or posting messages to it.</para>

      <para>In order to minimize naming conflicts between the many MLs created
      by the various CodeX projects, the mailing list follows the following
      naming pattern:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
projectname-listname@lists.codex.xerox.com
</programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><literal><emphasis>projectname</emphasis></literal>
          projectname is you project short name as defined during project
          registration</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal><emphasis>listname</emphasis></literal> is the name
          you have chosen for your mailing list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><note>Creating a mailing list implies that you are the
      mailing list administrator, at least at the beginning. As the ML
      administrator, you&#39;ll receive some additional instructions via
      e-mail shortly after the creation of the ML. This is an important mail
      message that contains the URLs for the ML administration and information
      pages and the default ML administration password generated by CodeX.
      Keep it in a safe place and remember it!</note></para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Create at least one Mailing List</title><para>A
      CodeX hosted project should at least create one mailing list where all
      users can post questions and comments. This list is typically called
      <literal>projectname-interest@lists.codex.xerox.com</literal>. We
      strongly encourage you to follow this well established practice.</para></tip></para>
      </section>

      <section id="MailingListsAdministration">
        <title>Administration</title>

        <para>The ML administration is also entirely Web based. You can access
        the ML administration page by using the URL that you received when you
        first created the ML. In case you have misplaced the original message
        you can access the ML administration page at the following URL:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
http://lists.codex.xerox.com/mailman/admin/listname
</programlisting>

        <para>The Administration page allows you to tune many ML parameters,
        manage list members, and administrators, privacy, new member welcome
        messages, etc. GNU/Mailman, the ML manager used by CodeX, is extremely
        capable software and we invite you to visit the administration page at
        least once to get an idea of the all the features.</para>

        <para><note>Note that project administrators are not
        automatically made administrators of project mailing lists, and the
        administrative password for the mailing list is distinct from any of
        the other CodeX user passwords.</note></para>
      </section>

      <section id="UnSubscriptionArchiveandPreferences">
        <title>(Un)Subscription, Archive and Preferences</title>

        <para>Unless its owner marks a ML as private, any CodeX user can
        subscribe to a project Mailing List (ML). To subscribe to a mailing
        list click on the &#34;Lists&#34; item in the Project Main menu on the
        Project Summary page. From there click on the
        &#34;Subscribe/Unsubscribe/Preferences&#34; link of the appropriate
        ML. Then follow the instructions presented.</para>

        <para>The CodeX ML system (GNU/Mailman) also archives all the messages
        posted on a mailing list. Following the &#34;Archive&#34; link on the
        same page as before will bring you to archived messages grouped by
        month. Note that the current archiving software is not MIME-aware and
        does not support the archiving of attachments.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="NewsService">
      <title>News Service</title>

      <para>The News service complements your mailing lists. This service
      allows you to publish pieces of news related to your project. Any event
      in the life of your project is a good candidate for a news release: new
      people in the team, new software release, information on related
      technologies and why not your wedding announcement or the birth of your
      sixth child ? . Do not keep your project concealed behind a veil. Make
      your project life public for the benefit of all Xerox employees and for
      your faithful community of users.</para>

      <para>News publishing is very easy. To use it simply click on the News
      item in the Project Main menu and then on the &#34;Submit&#34; link in
      the News Service menu at the top of the page. From there type the title
      of the news and its text body. You can type URLs in the body. CodeX will
      detect them and transform them into a hyperlink in the published
      version.</para>

      <para>All posted news will appear on your Project Summary page and will
      therefore be visible to all Xerox people visiting your project on CodeX.
      Any CodeX visitor can attach a follow-up comment to the news making each
      piece of news a potential forum of discussion<footnote><para>Behind the
      scene, each piece of news is actually managed exactly like a CodeX Web
      Forum.</para></footnote>. In addition the CodeX Team sees all the news
      published by all CodeX projects and can decide that a project news is
      worth publishing on the CodeX front page. A big splash indeed!!</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WebForums">
      <title>Web Forums</title>

      <para>This is the third form of communication offered by CodeX. Web
      Forums are more or less equivalent to mailing list except that the
      message-posting takes place via a Web interface. Therefore you need to
      have a connection to the site to participate in the discussion because
      you can&#39;t prepare your message off-line, as you can with an ML.</para>

      <para>To access the Web Forums of a CodeX project, click on the
      &#34;Forum&#34; item in the Project Main menu on the Project Summary
      Page. When a CodeX project is created, it is given three Web forums:
      Open Discussions, Help and Developers. These Forums and all others are
      open to all CodeX users both for reading and posting. A user can also
      decide to monitor a Web Forum. Monitoring a Forum will cause CodeX to
      automatically forward all the posted messages via e- mail thus avoiding
      repeated visits to the Forum Web page.</para>

      <para>Project administrators can create other Forums on demand by using
      the Forum Administration module that can be accessed via the
      &#34;Admin&#34; link in the News Service menu. Administrators can follow
      the links on this page to Add Forum, Delete Message, and Update Forum
      Info/Status. The Update Forum Info/Status page lets administrators make
      forums public or private, edit the name and description of the forum, or
      even delete the forum.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->