<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// 
//
//	Originally written by Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="CreatingANewProject">
    <title>Creating a New Project</title>

    <para>So - you are a freshly registered CodeX user and you want to make
    your developer or project leader life easier. In other words you want to:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                  spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Avoid the pain and cost of creating your own project
        infrastructure (with servers and backup)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Avoid paying a premium price for commercial version control,
        defect tracking and task management tools</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Quickly setup a project environment that you can share
        with your colleagues, your partners, your contractors or your
        customers where ever they are while keeping your information
        safe and under control.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make your organization globally more productive and efficient
        by possibly letting others re-use your software and build on it.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If any of these points is appealing to you then you should
    definitely host your software project on CodeX. Let&#39;s see how you can
    do that.</para>

    <section id="ProjectRegistration">
      <title>Project Registration</title>

      <para>Before you create a new project you must be a registered user (see
      <xref linkend="ClassesOfCitizens" />). You then login and select the
      item &#34;Register New Project&#34; in the upper part of the CodeX Main
      Menu.</para>

      <para>The project registration is an easy process:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Registration</emphasis></para>

          <para>Some information about CodeX Services. Just read it.</para>
          <para>Do not forget to read and agree the Terms of Services Agreement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Name</emphasis></para>

          <para>Give the project short name and the project full name.
          Carefully read the restrictions that apply to both names
          before you type anything. The full name can be changed at
          any time in the life of the project. The short name
          cannot<footnote><para>Actually it can but you have to ask
          the CodeX Team to do it for you.</para></footnote>. So think
          about it twice before you make a decision!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Template</emphasis></para>
        
          <para>You already registered a CodeX project and would now like to reuse
          the same configuration (services, trackers, documents, references, ...) ? 
          Make your old project a template project (see <xref linkend="ProjectType" />) 
          and you will find it here in the list of available 
          project templates. Check your old project as template and your new registered
          project will be staffed as you are used to. If you don't want to reuse
          a specific template just keep the Default CodeX Template checked and go on.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Description</emphasis></para>

          <para>This is where the rubber hits the road! Tell us about your
          project. Give an accurate description. This is really important if
          you want to maximize the chance of re-use by others. Also
          list any information related to Intellectual Property like
          Invention Proposal or Patents related to the software whether
          pending or already filed. Give the list of software needed (whether
          internal or 3rd party) to make your own software run properly. And the
          last field is entirely for you. Write down all the things that you
          consider as crucial for your project or for the community of users.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Services</emphasis></para>
        
          <para>You can choose which services will be activated for your project. 
          Please note that you will be able to change those preferences after 
          project creation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Categorization</emphasis></para>

          <para>Please select up to three classifications for this project in 
          each of the Trove root categories. This will help potential developers 
          and users to find your project and engage. If the project does not 
          require any or all of these classification, simply select 
          "None Selected". If you used a project template that had already been
	  classified you will find its categories already selected here.
          You can change the trove categories for this project at any time.
          You can categorize your project according to the seven criteria
          listed in <xref linkend="SoftwareMap" />.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Software Policy</emphasis></para>

          <para>Most of the time the only valid choice here is the
          default one: &#34;&SYS_ORG_NAME; Code eXchange
          Policy&#34;. As explained earlier in this document the CodeX
          Team assisted by &SYS_ORG_NAME; lawyers have carefully
          crafted the CodeX Policy and it is very unlikely that you
          need to create your own. If you do you&#39;ll have to talk
          to us and to the &SYS_ORG_NAME; Legal Department to validate
          it. A number of truly Open Source licenses are also
          mentioned in the list. Finally you can also choose you own
          licensing conditions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Final Confirmation</emphasis></para>

          <para>Last chance to review the submitted information before you
          send it to the CodeX Team for validation. Don&#39;t worry: the
          project members can later update all pieces of information shown on
          this page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>After you validate the project registration, the CodeX Team
      reviews the information you submitted and decides to approve it or not.
      This process can take up to 24 hours but in most cases it&#39;s less
      than a couple of hours. So far all projects have been accepted so there
      is little to fear ... Shortly after the CodeX Team approval you&#39;ll
      receive an e-mail summarizing the characteristics of your project
      including a pointer to your new &#34;Project Summary&#34; page. Bookmark
      it in a safe place!</para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section id="Post-RegistrationConfiguration">
      <title>Post-Registration Configuration</title>

      <para>The first thing to do after you receive the confirmation
      for your project registration is to visit the &#34;Project
      Summary&#34; page (URL included in the e-mail) and finish the
      configuration of your project.  The 2 following actions are the
      most frequent ones that have to be taken after a project is
      registered:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Categorize your project in the Software
          Map</emphasis></para>

          <para>If you haven't done it during the project registration
          process, you should do it now!
          Your project categorization appears on your
          &#34;Project Summary&#34; page. To categorize your project
          select the &#34;categorize it now&#34; link and fill out the
          category form fields.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Build the project team</emphasis></para>

          <para>Once a project is created, the creator is assigned the
          role of project administrator on this project. It is her
          responsibility to define who are the project members and
          what their permissions are. This can be done by accessing
          the &#34;Project Admin&#34; page, typing the names of all
          the registered users  promote as team members and then
          define their permissions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip: Cannot find an appropriate Topic? Contact us</title>

        <para>Rather than putting in place a heavy hierarchy of project topics
        and sub-topics, the CodeX Team has decided to start small and create
        only a handful of top-level topics in the hierarchy. As time goes and
        as more and more projects register on CodeX we&#39;ll refine the
        hierarchy. If you cannot find the appropriate topic for your project,
        please contact us through the &#34;Contact Us&#34; link in the CodeX
        Main Menu or submit a request in the appropriate Discussion Forum.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>
  </chapter>
