<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
<chapter id="DocumentManager">
  <title>Document Manager</title>

  <para>Documentation is probably the second most important deliverable in a
    software project after the software work products themselves. CodeX
    provides a specific service to manage your project documents.</para>

  <para>Although the CodeX Document Manager cannot be compared
    with dedicated document management systems, it
    is however very handy to publish documents that are critical to
    your community of users. Examples are: Installation, Administration
    or User Guide, API documentation, Frequently Asked Questions,
    etc...</para>

  <para>The Document Manager features are as follows:</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>The CodeX Document Manager can handle any type of
      document. However we strongly encourage editors to publish their
      documents in HTML and/or PDF to make it readable quickly and
      easily.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents are stored in groups (or folders). The folders are
        only one level deep which means you can&#39;t have subfolders in a
        folder.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents can be edited on line (if in text or HTML format).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Access control rules can be defined for each document or document group.</para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <section id="DocumentAccess">
    <title>Access to Documents</title>

    <section id="DocumentBrowsing">
      <title>Document Browsing</title>

    <para>To access the Document Manager select the &#34;Docs&#34; item from
      the Project Menu at the top of the screen of the Project Summary page.
      The welcome page of the Document Manager shows the list of all the
      documents published by the project by group.</para>

    <para>To read a document simply click on the title.</para>

    <figure id="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome">
      <title>A sample Document Manager welcome page</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="DocumentCrossReference">
      <title>Cross-Referencing documents</title>

      <para>Like artifacts, CVS/Subversion commits, and other CodeX objects,
      documents may be referenced in artifact comments or commit messages.
      Simply type the "doc #NNN" pattern to automatically create
      a link to the document with ID number NNN. Document IDs are
      visible in the 'Docs' main page by hovering over a document title
      with the mouse pointer. Please refer to <xref linkend="ReferenceOverview" /> 
      for more details on CodeX references.</para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="DocumentSubmission">
    <title>Document Submission</title>

    <para>Only project members with the 'Technician' role in the 'User Permissions'
      matrix (see <xref linkend="UserPermissions" />) can submit documentation.
      To submit a new document, click on the
      &#34;Submit New Documentation&#34; link in the Document Manager menu 
      (<xref linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />). Then provide the
      document title, the document description and the body of the text.</para>

    <para>The document itself can either be copy-pasted directly in the
      document text area or uploaded with the help of the &#34;Browse&#34;
      button and the &#34;Upload&#34; checkbox. Then select a document group
      from the pull-down menu and click on the &#34;Submit&#34;
      button.</para>

    <para>A document has to be attached to a group in any case. This is why
      CodeX provides a default group called 'Documents' to each project. 
      This default group may be renamed.</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: Copy-pasted vs. uploaded documents</title>
    <para>A copy-pasted document will be embedded in a CodeX page, so its 
      appearance will be modified, and some tags like HTML, TITLE, or HEAD
      will be ignored. An uploaded document, on the opposite, will be displayed
      "as-is" in the browser window. Another difference is that a copy-pasted
      document can be edited online, whereas an uploaded document can only be 
      updated by uploading a new version.</para>
    </tip></para>

    <para>The document title and summary can contain HTML tags. So you can
      use all sorts of typographic effects as well as pointers to other
      locations or documents, etc.</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: Referencing external documents</title>
    <para>It is sometimes convenient to create placeholder documents
    that actually point to an external location like file in another
    document management system or web site. To do this, simply
    surround the document title with an HREF tag (hyperlink) pointing
    to the target location.</para>
    </tip></para>

  </section>

  <section id="DocumentAdministration">
    <title>Document Administration</title>

    <para>The Document Manager provides a number of administration functions
      like changing the document access permissions, display position or group,
      creating new document groups, etc.</para>

    <figure id="FigureTheDocumentManagerAdministrationScreen">
      <title>The Document Manager Administration screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentadmin.png" width="15.3cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="DocumentPublication">
      <title>Document Publication</title>

      <para>Once a new document has been submitted by a project
      member with 'Technician' rights on the Document Manager, it
      is immediately visible on the Document Manager welcome page.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="DocumentUpdate">
      <title>Document Update</title>

      <para>Only members with the 'Administration' right on the
      Document Manager can modify an existing document.</para>

      <para>You can update a document in several ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		    spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>The title, description and document body can be modified. In
            this case you update the document content.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can change the group (or folder) a document belongs to.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can change the document display rank in the document group.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To update a document click on the &#34;Admin&#34; link in the
        Document Manager menu (<xref linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />).
        What you see next is the list of all documents of the project sorted
        by group and by rank. Then choose the
        document you want to update from the list. Click on the document title
        to make the document update screen appear. From here you can modify
        any part of the document, its rank, and the group it belongs to.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="DocumentGroupManagement">
      <title>Document Group Management</title>

      <para>In the CodeX Terminology, a CodeX Document group is
      equivalent to a folder.</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheDocumentGroupsAdministrationScreen">
	<title>The Document Groups Administration screen</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentadmingroups.png" width="13cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To create, delete or change the name of document groups, click
        on the &#34;Admin&#34; link in the Document Manager menu (<xref
        linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />) and then the
        &#34;Edit Document Groups&#34; item in the next menu.</para>

      <para>To add a new group, use the &#34;Group Name&#34; and &#34;Rank&#34; text fields
        at the top of the screen and click on the &#34;Create&#34; button. You
        can also update an existing group by clicking on its name in the group list.</para>

      <para>Document groups have a display rank property that defines
      how document groups are ordered. Document groups with smaller ranks 
      are displayed first.</para>

      <para>Access permissions can be defined by clicking on the &#34;[Define Permissions]&#34; link.</para>
      <para>Document groups can be deleted by clicking on the trash icon in the group list. 
      Only empty document groups may be deleted: move or delete documents that belong to a group before trying to delete it.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="DocAccessPermissions">
      <title>Setting Access Permissions</title>
      
      <para>Setting document access permissions is very similar to
      setting file access permissions (<xref
      linkend="FileAccessPermissions" />): you need to create user
      groups (see <xref linkend="UserGroups" />), and assign those
      user groups to documents or document groups.</para>

      <para>By default, document and document groups have no specific
      access permissions: access to all documents is granted to
      anybody, including anonymous user.  However, in some cases, you
      might want to restrict acces to a particular document, e.g. when
      it contains confidential data.</para>

      <para>Access permissions can be defined at two different levels:
      document groups and documents:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Document Group Permissions</emphasis></para>

          <para>By clicking on '[Define Permissions] on the "Edit
          Document Groups" screen (see <xref
          linkend="FigureTheDocumentGroupsAdministrationScreen" />), a
          project member with the 'Admin' right on the document manager (see
          <xref linkend="UserPermissions" />) can attach access
          permissions to any existing document group.</para>

          <para>The document group permissions edition page lists all
          the project user groups. Simply select the user groups that
          will be allowed to display documents from the document group
          and press 'Submit'. You may select several groups at the
          same time if needed. If you press 'Reset To Defaults', the
          access permissions to this document group will be reset, so
          any user will be able to download any of the documents
          located in the group.</para>

          <para>Permissions attached to a document group apply to all
          documents that belong to this group.  But you may also set
          different permissions to specific documents (see
          below).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Document permissions</emphasis></para>

          <para>If you need finer grained access control to your
          documents, you can also define permissions at the document
          level.</para>

          <para>The procedure is similar to the document group
          permissions definition. Simply click on 'Define Permissions'
          on the document manager 'admin' page (see <xref
          linkend="FigureTheDocumentManagerAdministrationScreen" />)
          to attach access permissions to a document. Then select
          allowed user groups and submit.</para>

          <para>If you do not specify any access permissions for a
          document (or reset them to default), it inherits the access
          permissions from the document group it belongs to. However,
          when you define a permission for a document, it overrides
          the permissions defined for the group. Permissions set for
          the document can be either stricter or less strict than the
          group permissions.</para>

        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      <para><tip><title>Tip: Updating existing permissions</title>
        <para>There is a shortcut to update document and document group permissions. For project
        administrators or document manager administrators, the main 'Docs' page displays small lock icons
        next to protected documents and groups. Simply click on the lock to update permissions
        for the corresponding object.
      </para></tip></para>
    </section>
      </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

