<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
<chapter id="DocumentManager">
  <title>Document Manager</title>

  <para>Documentation is probably the second most important deliverable in a
    software project after the software work products themselves. CodeX
    provides a specific service to manage your project documents.</para>

  <para>The CodeX Document Manager is very basic and cannot compare
    in any way with specialized document repository like DocuShare. It
    is however very handy to publish documents that are critical to
    your community of users. Examples are: Installation, Adminstration
    or User Guide, API documentation, Frequently Asked Questions,
    etc...</para>

  <para>The Document Manager features are a follows:</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>The CodeX Document Manager can handle any type of
      document. However we strongly encourage editors to publish their
      documents in HTML and/or PDF to make it readable quickly and
      easily.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents are stored in groups (or folders). The folders are
        only one level deep which means you can&#39;t have subfolders in a
        folder.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents can be edited on line (if in text or HTML format).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>It is based on a Submit-Publish model where anybody can submit a
        new piece of documentation and it is up to the project team to decide
        if they want it to appear in the document collection or not
        (publishing)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Define access control rules for each document.</para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The intent of the Document Manager is to give a quick and easy
    access to the essential documents of a project, those which are really
    useful to the developers community or the users if the software is
    intended for end users. Typical examples are: User Guide, Administration
    Guide, API References&hellip; HTML is the format of choice because it is a
    standard format and it does not require any specific software to be read.</para>

  <section id="DocumentBrowsing">
    <title>Document Browsing</title>

    <para>To access the Document Manager select the &#34;Docs&#34; item from
      the Project Menu at the top of the screen of the Project Summary page.
      The welcome page of the Document Manager shows the list of all the
      documents published by the project by group.</para>

    <para>To read a document simply click on the title.</para>

    <figure id="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome">
      <title>A sample Document Manager welcome</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="DocumentSubmission">
    <title>Document Submission</title>

    <note><para>Before the first document is submitted to a project,
      the project members with &#34;Editors&#34; rights on the Document
      Manager must first create one document group (folder). A document has to
      be attached to a group in any case hence the need for at least one
      document group.</para></note>

    <para>Following the CodeX philosophy, any CodeX user can submit a
      document to a project team. To submit a new document, click on the
      &#34;Submit New Documentation&#34; link in the Document Manager menu (<xref
										  linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />). Then provide the
      Document Title, the document description and the body of the text.</para>

    <para>The document itself can either be copy-pasted directly in the
      document text area or uploaded with the help of the &#34;Browse&#34;
      button and the &#34;Upload&#34; checkbox. Then select a document group
      from the pull-down menu and click on the &#34;Submit Information&#34;
      button.</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: Referencing external documents</title>
    <para>It is sometime convenient to create placeholder documents
    that actually point to an external location like a DocuShare
    collection or a DocuShare file for instance. To do this, simply
    surround the document title with an HREF tag (hyperlink) pointing
    to the real location elsewhere on the Intranet (an example
    is given with Document #15 in <xref
    linkend="FigureTheDocumentManagerAdministrationScreen" />)</para>
    </tip></para>

    <para>The document title and summary can contain HTML tags. So you can
      use all sorts of typographic effects as well as pointers to other
      locations, etc.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="DocumentAdministration">
    <title>Document Administration</title>

    <para>The Document Manager provides a number of administration functions
      like validating the publication of a document, changing a document
      status or group, creating new document groups, etc.</para>

    <figure id="FigureTheDocumentManagerAdministrationScreen">
      <title>The Document Manager Administration screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
		     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentadmin.png" width="15.3cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="DocumentPublication">
      <title>Document Publication</title>

      <para>Once a new document has been submitted it must be
      validated before publication. In other words it won&#39;t be
      visible on the Document Manager welcome page until a project
      member who has &#34;Editor&#34; rights on the Document Manager
      has blessed it.</para>

      <para>To validate the publication of a document click on the
      &#34;Admin&#34; link in the Document Manager menu (<xref
      linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />). What you see
      next is a list of all documents submitted to the project sorted
      by status.  The documents with status &#34;Pending&#34; are
      listed at the top of the page. These documents have been
      submitted and are awaiting the project member review and
      blessing to become public.</para>
      
      <para>To validate a document, click on the document title. Go at
      the bottom of the next screen and change the Document status
      from Pending to Active. Additionally you can also define an
      access control policy for each document:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">World Readable</emphasis>: by
	  default a document can be viewed by any CodeX user including
	  anonymous users.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Registered Users
	Only</emphasis>:if you check the "Access to register
	user only" checkbox, access to the document will be restricted
	to registered users only. In addition all accesses to the
	document will be tracked down and stored in an audit trail
	that Project Adminstrators can view (see <xref
	linkend="SourceCodeAccessLogs"/>).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members Only</emphasis>:
	  access to the document can be restricted to members of the
	  project by changing its status to private. (more details on
	  the document status in <xref
	  linkend="DocumentUpdate"/>).</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Finally click on the "Submit Edit" button to validate the
      changes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="DocumentUpdate">
      <title>Document Update</title>

      <para>You can update a document in several ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		    spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>The title, description and document body can be modified. In
            this case you update the document content</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can change the group (or folder) a document belong to</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can change the document status</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To update a document click on the &#34;Admin&#34; link in the
        Document Manager menu (<xref
				     linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />) and then the
        &#34;Edit Documents&#34; item in the next menu. Then choose the
        document you want to update from the list. Click on the document title
        to make the document update screen appear. From here you can modify
        any part of the document, the group it belongs to or its status. The
        document status can take one of the following value:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
		    spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Active</emphasis>: the document is
            visible on the Document Manager welcome screen and can be read by
            any CodeX user.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Deleted</emphasis>: the document has
            been marked as deleted by the project team. However it is not
            physically deleted from the Document Manager and it can be
            undeleted.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Pending</emphasis>: the document is
            temporarily hidden form the public view of the Document Manager</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Hidden</emphasis>: the document is
            temporarily hidden form the public view of the Document Manager</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Private</emphasis>: the document is
            only visible to the project members not to external CodeX users.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="DocumentGroupManagement">
      <title>Document Group Management</title>

      <para>In the CodeX Terminology, a CodeX Document group is
      equivalent to a folder.</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheDocumentGroupsAdministrationScreen">
	<title>The Document Groups Administration screen</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
		       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_documentadmingroups.png" width="13cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To create, delete or change the name of document groups, click
        on the &#34;Admin&#34; link in the Document Manager menu (<xref
									linkend="FigureASampleDocumentManagerWelcome" />) and then the
        &#34;Edit Document Groups&#34; item in the next menu.</para>

      <para>To add a new group, use the &#34;New Group Name&#34; text field
        at the top of the screen and click on the &#34;Add&#34; button. You
        can also delete or rename an existing group by clicking on the
        appropriate link in the group list.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Document Groups ordering</title><para>By
        default the Document Groups are listed by alphabetical order on the
        Document Manager welcome page. If you want to impose your own order
        modify the group names by adding a number at the head of the document
        group (e.g. 1-, 2-, 3-...) . The groups will then be presented on the
        screen in the same order as the prefix numbers.</para></tip></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

