<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id: DocumentManager.xml 2681 2006-03-02 12:37:39Z guerin $
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
<chapter id="DocumentManagerPlugin">
  <title>Document Manager</title>

  <para>Documentation is probably the second most important deliverable in a
    software project after the software work products themselves. CodeX
    provides a specific service to manage your project documents.</para>

  <para>Although the CodeX Document Manager cannot be compared
    with dedicated document management systems, it
    is however very handy to publish documents that are critical to
    your community of users. Examples are: Installation, Administration
    or User Guide, API documentation, Frequently Asked Questions,
    etc...</para>

  <para>The Document Manager features are as follows:</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>The CodeX Document Manager can handle any type of
      document.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents are stored in folders. You can have subfolders in a
        folder.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Documents can be edited on line (if in text or HTML format).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Access control rules can be defined for each document or folder.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>Documents have properties and searchable metadata.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title>Structure</title>
    <para>You can structure as you want your document manager by creating folders 
    and subfolders to classify your documents.</para>
    <figure id="docman2_folders">
        <title>Folders and subfolders</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_folders.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Actions</title>
    <para>The Document Manager allows some actions on folders or documents. Those 
    actions are available or not depending on permissions. In order to display the 
    action panel, you must click on the pencil icon next to the document or folder 
    name.</para>
    <figure id="docman2_actions">
        <title>Actions</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_actions.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>We will now describe all the actions that can be performed on a folder
    or document.</para>
    <section><title>New Document</title>
      <para>This action is only available for folders and allow the user to create 
      a new document in a folder. When you select this action, a "new document" 
      window is displayed, where you can enter information concerning the new 
      document.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_newdocument">
          <title>Create a new document</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_newdocument.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The new document inherits the permissions of the parent folder.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Metadata</title>
        <para>The title of the document is mandatory. The user can provide a description 
        wich will be displayed on the browse view. Depending on the project, there 
        may be additionnal metadata required to classify the document.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Document Type</title>
        <para>4 types of documents are available :</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Empty:</emphasis> the document will have no type. The user will be able to change the type after creation.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Link:</emphasis> allow the user to target a document 
            with a URL. The document will not be stored locally in the docman.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Wiki:</emphasis> the document could be created with 
            the wiki service. Just enter the name of the corresponding wiki page.
            You can also use an existing wiki page name.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>File:</emphasis> any type of document could be uploaded.
            From a powerpoint presentation, to a simple picture or a full office 
            document. Files are versionned, so you can add new versions on existing 
            document.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Embedded file:</emphasis> html or plain text can be 
            edited online. Embedded files are versionned.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Location</title>
        <para>By default, the system creates a document in the folder that was selected.
        The user can also choose another folder. He can also select the position 
        of the new document in the folder: at the beginning or at the end.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>New Folder</title>
      <para>This action is only available for folders and allow the user to create 
      a sub folder in a folder.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_newfolder">
          <title>Create a new folder</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_newfolder.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The new folder inherits the permissions of the parent folder.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Properties</title>
        <para>Like for documents, the title of the folder is mandatory. The user can 
        provide a description wich will be displayed on the browse view. 
        Depending on the project, there may be additionnal properties required to classify 
        the document.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Location</title>
        <para>Like for documents, by default, the system creates a folder in the folder 
        that was selected. The user can choose another folder. He can also select 
        the position of the new folder in the parent folder: at the beginning or at the end.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Properties</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to view the properties of a document or
      folder. If he has enough permissions, he will be able to modify those properties.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_properties">
          <title>Display and edit properties</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_properties.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <para>From the property panel, it is possible to view/edit permissions, history 
    and actions. There are also shortcuts to these panels in the initial "Actions" 
    window.</para>

    <section><title>Notifications</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to be notified when an item is modified. Therefore, he will be alerted about the creation of a document in a folder, about the update of a document, about its move, ... He just has to check the dedicated checkbox.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_notifications">
          <title>Notifications</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_notifications.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>    
    
    <section><title>History</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to see logs and old versions (if available).</para>
      <figure id="docman2_history">
          <title>Update a link</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_history.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Update</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to update the name of a wiki page or the url of a link.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_update">
          <title>Update a link</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_update.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>New version</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to update a new version of a file or an embedded file.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_newversion">
          <title>Create a new version for embedded file</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_newversion.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Permissions</title>
      <para>This action allows the user to manage the permissions of a document 
      or folder. Permissions for folders can be applied recusively to its hierarchy.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_permissions">
          <title>Define permissions</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_permissions.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>There is 3 types of permissions.</para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Readers</title>
        <para>Those who can "read" a document or access the content of a folder.</para>
        <para>"read" means access to the document, see it in the browse view, 
        see its properties or metadata, see its history.</para>
        <para>Please note that if a user cannot read a folder, then he cannot access 
        to all of its subitems whatever their permissions, even deep in the hierarchy.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Writers</title>
        <para>Writers are readers who can also modify the document.</para>
        <para>"Modify" means update a new version, modify the link or the wiki 
        page name, edit properties, move the item or delete it.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Managers</title>
        <para>Managers are writers who can also set permissions on a document or folder and can access to logs.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Move</title>
      <para>Documents or folders can be moved elsewhere in the project documentation.</para>
      <para>They can only be moved in a folder where you have write permissions.</para>
      <para>You can move an item in different ways.</para>
      <para>The traditionnal way is to select move from the popup menu. You will 
      be able to choose the target folder (or let it in the same folder) and the 
      new position (at the beginning, at the end or at a specific position). The 
      permissions of the item will not be changed.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_move">
          <title>Move a document</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_move.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>If you just want to reorder a folder and move some of its items 
      relatively to each other, you can click on shortcuts next to "move" item 
      in the popup menu : up, down, at the beginning or at the end.</para>
      <figure id="docman2_move_shortcuts">
          <title>Shortcuts to move a document inside a folder</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG" 
                fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_docman2_move_shortcuts.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section><title>Delete</title>
      <para>Documents or folders can be deleted. If the user wants to delete a 
      folder, he will be warned that all subitems will be deleted (if the user has enough permissions).</para>
      <para>To be able to delete an item, the user must have write permissions on the parent folder.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section><title>Administration</title>
    <section>
      <title>Permissions</title>
      <para>This section defines who can administrate the document manager.</para>
      <para>Document manager administrators have all access to all items of the manager.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Display preferences</title>
      <para>This section allows you to define the default view for the document manager. The settings will be overridden by user preferences.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Properties</title>
      <para>This section manage the properties of documents. Each property can be edited during document submission and updated in the document properties panel.</para>
      <para>There is no specific permissions. If a user can read(modify) a document, he can read(modify) all of its properties.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

