<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="FileRelease">
    <title>File Release</title>

    <section id="SourceCodeReleaseGuidelines">
      <title>Source Code Release: Guidelines</title>

      <para>There are 2 ways by which project administrators can
      provide access to their project source code on CodeX: the
      software configuration management repository (CVS or Subversion)
      and the File Release mechanism. At first glance, having two
      distinct CodeX services seems redundant. However both have been
      developed with different objectives and target audience in mind
      and they are very much complementary. Providing both is
      definitely a plus for your visitors.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The SCM repository</emphasis>
          provides a full access to your source code including its
          entire version history. However accessing the source code
          via SCM tools requires that the CodeX user installs specific
          software on his machine. Not everybody is capable or willing
          to do so. SCM access is well suited for CodeX users who want
          to get deeper in the project code, add some new extensions,
          fix bugs and contribute changes back to the project
          team. Please be awre that certain projects decide to
          restrict the access to the SCM to project members
          only. Hence the importance of the file release
          mechanism.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The File Release
          mechanism</emphasis> allows you to deliver pre-packaged
          version of the source code and/or binaries in one or several
          archive file (zip, tar, jar,...) that an authorized user can
          easily download from the CodeX Web site. No specific tools
          or knowledge is required. Besides possibly providing
          pre-packaged source code it is also considered a very good
          practice to provide ready-to-use binary version of your
          software to make developers life even easier.  The File
          Release service is well suited for people who want to start
          using your software without any further delay.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As you can see both services are fundamentally different in nature
      and we strongly encourage project teams to use both of them. In order to
      help project teams understand why these two services are highly
      complementary a typical project life cycle is documented on <xref
      linkend="FigureATypicalSoftwareDevelopmentLifeCycleOnCodeX" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseJargon">
      <title>File Release Jargon</title>

      <para>Before we get further into the description of the File Release
      service let&#39;s review the terms used throughout this section. These
      terms are key for the understanding of the File Release mechanism both
      for users and administrators (see <xref
      linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseStructure" />).</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseStructure">
        <title>The File Release Structure</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../slides/en_US/File_Release.png" width="12cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Packages</emphasis> :These are the
          topmost entities visible in the File Release service. A package is a
          container for one or several Releases. In general a package do
          correspond with high-level deliverables of your software products.
          Let&#39;s assume that your team is working on a database engine.
          Possible packages could be DB-engine for the database engine itself
          and DB-drivers for the database drivers like ODBC or JDBC drivers. A
          third package DB-Docs could also be created to deliver the
          documentation in a separate container.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Releases</emphasis>: A release is a
          collection of individual files that were all frozen and time stamped
          at a given moment in time. In that sense it is also a container like
          a package but one level below. The files contained in a release
          generally correspond to a given version (also called release) of
          your software. Building on the database example above we could
          imagine than the DB-engine package has release 1.0, release 1.1 and
          release 2.0beta available. DB-drivers could have release 1.0 as well
          but no release 1.2 because the 1.0 drivers also work with the
          release 1.2 of DB-engine. In other words release naming can be
          completely independent from one package to another.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis>: files are the basic
          entities that one can find in a release. Again building on the
          database engine example, we can imagine that the release 1.0 of
          package DB-engine contains the file db-engine-src-1.0.zip for the
          source file and db-engine-win32-1.0.zip for the pre-compiled Windows
          version. When release 1.2 of the DB-engine package pops up, we could
          have files db-engine-src- 1.2.zip for the source file and
          db-engine-win32-1.2.zip for the pre-compiled Windows version and a
          new file called db-engine-linux-intel-1.2.zip for the pre-compiled
          Linux version running on Intel hardware. We haven&#39;t said a word
          about the DB-docs package. May be it is still empty for the moment
          ;-)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note><para>At first glance, this structure may appear a bit
      complex. However this is really the kind of structure a project team
      should aim at to make their deliverables easy to understand and easy to
      access for the community. Thinking about the structure of your
      software and documentation deliverables ahead of time can help you
      structure your team, your working processes (e.g. build and test
      process) in the right way. Do not overlook this part of your project.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseBrowsingandDownload">
      <title>File Release Browsing and Download</title>

      <para>The latest version of each project package (if any) is always
      visible on the Project Summary page (see <xref
      linkend="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage" />). The latest version can
      immediately be downloaded by clicking on the &#34;Download&#34; link or visit the
      complete list of packages and release by clicking on the &#34;[View ALL
      project files]&#34; link.</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseScreenOfTheCodeXProject">
        <title>The File Release screen of the CodeX Administration project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_filereleasedownloads.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The first example given on <xref
      linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseScreenOfTheCodeXProject" />
      shows the File Release screen of the CodeX Administration project.
      </para>
      
      <section id="FileReleaseBrowsingPackages">
        <title>Browsing packages</title>
        <para>
        As explained in the <xref linkend="FileReleaseJargon" />, projects 
        can contain several packages. In the example, 
        the project has three packages called &#34;CodeX Installation ISO Image&#34;,
        &#34;CodeX specifics themes&#34; and &#34;CodeX CLI&#34;.
        </para>
        <para>
        The content of each package can be hidden by clicking the 
        <emphasis>minus</emphasis> icon located just before the package name.
        This can help for visibility reasons if your project has lots of packages 
        and releases.
        To expand a collapsed package, simply click the <emphasis>plus</emphasis>
        icon before the package name.
        By default, all the packages are expanded.
        </para>
        <para>
        CodeX gives you the opportunity to monitor the packages. Like this, 
        you will be notifyed when a new release is available, or if a release 
        is updated, etc.
        In order to monitor a package, click the <emphasis>bell</emphasis> icon 
        located after the package name.
        If you're already monitoring the package, there is a red sign on the bell.
        If you don't monitor the package, the bell has a green <emphasis>plus</emphasis>
        on it.
        </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="FileReleaseBrowsingReleases">
        <title>Browsing releases</title>
        <para>
        A package can contain several releases. In the example,
        the package &#34;CodeX Installation ISO Image&#34; contains 8 releases 
        from 2.4 to 3.0.1 listed in chronological order. Each release contains a 
        certain number of files.
        </para>
        <para>
        Like packages, the content of the releases can be hidden to enhance 
        visibility. The mechanism is the same: click the <emphasis>plus</emphasis> 
        and <emphasis>minus</emphasis> icons to expand/collapse the release content.
        By default, only the first release of each package (which is the latest one) 
        is expanded.
        </para>
        <para>After each release name, the icon reresenting a text file let you 
        read the notes and the changelog of the current release.
        </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="FileReleaseDonwloadingFiles">
        <title>Downloading files</title>
        <para>
        Each release contains a certain number of files to be downloaded.
        In the case of the release 3.0.1, two ISO image archives can be downloaded.
        Files that belong to the other releases are hidden in this example.
        To make them visible, just click the small <emphasis>plus</emphasis> 
        that stands just before the name of the release.
        Some file information is given, like the size, the type of file, the 
        architecture (if it is relevant) the date and the number of downloads.
        To download a file, you just have to click the name of the file and follow 
        the instructions.
        </para>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseDelivery">
      <title>File Release Delivery and Administration</title>

      <para>This section is for project admins and file admins only. 
      It goes through a detailed explanation of the File Release delivery process. 
      This is a 2-step process:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Package Creation</emphasis>: Create one
          or several packages. This must only be done once. When packages are
          in place you can add a new release or update an existing one in them 
          at any time.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Release Creation</emphasis>: Once a
          package has been created, you can add (and update) releases to it</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      
      <para>When you are project admin or file admin, you are able to perform 
      the admin actions on the File Release System home page. (See 
      <xref linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseAdminScreenOfTheCodeXProject" />
          <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseAdminScreenOfTheCodeXProject">
            <title>The File Release screen of the CodeX Administration project, when you are admin</title>
    
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_filereleasedownloadsadmin.png" width="15.3cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
      </para>
      
      <section id="PackageAdministration">
        <title>Package Administration</title>
        
        <para>To administrate packages, you must be project admin or file 
        admin. Package creation and modification are nearly the same.
        </para>
        
        <section id="PackageCreation">
        <title>Package Creation</title>
        
        <para>To create a package, you just have to click the [add a package] 
        link located on the top of the File Release screen.
        Then, fill the form, giving the package name, its relative rank on the 
        File Release screen, and its status:
        
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Package Name</emphasis>: this is the
                name of the package. The name of the package must be unique in a 
                project.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on screen</emphasis>: the rank 
                indicates the position the packages will be displayed in the screen.
                You can choose the value: 'at the beginning', 'at the end', or after 
                every other package.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: an active package 
                will be displayed, whereas a package with a hidden status won't 
                appear on the File Release screen. For project admins or file admins,
                the hidden packages are displayed in italic, in order to update them.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section id="PackageModification">
        <title>Package Modification</title>
        
        <para>To update a package, just click the [edit] icon located after each 
        package name. Then, the modification form is the same than the creation one, 
        except that you can set read permissions on the package 
        (see <xref linkend="FigureAPartOfThePackageAdministrationScreenCodeXProject" />).
        </para>
        <figure id="FigureAPartOfThePackageAdministrationScreenCodeXProject">
          <title>Package Edition Screen of the CLI package, in the CodeX Administration project</title>
    
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_filereleasepackageadmin.png" width="10cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
          
        <para>A project member with the 'File Manager Admin' right
        (see <xref linkend="UserPermissions" />) can attach access
        permissions to any existing package.
        </para>

        <para>By default, permissions attached to a package apply to
        all releases and files that belong to this package.  But you
        may also set different permissions to specific releases (see
        below).</para>

        </section>
     </section>

      <section id="ReleaseAdministration">
        <title>Release Administration</title>
        
        <para>To administrate releases, you must be project admin or file 
        admin. Release creation and modification are the same.
        </para>
        
        <section id="ReleaseCreation">
        <title>Release Creation and modification</title>
        
        <para>Once a package has been created you can immediately start adding
        releases to it. Click on the [Add a Release] link of the appropriate 
        package (see <xref linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseAdminScreenOfTheCodeXProject" />).
        </para>
        
        <para>The release creation and modification process is really easy to 
        perform. It can be divided into 6 steps, but some are optional.
        (see <xref linkend="FigureTheReleaseModificationScreenOfTheCodeXProject" />).
        In every case, you can update the release at any time
        </para>
        
        <figure id="FigureTheReleaseModificationScreenOfTheCodeXProject">
          <title>The release update screen of the CodeX project</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_frsreleases.png" width="15.3cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 1 - Give Release properties</emphasis></para>
            <para>The first step is the only one mandatory to create a release.
            It gives you a chance to modify the package of the release, 
            the release date, and the status of the release. You also have to provide the 
            release name.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 2 - Upload and attach files to the release (optional)</emphasis></para>
            <para>This step is optional in the way that you can add the files 
            after having create the release, but of course, a release should contain 
            at least one file to be relevant.
            As explained above multiple files can be attached to the
            same release. To attach a file, click the [add file] link.
            Then, a select box appear, in order to select the file to attach.
            There is two solution to attach a file:
            
            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Direct Upload</emphasis>: 
                you can upload the file via the Web interface by using the 
                &#34;Local file - Browse&#34; option in the pull down menu and
                pointing to the appropriate file on your local disk.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">FTP / SCP</emphasis>: upload
                your file via ftp or scp and then select the
                appropriate file name from the &#34;FTP/SCP Files list &#34;
                in the pull down menu.</para>
                <para>
                    <tip><title>Tip: How to upload files using FTP or SCP</title>
                    <para>CodeX server offers an upload mechanism via FTP (ou SCP). 
                    To upload your files, follow the instructions given when you 
                    click the <emphasis>?</emphasis> next to the [add file] link.
                    Alternatively, if you are a MS Windows user, you can also
                    see the FTP Incoming space directly from Windows Explorer and drag
                    and drop your files in there (see <xref
                    linkend="MSWindowsSharedResources" />). Then click the 
                    [Refresh File list] link to see your files.</para></tip>
                </para>
                <para>Before you upload the files make sure you gave them names
                that will speak to CodeX users. Ideally the file names should
                include the release label in it and any other extension telling
                whether it is a source file or a binary file.</para>
                </listitem>
                <para>After attaching a file to the release, you
                can provide additional information for each of them. For each file
                you can specify the hardware architecture the file is going to run
                on and what is the file type (source, binary or documentation and
                what type of archive it is). This step is not mandatory but
                assigning the right type and hardware architecture to each file is
                useful to your visitors.</para>
            
                <para><tip><title>Tip: Always compress your deliverables</title><para>
                In order to save disk space on the CodeX server as well as on CodeX
                users&#39; machine and minimize network bandwidth consumption
                always compress your deliverables. Use Winzip on Windows and compress, 
                gzip or even better bzip2 on Linux/Unix machines.</para></tip></para>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para> 
         </listitem>
         
         <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 3 - Add Release Notes and/or Changelog (optional)</emphasis></para>
            <para>With the release, you can also provide notes or changelog, and 
            even both! You can either cut and paste or upload Release Notes and ChangeLog.
            To upload a release note or a changleog, click the <emphasis>Upload</emphasis> link.
            </para>
            
            <para>The Release Notes is typically a short (10 to 20 lines) and
            high-level document that summarizes the new features delivered in
            this release with a focus on the user visible changes (new UI, new
            functions, new APIs...). This is an important document and all new
            releases should definitely have one. Release Notes are immensely
            helpful to the community to determine whether they need to
            upgrade to the next release.</para>

            <para>The ChangeLog is a much more technical document. It contains
            all bugs fixed in this new release as well as any change in the
            design or the architecture. This document is not as critical as
            the previous one to the normal end-user but it is absolutely
            pivotal for those who use your software in other development or
            integration activities.</para>

            <para><tip><title>Tip: Generate a Changelog file easily</title><para>If
            you use CVS as you version control system you can very easily
            generate a well formatted and informative Changelog file. The
            cvs2cl utility available at <ulink
            url="http://www.red-     bean.com/cvs2cl">http://www.red-
            bean.com/cvs2cl</ulink> automatically extract all the CVS commit
            messages, aggregate them with modification dates and author name
            and format them in a nice way. This is a very good basis for a
            Changelog document.</para></tip></para>
            
          </listitem>
        
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 4 - Set permissions to the Release (optional)</emphasis></para>
            <para>By default, releases have no specific access permissions: 
            access to all files is granted to any CodeX registered user 
            (anonymous users are not allowed to download release files). 
            However, in some cases, you might want to limit the users allowed 
            to download your software. In these specific cases, you can restrict 
            access permissions to your packages and releases to specific user groups. 
            See <xref linkend="UserGroups" /> for more information on user groups.
            To define or to change the permissions on a release, click the [view/change]
            link in the permissions frame.
            </para>
            <para>Package and release permissions are enforced at two different levels:
            <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">File List:</emphasis>
            When a user is not granted access to a package or release,
            then the package or release is not listed in the 'File' main
            page, so s/he does not know that the file
            exists.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Download:</emphasis> If
            a user finds or forges a download link for an unauthorized
            file, the download will still fail. The system systematically
            re-checks for permissions when files are requested for
            download.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>If you do not specify any access permissions for a
            release (or reset them to default), it inherits the access
            permissions from the package it belongs to. However, when
            you define a permission for a release, then it overrides the
            permissions defined for the package.</para>

            <para>The permissions set for the release can be either
            stricter or less strict than the package permissions.
            </para>

          </listitem>
        
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 5 - Submit a News (optional)</emphasis></para>
            <para>This step is optional in the sense that you can skip it 
            if you want. This step gives the opportunity to project admin to 
            submit a news about the release they've just created (if you're 
            not project admin or news admin, you won't see this step). A default 
            subject and message are pre-filled. You are of course free to modify 
            it. The news will be displayed on your project summary page.
            It is a good way to advertise the users that a new release have been done.
            The news will also appear in the news administration page, like others.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 6 - Send e-mail notification (optional)</emphasis></para>
            <para>This step is optional in the sense that it may not show up
            on your screen. If some CodeX users monitor your package, this step
            will tell you how many of them are doing so. CodeX gives you the
            freedom to send an e-mail notification or not to the users who
            expressed interest in your packages. Do not bypass this step,
            always inform your community of users and developers.</para>
            
            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            
            <para><tip><title>Tip: Always include a useful README file</title><para>When
            you prepare your files for release make sure that you include a
            README file in the top directory of each file that a user can
            download. And pack this README with useful information like the
            address of your CodeX site, the Mailing list you have put in place
            for your project, how to submit a bug or a support to the project
            team (via CodeX of course)</para></tip></para>
            
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ManageProcessorsList">
    <title>Processor List Administration</title>
      <para>
          Project admins and file admins can manage the processor list per project. 
          The processor is an (optional) attribute of a released file. 
          Depending the project or working domain, you could be 
          interested in adding processors to the existing list.
          To do it, follow the admin link of the File Release System.
          Then, you have the list of the available processors. 
          System processors are not editable. 
          The other processors are specifics to the current project. 
          You can edit them, delete them, as well as create new ones.
          A processor has a name and a rank in the processor list.
      </para>
  </section>
    
    
 </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

