<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="FileRelease">
    <title>File Release</title>

    <section id="SourceCodeReleaseGuidelines">
      <title>Source Code Release: Guidelines</title>

      <para>There are 2 ways by which project administrators can provide
      access to their project source code on CodeX: the CVS repository and the
      File Release mechanism. At first glance, having two distinct CodeX
      services seems redundant. However both have been developed with
      different objectives and target audience in mind and they are very much
      complementary. Providing both is definitely a plus for your visitors.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The CVS repository</emphasis> provides a
          full access to your source code including its entire version
          history. However accessing the source code via CVS requires that the
          CodeX user has CVS installed on their machine and knows enough about
          CVS to checkout a working copy. Not everybody is capable or willing
          to do so. CVS access is well suited for CodeX users who want to get
          deeper in the project code, add some new extensions, fix bugs and
          contribute changes back to the project team.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The File Release mechanism</emphasis>
          allows you to deliver pre-packaged version of the source code and/or
          binaries in one or several archive file (zip, tar, jar,...) that a
          CodeX user can easily download from the CodeX Web site. No specific
          tools or knowledge is required. Besides pre-packaged source code it
          is also considered a very good practice to provide ready-to-use
          binary version of your software to make developers life even easier.
          The File Release service is well suited for people who want to start
          playing with your software and see how it can help them in their own
          work. This type of user probably doesn&#39;t want to bother with all
          the intricacies of your source code to start with. As time goes or
          if need be they may be tempted to look into it but this is
          definitely not their first objective. Hence the importance of
          providing pre-compiled version of your software.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As you can see both services are fundamentally different in nature
      and we strongly encourage project teams to use both of them. In order to
      help project teams understand why these two services are highly
      complementary a typical project life cycle is documented on <xref
      linkend="FigureATypicalSoftwareDevelopmentLifeCycleOnCodeX" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseJargon">
      <title>File Release Jargon</title>

      <para>Before we get further into the description of the File Release
      service let&#39;s review the terms used throughout this section. These
      terms are key for the understanding of the File Release mechanism both
      for users and administrators (see <xref
      linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseStructure" />).</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseStructure">
        <title>The File Release Structure</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../slides/en_US/File_Release.png" width="12cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Packages</emphasis> :These are the
          topmost entities visible in the File Release service. A package is a
          container for one or several Releases. In general a package do
          correspond with high-level deliverables of your software products.
          Let&#39;s assume that your team is working on a database engine.
          Possible packages could be DB-engine for the database engine itself
          and DB-drivers for the database drivers like ODBC or JDBC drivers. A
          third package DB-Docs could also be created to deliver the
          documentation in a separate container.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Releases</emphasis>: A release is a
          collection of individual files that were all frozen and time stamped
          at a given moment in time. In that sense it is also a container like
          a package but one level below. The files contained in a release
          generally correspond to a given version (also called release) of
          your software. Building on the database example above we could
          imagine than the DB-engine package has release 1.0, release 1.1 and
          release 2.0beta available. DB-drivers could have release 1.0 as well
          but no release 1.2 because the 1.0 drivers also work with the
          release 1.2 of DB-engine. In other words release naming can be
          completely independent from one package to another.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Files</emphasis>: files are the basic
          entities that one can find in a release. Again building on the
          database engine example, we can imagine that the release 1.0 of
          package DB-engine contains the file db-engine-src-1.0.zip for the
          source file and db-engine-win32-1.0.zip for the precompiled Windows
          version. When release 1.2 of the DB-engine package pops up, we could
          have files db-engine-src- 1.2.zip for the source file and
          db-engine-win32-1.2.zip for the precompiled Windows version and a
          new file called db-engine-linux-intel-1.2.zip for the precompiled
          Linux version running on Intel hardware. We haven&#39;t said a word
          about the DB-docs package. May be it is still empty for the moment
          ;-)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note><para>At first glance, this structure may appear a bit
      complex. However this is really the kind of structure a project team
      should aim at to make their deliverables easy to understand and easy to
      access for the community. Thinking about the structure of your
      software and documentation deliverables ahead of time can help you
      structure your team, your working processes (e.g. build and test
      process) in the right way. Do not overlook this part of your project.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseBrowsingandDownload">
      <title>File Release Browsing and Download</title>

      <para>The latest version of each project package (if any) is always
      visible on the Project Summary page (see <xref
      linkend="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage" />). The latest version can
      immediately be downloaded by clicking on the Download link or visit the
      complete list of packages and release by clicking on the [View ALL
      project files] link.</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseScreenOfTheDataGlyphToolkitProject">
        <title>The File Release screen of the DataGlyph Toolkit project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_filereleasedownloads.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The first example given on <xref
      linkend="FigureTheFileReleaseScreenOfTheDataGlyphToolkitProject" />
      shows the File Release screen of the DataGlyph Toolkit project. This
      project only has one package called &#34;Xerox DataGlyph Toolkit&#34;
      with 5 releases in it from 3.0.5 to 3.1.0beta2 listed in chronological
      order. Each release contains an archive for the source code and another
      one with precompiled binaries (Java byte code here). Starting at release
      3.0.6 new files handling license key issues have been added.</para>

      <para>The second example comes from the Global Solutions Architecture
      project. The File Release structure is different from the previous one.
      The project has 2 separate packages: one for the GSA Toolkit and a
      second one for the DataBus. Clearly the release-numbering schemes for
      these 2 packages are completely independent. It is very likely that
      DataBus release 0.5 works with the 3 Toolkit releases names Auk, Booby
      and Condor (releases doesn&#39;t need to be numbers). In the second
      release of the Toolkit package the documentation was delivered as a
      separate file.</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheFileReleaseScreenOfTheGSAProject">
        <title>The File Release screen of the GSA project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_filereleasedownloads2.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="FileReleaseDelivery">
      <title>File Release Delivery</title>

      <para>This chapter is for project members only. It goes through a
      detailed explanation of the File Release delivery process. This is a
      3-step process:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Package Creation</emphasis>: Create one
          or several packages. This must only be done once. When packages are
          in place you can add a new release in them at any time.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Release Creation</emphasis>: Once a
          package has been created, you can add releases to it</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Release Configuration and Validation</emphasis>:
          When a release has been created you can use it to attach files to
          it, give it a release date, list the changes made in this release,
          etc.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <section id="PackageCreation">
        <title>Package Creation</title>

        <para>To create a package first go to the File Release delivery
        screen. To this end visit your Project Administration page and select
        the [Edit/Add File Release...] link in the lower right corner of the
        screen.</para>

        <para>The first time you enter this page no package is available.
        Adding new packages is as easy as typing the package name in the blank
        field at the bottom of the screen and push on the &#34;Create This
        package&#34; button. Once a package has been created you can modify
        its name and status. A package is either active, which means that it
        is visible to the CodeX users in the File Release service and in the
        Project Summary Page, or Hidden, which means that it is only visible 
        to the Project Administrators.
        Switching the status from Active to Hidden doesn&#39;t delete any
        attached releases and files.</para>

        <para>Whenever you update the name or the status don&#39;t forget to
        push on the &#34;Update&#34; button!</para>

        <figure id="FigureAPartOfThePackageAdministrationScreenGSAProject">
          <title>A part of the Package Administration screen - GSA project (3
          packages created, 2 active, 1 hidden)</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_frspackages.png" width="15.3cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="ReleaseCreation">
        <title>Release Creation</title>

        <para>Once a package has been created you can immediately start adding
        releases to it. Click on the [Add/Edit Releases] link of the
        appropriate package (see <xref
        linkend="FigureAPartOfThePackageAdministrationScreenGSAProject" />).</para>

        <para>The next screen is similar in spirit with Package Administration
        screen but this one deals with releases. The Release Administration
        screen allows you to create a new release by typing a name (with
        letters, numbers, punctuation symbols...) in the blank field at the
        bottom of the screen. You also have a last chance to assign this new
        release to the appropriate package by selecting the package name in
        the package menu box next to it. Then Click on the &#34;Create This
        Release&#34; button.</para>

        <figure id="FigureAPartOfTheGSAProjectReleaseScreen">
          <title>A part of the GSA project release screen</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_frsreleases.png" width="15.3cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="ReleaseConfigurationandValidation">
        <title>Release Configuration and Validation</title>

        <para>The next step after you have named a new release creation is to
        define its content. Please note that this step is used both to define
        the content of a new release and also to modify an existing one. To
        access the release configuration screen click on the [Edit This
        Release] link next to the release name on the Release Administration
        screen (see <xref linkend="FigureAPartOfTheGSAProjectReleaseScreen" />).</para>

        <para>The Release Configuration screen that is now in front of you is
        divided in 4 steps. It is quite a long page but the steps are
        documented on the screen and are easy to understand. Remember that
        each step has its own validation button and before you go the next you
        must validate the one you&#39;ve been working on.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 1 - Give Release information</emphasis></para>

            <para>The first step gives you a chance to modify some of the
            information you gave before like the release name, the status and
            the related package. You must also provide a Release Date and
            either cut and paste or upload Release Notes and ChangeLog</para>

            <para>The Release Notes is typically a short (10 to 20 lines) and
            high-level document that summarizes the new features delivered in
            this release with a focus on the user visible changes (new UI, new
            functions, new APIs...). This is an important document and all new
            releases should definitely have one. Release Notes are immensely
            helpful to the community to determine whether they need to
            upgrade to the next release.</para>

            <para>The ChangeLog is a much more technical document. It contains
            all bugs fixed in this new release as well as any change in the
            design or the architecture. This document is not as critical as
            the previous one to the normal end-user but it is absolutely
            pivotal for those who use your software in other development or
            integration activities.</para>

            <para><tip><title>Tip: Generate a Changelog file easily</title><para>If
            you use CVS as you version control system you can very easily
            generate a well formatted and informative Changelog file. The
            cvs2cl utility available at <ulink
            url="http://www.red-     bean.com/cvs2cl">http://www.red-
            bean.com/cvs2cl</ulink> automatically extract all the CVS commit
            messages, aggregate them with modification dates and author name
            and format them in a nice way. This is a very good basis for a
            Changelog document.</para></tip></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 2 - Upload and attach files to
            the Release</emphasis></para>

            <para>As explained above multiple files can be attached to the
            same release. Before the files can be attached one has to upload
            them on the CodeX server. To this end, the CodeX server offers an
            upload mechanism via FTP. To upload your files follow the
            instruction on the screen and don&#39;t forget to refresh the Web
            page to see the new uploaded files with the &#34;Refresh&#34;
            button. Alternatively, if you are a MS Windows user, you can also
            see the FTP Incoming space directly from Windows Explorer and drag
            and drog your files in there (see <xref
            linkend="MSWindowsSharedResources" />). Then refresh the CodeX Web
            page to see your files.</para>

            <para>Before you upload the files make sure you gave them names
            that will speak to CodeX users. Ideally the file names should
            include the release label in it and any other extension telling
            whether it is a source file or a binary file.</para>

            <para>Once your files have been uploaded check the box next to
            each of them and push on the &#34;Attach Marked Files&#34; button.</para>

            <para><tip><title>Tip: Always compress your deliverables</title><para>In
            order to save disk space on the CodeX server as well as on CodeX
            users&#39; machine and minimize network bandwidth consumption
            always compress your deliverables. Use Winzip
            on Windows and compress, gzip or even better bzip2 on Linux/Unix
            machines.</para></tip></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 3 - Gives additional information
            on each attached file</emphasis></para>

            <para>After all your files have been attached to the release, you
            can provide additional information for each of them. For each file
            you can specify the hardware architecture the file is going to run
            on and what is the file type (source, binary or documentation and
            what type of archive it is). This step is not mandatory but
            assigning the right type and hardware architecture to each file is
            useful to your visitors.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Step 4 - Send e-mail notification
            (optional)</emphasis></para>

            <para>This step is optional in the sense that it may not show up
            on your screen. If some CodeX users monitor your package, Step 4
            will tell you how many of them are doing so. CodeX gives you the
            freedom to send an e-mail notification or not to the users who
            expressed interest in your packages. Do not bypass this step,
            always inform your community of users and developers.</para>

            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            <para></para>
            
            <para><tip><title>Tip: Always include a useful README file</title><para>When
            you prepare your files for release make sure that you include a
            README file in the top directory of each file that a user can
            download. And pack this README with useful information like the
            address of your CodeX site, the Mailing list you have put in place
            for your project, how to submit a bug or a support to the project
            team (via CodeX of course)</para></tip></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="QuickFileRelease">
      <title>Quick File Release</title>

      <para>CodeX also provides you with a quick File Release mechanism. To
      access the short version of the Release Process click on the [Quick Add
      File Release...] link in the lower right corner of your Project
      Administration page. The Quick File Release page is a one step process
      where you can specify all the necessary information at the same time.
      The counterpart is that you can only attach one single file to a given
      release and not several as in the full File Release process</para>

      <para>In addition the Quick File Release screen allows you to upload the
      attached file in 2 different ways: <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
      spacing="compact"><listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">FTP</emphasis>:
      upload your file via ftp as above and then select the appropriate file
      name from the &#34;Select a File&#34; pull down menu.</para></listitem><listitem><para><emphasis
      role="underline">Direct Upload</emphasis>: you can upload the file via
      the Web interface by using the &#34;Browse&#34; button and pointing to
      the appropriate file on your local disk.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Don&#39;t forget to specify the hardware architecture and the file
      type. Then push on the &#34;Release File&#34; button at the bottom of
      the screen.</para>
      <para>If some CodeX users were monitoring the package, they will 
      automatically receive an email notification, unless you set the release
      status to 'Hidden'.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

