<!--
//
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, Codendi 2007-2008.
// This file is licensed under the GNU General Public License version 2. See the file COPYING. 
//
//
//
-->
  <chapter id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; is a free and Open Source Suite to improve management 
	of software projects and connect with team members. 
	With a single web-based solution, CTO, project managers, developers, quality managers 
	and other users can easily build, deploy smart and quality projects.</para>

    <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; provides tools for managing projects, tasks, changes, defects, 
	documents as well as version control, continuous integration and social collaboration. </para>

    <para>With &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;, you will be able to:</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem><para>plan and monitor projects,</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>manage software development lifecycle: source code, builds...,</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>track requirements, tasks, incidents, etc.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>produce documents and releases,</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>favour collaboration between project members.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
    <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; 's high customization capability enables you to tailor each tool to your processes and business requirements. More info on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; features</para>
	
	<para>We want you to experience the full power of &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; technology. So we do not distinguish between a Enterprise version and 
	a Community version. In the same idea, we provide you in this guide all useful information and good practices to get the most of Tuleap Suite.</para>
    
	<para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team makes great work to make this guide updated to every new release. Do not hesitate to help us improve it, 
	share your experience and tips: write to the mailing list tuleap-devel</para> 
	
	<para>Enjoy &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; capabilities and let us know how you use it!</para>

    <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team</para>

    <figure id="FigureTheCodendiHomePage">
      <title>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Home Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_homepage.png" width="15.5cm"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("Codendi_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

