<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id: 
//
//	Originally written by Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The goal of the Xerox Code eXchange Initiative (CodeX) is to
    transpose and apply the principles of Open Source [XOSP] into our own
    corporate environment. Establishing internal source code sharing as one of
    our core software engineering values will improve the quality of our
    software and the productivity of our development teams while providing a
    compelling, attractive and rich working environment.</para>

    <para>Thanks to the community building effect of software sharing,
    cooperation and trust should improve in between Xerox research, business
    groups and customer organizations. If properly utilized, CodeX can
    significantly improve our Time To Market and create more and better code
    with less work.</para>

    <para>The CodeX initiative is supported by a Xerox internal Web site of
    the same name that is available at <ulink url="http://codex.xerox.com/">http://codex.xerox.com/</ulink>.
    The CodeX web site is provided as a service to all Xerox software
    development teams who want to share their project source code with others
    inside Xerox. Since the site went live on January 12th, 2001 the CodeX
    site has been growing at a fast pace. To us this is a strong indicator
    that the software community in Xerox is alive and well. It is also asking
    for more communication and has a strong desire to establish bridges with
    the rest of Xerox. Further, it shows a desire to speed up the innovation
    process and to develop more flexible, better quality and more usable
    software in less time.</para>

    <para>Many Xerox software projects have already made CodeX their project
    home and project teams are now using CodeX services on a daily basis to do
    their job faster, cheaper and easier. The community is constantly giving
    us feedback on CodeX and we have responded with enhancements to CodeX that
    increase its ability to support your projects. One of the requests was to
    have a CodeX User Guide handy. That is why this document was created. The
    CodeX User Guide not only describes the CodeX features and services, but
    it is also packed with tips and guidelines to help you get the most out of
    CodeX and manage your project with a true source code sharing spirit.</para>

    <para>We hope that you enjoy working with CodeX. If so, keep talking about
    the CodeX initiative to fellow programmers and software management. CodeX
    users are our best advocates. Also keep in mind that this User Guide is
    yours and, following source code sharing principles, we welcome your
    corrections and contributions.</para>

    <para>Enjoy CodeX!</para>

    <para>The CodeX Team</para>

    <figure id="FigureTheCodeXHomePage">
      <title>The CodeX Home Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_homepage.png" width="15.5cm"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </chapter>
