<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// 
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="OtherServices">
    <title>Other Services</title>

    <section id="ShellAccount">
      <title>Shell Account</title>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Important Note</emphasis>: this
      feature can be deactivated by your CodeX site administrator and
      may therefore be unavailable in your organization.</para>

      <para>If the CodeX administrators have enabled this feature,
      each registered user receives its own Unix shell account on the
      CodeX Shell Account server. You can access your CodeX Shell
      Account in 2 ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">SSH</emphasis>: the secured remote shell
          is the preferred way to connect to the CodeX Shell Account server.
          SSH clients are available for all platforms (Windows, Linux, Unix
          and Mac) and allows a secure link with your personal directories. It
          also provides you with a number of other useful utilities like scp
          for remote file transfer. To access your account type the
          following command and use your CodeX login and password to
          authenticate yourself:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
ssh -l loginname &SYS_SHELL_HOST;
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Telnet</emphasis>: telnet comes standard
          with Windows and Unix environment. Use the following command to
          connect to the CodeX Shell Account server and provide your login and
          password as requested. (Remark: on some site telnet might be
          disabled for security reasons)</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
telnet &SYS_SHELL_HOST;
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Whether you use SSH or Telnet, a welcome banner will be displayed
      right after you log in. This message tells you what are the directories
      you are allowed to access. Use the Unix &#34;cd&#34; command to change
      the current working directory. Once logged in and if you are a member of
      several projects you must specify for which project you are going to
      work in this shell session. To this end use the following command:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
newgrp projectname
</programlisting>

      <para>You can use this command as many time as you want during a shell
      session when you are about to do work for another one of your project.</para>

      <para></para>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="FTPStorageSpaces">
      <title>FTP Anonymous Storage Space</title>

      <para>Each project receives its own FTP storage, the Anonymous FTP Space.
      If you need a controlled access to your files, it is recommended to use 
      the web-based File Release System (<xref
        linkend="FileRelease" />).</para>

      <para>The anonymous FTP space can be used by the project
        members to upload any kind of documents or project data and
        deliverables they want. This storage will then be visible to
        any CodeX users and all files placed in this directory can be
        freely downloaded. So make sure that you use this storage
        space for world readable files only.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Anonymous Users access: use an ftp client to connect
            to <literal>&SYS_DOWNLOAD_HOST;</literal>. Use
            &#34;ftp&#34; as login and your email address as the
            password. Then <literal>cd
            /pub/projectname</literal> to access
            the FTP Anonymous space.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Project Members access: use an ftp client to connect
            to <literal>&SYS_DOWNLOAD_HOST;</literal>. Use CodeX
            login and password and then type <literal>cd
            /var/lib/codex/ftp/pub/projectname</literal>
            to access the FTP Anonymous space. From there project
            members have both read and write access which means that
            they can upload files.</para>

	    <para>To point to this storage space in your Web pages or
	    your email to other users simply use the following
	    URL:</para>

            <para><literal>ftp://projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/pub/projectname</literal></para>

          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="MSWindowsSharedResources">
      <title>MS Windows Shared Resources</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Important Note</emphasis>: this
    feature can be deactivated by your CodeX site administrator and
    may therefore be unavailable in your organization.</para>

	<para>Windows users (as well as Linux/Unix users equipped with Samba) can also use mapped
		network drives to access the following storage spaces from their Windows
		Explorer:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Your user home directory,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The various project home directories (where the project Web
          site is located)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The FTP incoming space where you can directly drag and drop
          your file releases instead of using FTP upload (See <xref
          linkend="ReleaseAdministration" />)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To access your CodeX shared resources, open your file explorer,
      browse the Entire Microsoft Network, open the &SYS_SAMBA_DOMAIN; domain and click on
      the CodeX machine. Use your CodeX login and password to connect to the
      resources (If they are not the same as your Windows login/password a
      dialog box will pop up asking for the appropriate CodeX login/password)</para>

      <para>Shared resources can also be directly accessed at:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>\\codex\your_login_name</literal> (User home
          directory - for all users)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>\\codex\Projects</literal> (All project directories -
          for project members)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>\\codex\Ftp_Incoming</literal> (FTP upload space -
          for project members)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Needless to say all read and write permissions put in place by
      CodeX to protect your data still apply to these shared resources.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="SoapAPI">
      <title>SOAP API</title>
      <para>CodeX provides a SOAP API to access CodeX through web-services.
            At this time, only session (login/logout) and tracker 
            services are available.
      </para>
      <para>A human-friendly description of the services is available at <ulink url="/soap/">
        http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/</ulink>. It is a list of
        services, with a description of each function, its input, ouput and documentation</para>
      <para>A more detailed description of the services is also available with 
      the more formal WSDL language at <ulink url="/soap/?wsdl">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/?wsdl</ulink>.
      The WSDL also includes the types definition.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="CodeXCLI">
      <title>CodeX Command Line Interface (CLI)</title>
      <para>Another way to use CodeX is to use the command line interface (CLI).
        It's a client application that use the SOAP API to interact with the 
        CodeX server. At this time, only session (login/logout) 
        and tracker services are available. The CLI is currently missing a few 
        features of the SOAP API (e.g. it is not possible to attach a file, 
        a CC address or a dependency to an artifact), and the mail notification is 
        not active with the CLI.
      </para>
      <para>The full CLI documentation is available at <ulink url="/documentation/cli/pdf/en_US/CodeX_CLI.pdf">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/documentation/cli/pdf/en_US/CodeX_CLI.pdf</ulink>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="CodeXEclipsePlugin">
      <title>CodeX Eclipse plugin</title>
      <para>CodeX provides a plugin for the Eclipse IDE. 
        This plugin will let you browse your artefacts, 
        modify them and create new ones whithin Eclipse 
        environment.
      </para>
      <para>The CodeX Eclipse plugin is to be deployed on Eclipse 3.2 and needs JRE 1.5</para>
      <para>The Eclipse plugin can be installed and updated with the updatesite mecanism.
        The CodeX update site for this plugin is: &SYS_UPDATE_SITE;
      </para>
      <para>
        To install the CodeX plugin with Eclipse update site mecanism, please follow the instructions below:
        <procedure>
            <step><para>In the Eclipse main toolbar, select <emphasis role="bold">Help > Software Update > Find and install...</emphasis></para></step>
            <step><para>Check <emphasis role="bold">Search for new features to install</emphasis>, then click Next</para></step>
            <step><para>Press the <emphasis role="bold">New Remote Site...</emphasis> button</para></step>
            <step>
                <para>Fill the dialog box with
                    <substeps>
                     <step><para><emphasis role="bold">Name:</emphasis> CodeX (for instance)</para></step>
                     <step><para><emphasis role="bold">URL:</emphasis> &SYS_UPDATE_SITE;</para></step>
                    </substeps>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step><para>Check the <emphasis role="bold">CodeX</emphasis> box (you can expand to see the feature details), and then press OK</para></step>
            <step><para>Eclipse will ask you to accept or not the license. If you want to accept the license, check "I accept the terms in the license agreement"</para></step>
            <step><para>Then click the <emphasis role="bold">Finish</emphasis> button.</para></step>
            <step><para>Eclipse will ask you to check the feature to install. Press the <emphasis role="bold">Install</emphasis> button</para></step>
            <step><para>Eclipse will download the feature and may need to restart to complete the installation</para></step>
            <step><para>Enjoy CodeX!</para></step>
        </procedure>
      </para>
      <para>The full Eclipe plugin documentation is available at <ulink url="/documentation/eclipse/pdf/en_US/CodeX_Eclipse_Plugin_User_Guide.pdf">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/documentation/eclipse/pdf/en_US/CodeX_Eclipse_Plugin_User_Guide.pdf</ulink>
      </para>
    </section>
    
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

