<!--
//
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, Codendi 2007-2008.
// This file is licensed under the GNU General Public License version 2. See the file COPYING. 
//
//
-->
  <chapter id="OtherServices">
    <title>Other Services</title>

    <section id="ShellAccount">
      <title>Shell Account</title>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Important Note</emphasis>: this
      feature can be deactivated by your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; site administrator and
      may therefore be unavailable in your organization.</para>

      <para>If the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; administrators have enabled this feature,
      each registered user receives its own Unix shell account on the
      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Shell Account server. You can access your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Shell
      Account in 2 ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">SSH</emphasis>: the secured remote shell
          is the preferred way to connect to the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Shell Account server.
          SSH clients are available for all platforms (Windows, Linux, Unix
          and Mac) and allows a secure link with your personal directories. It
          also provides you with a number of other useful utilities like scp
          for remote file transfer. To access your account type the
          following command and use your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; login and password to
          authenticate yourself:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
ssh -l loginname &SYS_SHELL_HOST;
</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Telnet</emphasis>: telnet comes standard
          with Windows and Unix environment. Use the following command to
          connect to the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Shell Account server and provide your login and
          password as requested. (Remark: on some site telnet might be
          disabled for security reasons)</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
telnet &SYS_SHELL_HOST;
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Whether you use SSH or Telnet, a welcome banner will be displayed
      right after you log in. This message tells you what are the directories
      you are allowed to access. Use the Unix &#34;cd&#34; command to change
      the current working directory. Once logged in and if you are a member of
      several projects you must specify for which project you are going to
      work in this shell session. To this end use the following command:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
newgrp projectname
</programlisting>

      <para>You can use this command as many time as you want during a shell
      session when you are about to do work for another one of your project.</para>

      <para></para>
      <para></para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="FTPStorageSpaces">
      <title>FTP Anonymous Storage Space</title>

      <para>Each project receives its own FTP storage, the Anonymous FTP Space.
      If you need a controlled access to your files, it is recommended to use 
      the web-based File Release System (<xref
        linkend="FileRelease" />).</para>

      <para>The anonymous FTP space can be used by the project
        members to upload any kind of documents or project data and
        deliverables they want. This storage will then be visible to
        any &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; users and all files placed in this directory can be
        freely downloaded. So make sure that you use this storage
        space for world readable files only.</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Anonymous Users access: use an ftp client to connect
            to <literal>&SYS_DOWNLOAD_HOST;</literal>. Use
            &#34;ftp&#34; as login and your email address as the
            password. Then <literal>cd
            /pub/projectname</literal> to access
            the FTP Anonymous space.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Project Members access: use an ftp client to connect
            to <literal>&SYS_DOWNLOAD_HOST;</literal>. Use &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
            login and password and then type <literal>cd
            &SYS_DATA_DIR;/ftp/pub/projectname</literal>
            to access the FTP Anonymous space. From there project
            members have both read and write access which means that
            they can upload files.</para>

	    <para>To point to this storage space in your Web pages or
	    your email to other users simply use the following
	    URL:</para>

            <para><literal>ftp://projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/pub/projectname</literal></para>

          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="SoapAPI">
      <title>SOAP API</title>
      <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; provides a SOAP API to access &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; through web-services.
            At this time, only session (login/logout) and tracker 
            services are available.
      </para>
      <para>A human-friendly description of the services is available at <ulink url="http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/">
        http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/</ulink>. It is a list of
        services, with a description of each function, its input, output and documentation</para>
      <para>A more detailed description of the services is also available with 
      the more formal WSDL language at <ulink url="http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/?wsdl">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/soap/?wsdl</ulink>.
      The WSDL also includes the types definition.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="CLI">
      <title>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Command Line Interface (CLI)</title>
      <para>Another way to use &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; is to use the command line interface (CLI).
        It's a client application that use the SOAP API to interact with the 
        &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; server. At this time, only session (login/logout) 
        and tracker services are available. The CLI is currently missing a few 
        features of the SOAP API (e.g. it is not possible to attach a file, 
        a CC address or a dependency to an artifact), and the mail notification is 
        not active with the CLI.
      </para>
      <para>The full CLI documentation is available at <ulink url="http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/documentation/cli/pdf/en_US/Codendi_CLI.pdf">http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/documentation/cli/pdf/en_US/Codendi_CLI.pdf</ulink>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

