<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="ProjectAdministration">
    <title>Project Administration</title>

    <para>Whenever you enter the Project Summary page of a given
    project or any of its service you&#39;ll see a menu item called
    Admin appears in the project menu.</para>

    <para>Only project members can access the Project Administration page. All
    other CodeX users are denied access to this part of a project.</para>

    <section id="ProjectAdministrationMenu">
      <title>Project Administration Menu</title>

      <para>In addition to the project main menu that was introduced in the
      description of the Project Summary page, the Project Administration page
      has its own menu. This menu is not redundant with the page content right
      below. Except for 1 or 2 items the menu and the page content give access
      to distinct parts of the administration space. So pay attention to both
      the Page Admin menu and the Page Admin content. In the following
      sections the Location label indicates where to find the corresponding
      administrative function.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="AddingRemovingUsers">
      <title>Adding/Removing Users</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>User administration in CodeX is easy. To add a new member to a
      project team one of the project administrator just has to type the login
      name of the invited member and click on the &#34;Add User&#34; button.
      If you don&#39;t know the login name of the new project member you want
      to add, open a new browser window on CodeX and use the search box in the
      CodeX Main Menu to search for the person&#39;s real name (first or last
      name or both) and don&#39;t forget to select &#34;People&#34; in the
      Search pull-down menu. The result list will show you the user real name
      and login name.</para>

      <para>Removing a project member is even easier. Just click on the trash
      icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="PNG"
      fileref="../../icons/trash.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>) next
      to the person&#39;s name to revoke his/her membership. Revoking
      membership has absolutely no effect on the history and the data
      integrity of the project. In other words all tracker artefacts assigned or submitted by this person will continue to show
      up as before in the project database. Only the ability of this person to
      perform project management tasks is affected. Also notice that in order
      to remove a project administrator from the project member list, another
      project administrator must first change the &#34;Project Admin&#34; flag
      of this user to &#34;No&#34; in the User Permission table. In other
      words, a Project Administrator cannot be removed from the project
      members as long as she has administrator privilege.</para>

      <note><para>You have probably noticed that project member&#39;s
      name on the Project Administration page are actually hyperlinks. On this
      page as well as in many other pages throughout CodeX a click on a login
      name leads you to the user page where you can know more about the user
      (including its location, phone/fax number, etc. extracted from the LDAP 
      Directory in real time) and send an e-mail message to this person
      directly via a Web form.</para></note>

      <figure id="FigureASampleProjectAdministrationPage">
        <title>A Sample Project Administration Page</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_projectadminpage.png" width="15.3cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectPublicInformation">
      <title>Project Public Information</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The &#34;Edit Public Info&#34; item of the Project Administration
      menu allows a project administrator to update the Project Description Elements:
      these are elements provided during the registration process.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="ProjectCategorization">
      <title>Project Categorization</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is where you can categorize your project. You can define up
      to 3 values for each of the 7 criteria used in the Software Map. If you
      cannot find any matching value in the predefined list do not hesitate to
      contact the CodeX Team.</para>
    </section>


    <section id="ServiceConfiguration">
      <title>Service Configuration</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The &#34;Service Configuration&#34; item of the Project Administration
      menu lists all services available to the project. Services are items listed 
      in the  &#34;Service Bar &#34; on top of each page: trackers, 
      CVS, homepage, documentation, etc. 
      The Service Configuration page allows a project 
      administrator to update, enable, disable or even create services.
      </para>

      <para>There are two kinds of services:</para>
 
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">System services</emphasis>:
          these services are defined by the site administrator and are common to
          all projects. They cannot be modified, except for their status 
          (enabled/disabled) and their position on the screen (see below).
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project services</emphasis>: 
          these services can be fully customized or deleted by the project administrator.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>There is one exception, the
          <emphasis role="bold">Home Page</emphasis> service is a
          system service but it can be customized with any URL. Each
          project hosted on CodeX has its own virtual Web server available on
          the CodeX site. By default the &#34;Home Page&#34; in the Project
          Service Bar links to this location (see <xref linkend="ProjectWebSite" /> for more details).
          If you want the Home Page of your project to link to some other
          locations on the Intranet or on the Web, simply replace
          the default value with your own Web location. Do not confuse your
          Project Home Page with your Project Summary page. The Project Home
          Page actually points to real Web Site whereas the Public Summary
          Page is just an entry point to access software related activities
          and deliverables.</para>


    <section id="ServiceCreation">
      <title>Creating or Updating a Service</title>
      <para>When creating or updating a service, one has to fill the following fields:</para>
     <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Service Label</emphasis>:
          This is the label that will be displayed in the Service Bar. It 
          should be as concise as possible.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Service Link</emphasis>:
          This is the URL of the service, i.e. the address the user will be 
          redirected to when clicking on the service label in the Service Bar.
          If the URL is absolute (i.e. starting with &#34;http://&#34;), the page
          will be loaded in a new window. Otherwise, it will be loaded in the 
          current window.
          </para>
          <para>A few keywords can be inserted into the link: they will be automatically replaced by their value:
          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$projectname</emphasis>:
              short name of the project
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$sys_default_domain</emphasis>: 
              domain of your CodeX server (e.g. &#34;&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;&#34;)
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$group_id</emphasis>: 
              project number.
              </para>
              <para></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$sys_default_protocol</emphasis>: 
              'https' if your server is configured in secure mode, 'http' otherwise.
              </para>
              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Service Description</emphasis>:
          Short description of the service. It will be displayed as a tooltip 
          when the mouse cursor is over the service label.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Enabled</emphasis>:
          Toggling this check box will simply disable (or enable)
          the service. Disabling a service just
          means that it no longer appears in the Service Bar and in the  
          Project Summary page of your
          project but all existing data related to this service remains
          untouched. In other words, re-enabling the service will restore
          the service in the exact same state it was when you first
          disabled it. See also &#34;Deleting a Service&#34; below. 
          </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on Screen</emphasis>:
	    this arbitrary number allows you to define the position of
	    this service in the Service Bar relative to other services. 
	    The services with smaller values will appear first. The
	    rank values don't have to be consecutive values. It is a
	    good idea to use values like 10, 20, 30,... so that it is
	    easy for you to insert new services in the future without
	    having to renumber all the services.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section id="ServiceDeletion">
      <title>Deleting a Service</title>

      <para>Project services can be deleted. They appear with a small
      trash icon in the service list. Just click on this icon to
      suppress the service from the database. The service data are
      however preserved.
      </para>
      <para>System services cannot be deleted. However, you can 
      disable them and they will not appear in the Service Bar.
      </para>
    </section>
    </section>


    <section id="ServicesAdministration">
      <title>Services Administration</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Admin page</emphasis></para>

      <para>The project administration page gives direct access to the
      administration of all services that have been activated for a
      given project. This is available in the form of a series of
      pointers located on the lower left part of the project
      administration page. Only project members with appropriate
      permission are allowed to access the CodeX services
      administration pages (see <xref linkend="UserPermissions"
      />).</para>

    </section>


    <section id="ReferenceConfiguration">
      <title>Reference Pattern Configuration</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The &#34;Reference Configuration&#34; item of the Project Administration
      menu lists all reference patterns available to the project. 
      The &#34;Reference Configuration&#34; page allows a project 
      administrator to update, enable, disable or even create reference patterns.
      </para>

    <section id="ReferenceOverview">
      <title>Reference Overview</title>

      <para>References are a powerful tool that allow cross-referencing of CodeX objects.
      Based on a text pattern, CodeX automatically creates hyperlinks to the desired object.
      </para>

      <para>When typing a follow-up comment or a commit message, any text containing the
      pattern "XXX #NNN" will be interpreted as a reference to the object of type XXX with ID number NNN.
      For instance, 'artifact #123' is recognized as a reference to artifact number 123, and 
      CodeX automatically creates a hyperlink that directly points to the details of artifact 123.
      </para>
      <para>You may also reference an object that belongs to another project. In that case, use 
      either 'XXX #group_id:NNN' or 'XXX #group_name:NNN' to reference object XXX number NNN 
      belonging to project which ID is 'group_id' or which short name is 'group_name'. 
      For instance, 'wiki #myproj:Welcome' is a reference to the 'Welcome' wiki page of the project 'myproj'.
      </para>
      <para>Some reference patterns may need more than one parameter. In this case, use '/' as a separator 
      between parameters. For example, 'wiki #Welcome/2' creates a reference to the wiki page named 'Welcome' at version '2'.
      </para>

      <para>There are two kinds of reference patterns:</para>

 
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">System reference patterns</emphasis>:
          these reference patterns are defined by the site administrator and are common to
          all projects. They cannot be modified, except for their status 
          (enabled/disabled).
          </para>
          <para>Most system references are related to a specific service. For example,
          'artifact', 'doc', 'file' or 'wiki' are respectively related to the tracker,
          document manager, file manager and Wiki services. In order to facilitate 
          the usage of such reference patterns, they are automatically enabled and disabled
          when the corresponding service is enabled/disabled. Still, it is always 
          possible to enable or disable those reference patterns manually.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project reference patterns</emphasis>: 
          these reference patterns can be created, modified or deleted by the project administrator.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>


    <section id="ReferencePredefined">
      <title>Predefined Reference Patterns</title>
<para>Here is a list of predefined reference patterns:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">art #num or artifact #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to artifact number 'num'. Note that 'num' is a system-wide number and is unique accross projects. This reference links to the artifact detail/update page. In addition to the 'art' and 'artifact' keywords, artifacts may be referenced using the related tracker short name. For example, an artifact in the bug tracker can be referenced with <emphasis role="bold">bug #NNN</emphasis>, a support request with <emphasis role="bold">sr #NNN</emphasis>, a task with <emphasis role="bold">task #NNN</emphasis> and a patch with <emphasis role="bold">patch #NNN</emphasis>. So, when you create a custom tracker, make sure that you specify a meaningful tracker short name.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">commit #num or cvs #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to CVS commit number 'num'. This is a system-wide number. The reference links to the commit details page: log message, impacted files, link to diff view, etc.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">rev #num or revision #num or svn #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to Subversion revision number 'num'. This is a project-specific number, so if you need to reference a revision belonging to another project, you should specify the project in the reference (e.g. 'rev #myproj:123'). The reference links to the subversion revision details page: log message, impacted files, link to diff view, etc.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">wiki #wikipage and wiki #wikipage/num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to a wiki page named 'wikipage'. The second format allows one to specify a wiki page version. Wiki pages are project specific, so if you need to reference a page belonging to another project, you should specify the project in the reference.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">doc #num or document #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to the document number 'num'. This is a system-wide number. Document numbers, or IDs, are visible in the 'Docs' main page by hovering over a document title with the mouse pointer. This reference links to the document itself.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">news #num</emphasis>: Reference to the news item number 'num'. This is a system-wide number. The reference links to the news item page, where you can add comments.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">forum #num and msg #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to forum number 'num' or to forum message number 'num'. Those are system-wide numbers. The first reference links to the forum welcome page, while the second one directly links to the message page, where you can view the message thread, and post a follow-up message.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">file #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to file number 'num'. This is a system-wide number. This kind of reference allows a direct download of a file that is part of a release. File numbers, or IDs, are visible in the 'Files' main page by hovering over a file name with the mouse pointer. This reference links to the file itself, so you might be prompted for a location to store the file. You may also have to accept the project license before downloading the file.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">release #num</emphasis>: 
        Reference to release number 'num'. This is a system-wide number. Release numbers, or IDs, are visible in the 'Files' main page by hovering over a release name with the mouse pointer. This reference links to the project file manager page, where the referenced release is highlighted in the list.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="ReferenceUsage">
      <title>Reference Usage</title>

<para>
While working in the development or the maintenance phase of a software project, it is vital to keep track of the changes made to the source code. This is what Version Control systems like CVS and Subversion do. In addition to keeping track of the source code change history it is often critical to relate the changes to the artifact (a task, a defect or a support request) that led the developers to make a change in the code. And conversely, when reading the artifact description it is also very helpful to immediately see how the change was implemented.
</para><para>
The integration of CVS and Subversion in CodeX precisely provide the CodeX users with this bi-directionnal cross-referencing mechanism. This is achieved through the use of references that are automatically detected by CodeX in either the follow-up comments of the project artifacts or in the messages attached to a CVS or SVN commit.
</para>
<para>The system is not limited to artifact and commit references, so you may also reference the forum message where the bug was found, the documentation that describes an issue, or the file that fixes it. The system is flexible enough to allow referencing of items that are not stored in CodeX. So you may now create your own reference pattern to link to an external document manager like DocuShare, or source code management tool like ClearCase</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: cross-reference artifacts and Source Code
      commits</title><para>It is considered a best practice to always
      reference a bug, a task or a support request in any of the log
      message attached to a Subversion or CVS commit. Similarly when closing
      the related artifact (task, bug,etc.) make sure you mention the
      revision or commit number in the follow-up comment. You will find this
      extremely convenient while trying to keep track of the changes
      and why they were made.</para></tip></para>


</section>


    <section id="ReferenceCreation">
      <title>Creating or Updating a Reference Pattern</title>
      <para>When creating or updating a reference pattern, one has to fill the following fields:</para>
     <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Reference Keyword</emphasis>:
          This is the keyword that triggers a reference creation when it is found.
          It should be concise and meaningful in order to facilitate readability.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Reference Description</emphasis>:
          Short description of the reference. It is displayed in a tooltip 
          when the mouse cursor is over an identified reference.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Reference Link</emphasis>:
          This is the URL pointed by the reference, i.e. the address the user will be 
          redirected to when clicking on a reference. 
          The URL does not need to point to the CodeX server: you may create references pointing to external pages.
          The page will be loaded in the current window.
          </para>
          <para>A few keywords can be inserted into the link: they will be automatically replaced by their value:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$projname</emphasis>:
              short name of the project.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$group_id</emphasis>: 
              project number.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$0</emphasis>: 
              The keyword extracted for this reference.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$1</emphasis>: 
              The first parameter in the reference.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$2</emphasis>: 
              The second parameter in the reference.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">$3...$9</emphasis>: 
              Up to nine parameters in the reference.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para> Examples:</para>
          <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            

          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">artifact #25</emphasis>: '$0' is 'artifact', '$1' is '25'</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">wiki #codex:Welcome/1</emphasis>: '$0' is 'wiki', '$1' is 'Welcome', '$2' is '1', '$projname' is 'codex'</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">myref #123:1/23/456</emphasis>: '$0' is 'myref', '$1' is '1', '$2' is '23', '$3' is '456' and '$group_id' is '123'</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">google #codex/xerox</emphasis>: '$0' is 'google', '$1' is 'codex', '$2' is 'xerox'. If you define the reference pattern 'google', with its link pointing at <emphasis role="bold">http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=$1+$2</emphasis>, clicking on the reference 'google #codex/xerox' will create a google search for 'codex xerox'.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">ds #123</emphasis>: '$0' is 'ds', '$1' is '123'. If you define the reference pattern 'ds', with its link pointing at <emphasis role="bold">http://docushare/dsweb/Get/Document-$1</emphasis>, clicking on the reference 'ds #123' will download document '123' from your local DocuShare server.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>You should also note that the number of parameters is important: if the number of parameters used in the text does not match the number of parameters needed by the reference pattern, the reference will not be extracted. This allows one to create several reference patterns with the same keywords but different number of arguments. See for instance the 'wiki' references: 'wiki #Welcome' is a reference with one parameter, and it links to the wiki page 'Welcome', while 'wiki #Welcome/2' is another reference with two parameters that links to the wiki page 'Welcome' at version '2'. </para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Enabled</emphasis>:
          Toggling this check box will simply disable (or enable)
          the reference pattern. Disabling a reference pattern just
          means that it is no longer extracted from text fields or 
          commit emails. Re-enabling the reference pattern is possible.
          See also &#34;Deleting a Reference Pattern&#34; below. 
          </para>
        </step>

      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section id="ReferenceDeletion">
      <title>Deleting a Reference Pattern</title>

      <para>Project reference patterns can be deleted. They appear with a small
      trash icon in the reference pattern list. Just click on this icon to
      delete the reference pattern from the database. A deleted reference pattern
      must be re-created if you need to use it again.
      </para>
      <para>System reference patterns cannot be deleted. However, you can 
      disable them so that they will not be extracted.
      </para>
    </section>
    </section>


    <section id="UserPermissions">
      <title>User Permissions</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>Project Administrators have the ability to grant different
      permissions to different users. As an example, a project member can be
      granted full administration rights on the bug tracker and no
      rights at all on the Documentation Manager of the project.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleProjectMembersPermissionTable">
        <title>A sample project members permission table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_userpermissions.png"  width="15.3cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><xref linkend="FigureASampleProjectMembersPermissionTable" />
      shows a sample project members permission table. Each column represents
      a service or a user capability and there is one line per project member.
      Let&#39;s review the column one by one:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Admin</emphasis>: A Yes/No flag
          stating whether a given project member is a project administrator,
          that is to say a project member with absolutely all rights over the
          project services, project deliverables and project members. Only
          Project Admin can access the project members permission page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS Write</emphasis>: Right now this is
          always set to Yes. All project members have write permission over
          the CVS <footnote><para>CVS stands for Concurrent Versions System.
          It is one of the source code version control system offered on the
          CodeX site. CVS is used by hundreds of thousands of software
          projects all over the world. See <ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org">http://www.cvshome.org</ulink>
          for more information.</para></footnote>repository and this cannot be
          changed from the current version of the Web interface. However
          we&#39;ll see how to deny CVS write permission to project members in
          the CVS chapter (<xref linkend="VersionControlWithCVS" />).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Trackers</emphasis>: 
          </para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">None</emphasis>: the
              user has the same permissionson this tool as a non
              poject member.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Administrator</emphasis>:
              tool administrators have full access to the administration part
              of the tools. As an example, they can define new artifact
              categories, new predefined values for artifact fields, etc.</para>
            </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Forums, Documentation Manager, File Manager</emphasis>:</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">None</emphasis>: the
              user has the same permissionson this tool as a non
              poject member.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Moderator</emphasis>: (Forums
              only): A moderator has the ability to moderate the Web
              Discussion forum that is to say create/delete discussion forums
              for the project, delete posted messages and update the Forum
              status (public/private) as well as the Forum description</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Editor</emphasis>: (Doc Mgr
              only): An editor has the ability to review and validate a
              document prior to its publication. S/he can also update and
              delete a document.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Administrator</emphasis>: (File Mgr
              only): A file manager administrator has the ability to upload and 
              manage file packages and releases. S/he can also set access permissions
              to user groups on packages and releases, even though s/he cannot 
              define or update user groups (only a project administrator can).</para>
		<para> </para><para> </para><para> </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Member of user groups</emphasis>:
          For each individual members, the column lists all the project user groups s/he belongs to. 
          See <xref linkend="UserGroups" /> for more information on user groups.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <title>Reminder!</title>

        <para>Don&#39;t forget to click on the &#34;Update User
        Permissions&#34; button after making any changes in the permission
        table.</para>
      </important>
    </section>


  <section id="UserGroups">
    <title>User Groups</title>
    
    <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>A user group, sometimes called a &#34;ugroup &#34;, is
    simply a group of CodeX users.  User groups are used to set
    specific permissions to some project data (e.g. software releases
    and packages - see <xref linkend="FileAccessPermissions" />).  A
    user group is always attached to a project, but the users
    comprising the group do not necessarily belong to that
    project.</para>
    
    <section id="UGroupList">
      <title>User Groups Management</title>

      <para>The &#34;User Groups Admin&#34; function of the Project
      Administration menu lists all available user groups, and
      provides a way to create new ones.</para>

      <figure id="FigureUserGroupManagementPage">
        <title>User Group Management Page</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_usergrouplist.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In the list, (see for example <xref
      linkend="FigureUserGroupManagementPage" />) there are two
      different kinds of user groups: </para>

     <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Pre-defined User
          Groups</emphasis>: These groups are defined for every
          project. Examples of pre-defined groups are: <emphasis
          role="bold">project_members, project_admins,
          registered_users, nobody, file_manager_admin</emphasis>,
          etc. These groups are dynamic: if you assign some permission
          to 'project_admins', and a new project administrator is
          defined, then this new user will automatically be granted
          the corresponding permission.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Custom User Groups</emphasis>
          are defined by project administrators. They are composed of
          a static list of users. The only requirement is that any
          member must be a registered CodeX user. This list can be
          modified at any time, but will not automatically be updated,
          except if a member is removed from the project or deleted
          from the system.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section id="UGroupCreation">
      <title>Creating a User Group </title> <para>When creating a user
      group, one has to provide the following fields:</para>
     <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: This is the
          label that will be displayed when selecting user groups in a
          permission screen. The group name may not contain space and
          punctuation.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: Short
          description of the user group. It is only displayed in the
          User Group Admin page.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Create From</emphasis>: This is
          a quick way of pre-selecting group members: you may create a
          user group from scratch (Empty Group), from all Project
          Members or Project Admins, or from an existing user group
          attached to this project. The members of the selected group
          will automatically be added to the new group. You will be
          able to add or remove members on the next screen.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <figure id="FigureUserGroupEdit">
        <title>User Group Edit</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_usergroupedit.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In the next page (see <xref linkend="FigureUserGroupEdit"
      />), the project administrator may select individually the
      members of the new group.</para>

      <para>Two columns are displayed: the one on the left contains
      the list of all CodeX registered users, while the one on the
      right contains the list of users already admitted to the
      group. Use the two arrows between the columns to move users from
      one column to the other. </para>

      <para>The user interface also provides convenient ways of
      selecting users when the registered list is very large: you can
      choose to display only those users whose login starts with a
      specific letter, or you may also filter the list by typing
      letters in the 'Filter' text box.  For instance, if you type
      'john', only users whose name or login contains 'john' will be
      displayed.</para>
      
      <para>Once you are done, you may click on the Submit button. The
      user group is created.</para>

    </section>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip: Combining pre-defined groups with additional members</title>

        <para>Sometimes, you might want to grant some permissions to
        all project members and some other CodeX users.  In this case,
        you might be tempted to build a user group from the list of
        project members and to add the other users to the group.  The
        issue with this solution is that if new members join the
        project, they will have to be manually added to the group. So
        it is more convenient to create a group containing only the
        users that are not member of the project. And then,
        permissions should be granted to this group and to the
        pre-defined "project members" group.
        </para>
      </tip>

    <section id="UGroupUpdate">
      <title>Updating a User Group</title>

      <para>In order to update an existing user group, simply select
      it in the user group list. You will be presented with the same
      screen as with Group Creation, where you can update the name,
      description and composition of the user group.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section id="UGroupDeletion">
      <title>Deleting a User Group</title>

      <para>User groups can be deleted. Just click on the trash icon
      next to the group name in the group management page (<xref
      linkend="FigureUserGroupManagementPage" />) to suppress the user
      group from the database. Only custom user groups can be deleted.
      </para>

      <important>
        <title>Warning</title>

        <para>Please note that if a user group was specifically
        granted some permission, deleting the user group might be
        dangerous. Indeed, if a group is the only one allowed to
        access a package and this group is deleted, the permission is
        also deleted and reset to default, so any registered user can
        access the package.
      </para>
      </important>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Additional Information on User Groups</title>

      <para>It is possible to know all user groups one individual
      project member belongs to. Simply display the User Permissions
      page (<xref linkend="UserPermissions" />). However, please note
      that only user groups belonging to the current project are
      displayed. The user might also be a member of additional user
      groups in other projects.
      </para>

      <para>The bottom of the User Group Edit page (<xref
      linkend="FigureUserGroupEdit" />) also lists all the permissions
      granted to this group, e.g. packages and releases this user
      group is granted access to.</para>

      <para>When a project member is removed from a project, or quits
      a project, they are also automatically removed from all project
      user groups for safety reasons.</para>

      <para>Similarly, when a user is deleted (not just suspended) by
      the site administrator, they are removed from all user
      groups in all projects.</para>
    </section>

    </section>


    <section id="ProjectDataExport">
      <title>Project Data Export</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>CodeX is very appealing to many project development teams
      because it provides full-featured project development and
      management tools. A software project can be managed almost
      entirely from within CodeX. However a project team may need to
      perform some additional processing on the project data. It may
      need to report about progress made, what goes well or wrong, how
      far you are from the end date, derive statistical data,
      etc.</para>

      <para>It is far beyond the scope of CodeX to provide project
      teams with such reporting tools. There are many specialized
      tools on the market to generate progress reports and each
      project team has its favorite one. In order to satisfy this
      diversity of needs, the CodeX Team has developed a very
      efficient system that allows the project team to export the
      project data outside of CodeX for re-use in other tools like
      MS Access, Excel, Crystal Report, Open Office,  or
      any other ad-hoc tools.</para>

      <para>CodeX provides you with 2 kinds of Data Export:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Text File Export</emphasis>:
          this is a simple text extract of your project data. It uses
          the well known CSV (Comma Separated Value) format. CSV is
          recognized by almost every Office Suite or database tool on
          the market. In case you want to develop your own report
          application most programming languages also come with a
          standard library that knows how to parse CSV format. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Direct Database
          Connection</emphasis>: so to speak this is not a Data
          Export. It is rather a direct connection to your project
          database through an ODBC or JDBC driver. If you want to
          manipulate your project data with a database tool (like
          MS-Access or an ODBC/JDBC application) this is certainly the
          best choice.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <section id="ExportedData">
      <title>Exported Data</title>
      <para>CodeX gives access to the following data (details on exported fields are listed on the CodeX page): </para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Tracker</emphasis>: the
	  artifacts data, the changes history and the artifacts
	  dependencies can be exported for each tracker.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Survey Responses</emphasis>: all
	  responses to all the surveys you have created in your
	  project.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="TextFileExport">
      <title>Text File Export</title>

      <para>Text File Export follow the well known CSV (Comma
      Separated Values) format, recognized by almost every Office
      Suite on the market. It can easily be imported in MS-Access,
      MS Excel, OpenCalc&hellip;</para>

      <section id="ImportingCSVFilesinExcel">
	<title>Importing CSV Files in Excel</title>
	<para>Clicking on any of the table export link (Bug
	Export, Task Export,..) on the Project Data Export page 
	generates and downloads a CSV file that you can save on your
	local disk or directly open in Excel or any other spreadsheet
	of your choice. No particular setting is required in most cases.
    Nevertheless, you can change the CSV separator (see <xref linkend="AccountMaintenance" />)
    if the default one doesn't correspond with your Excel version
    <footnote><para>For example, by default, the separator for the french version 
    of Excel is the semicolon instead of the comma.</para></footnote>.
    </para>
      </section>

      <section id="ImportingCSVFilesinMS-Access">
	<title>Importing CSV Files in MS-Access</title>

	<para>Before you import external data you must first create a
	new database. Then go through the following steps:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select <literal>File Menu -> Get External Data -> Import</literal></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Choose the appropriate CSV file that you have just
	    generated and then click on the
	    <literal>Import...</literal> button. A preview of the
	    imported table shows up on the screen</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Click on the <literal>Advanced...</literal> button</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Text Delimiter to " (double quote)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Date Format to <literal>YMD</literal> </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Date delimiter to - (dash)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Then enter the name and the type of each field in
	    the lower part of the dialog box. Remember that this
	    information is available on the Project Data
	    Export page.</para>

	    <note><para><emphasis role="bold">Important
	    Remark</emphasis>: you can leave the default field name
	    (Field1,....FieldN) as well as the default Text type in
	    most cases. However long text fields like bug/tasks
	    follow-up comments (details field) and original comment
	    must be declared as type Memo. Failing to do so will cause
	    MS-Access to corrupt the imported data.</para>
		<para>In case you encounter difficulties opening your exported
		CSV file please consult our <xref linkend="ExcelAndRegionals"/>
		</para></note>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Once you are done with the specification of the Import,
	save it by clicking on the <literal>Save As...</literal>
	button. For future import of the same table simply click on
	the Specs... button and reload your Import
	specification. </para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="DirectDatabaseAccess">
      <title>Direct Database Access</title>

      <para>To offer maximum flexibility CodeX also provides a direct
      access to your project data via an ODBC or JDBC database
      connection. Once installed on your PC the MySQL
      ODBC (or JDBC) driver allows a transparent access to your
      project specific database tables.</para>

      <para>If you use MS-Access to generate your progress or status
      report then the 'Direct Database Access' is the easiest way to
      access all of your project data in no time.</para>


      <section id="GeneratingYourProjectDatabase">
	<title>Generating Your Project Database</title>

	<para>Before you attempt to access your project data with
	MS-Access or any other ODBC/JDBC capable application you must
	first generate your project database. Go to the
	<literal>Project Admin -> Project Data Export</literal> and
	click on the 'Generate Full Project Database' link at the
	bottom of the page.The 'Generate Full Project Database' link
	generates a snapshot of your project data. This means you must
	click on the link again each time you want the project
	database to be updated with current data.</para>

	<para>If everything goes well your project database will be
	generated in real time and a message will tell you about the
	result of the generation process and what are the parameters
	to use to connect to the remote database from your
	desktop. Write them down and keep them in a safe
	place. </para>

	<note><para><emphasis role="bold">Remark</emphasis>: if your project
	database contains several thousands of records (tasks,
	bugs,&hellip;) it may take the project database generation may
	take several minutes to complete.</para></note>
      </section>
      
      <section id="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLODBCDriver">
	<title>Installing and Configuring the MySQL ODBC Driver</title>

	<procedure>
	  <step>
	    <para>First download the <ulink
	    url="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/api-myodbc.html">MySQL
	    ODBC driver</ulink> and unzip the zip archive in a
	    temporary directory of your choice.</para> </step>
	  <step>
	    <para>Run the setup program and go through the
	    installation process.<emphasis role="bold">Important
	    Remark</emphasis>: On Windows NT/2000/XP you must have
	    administrator rights to install the driver.</para>
	  </step>
	  <step>
	    <para>Add your project database to Windows Data
	    Sources. For Windows NT/2000/XP users:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para>Use your normal user account to login.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Go to <literal>Start menu -> Settings -> Control
		Panel -> Administrative Tools -> Data Sources
		(ODBC)</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Select the "User DSN" tab and then click on the
		"Add" button</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Select the "MySQL" item from the list and then
		click on the "Finish" button</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para>A dialog box will pop up asking for the database
		following connections parameters:</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Windows DSN Name</emphasis>: is
		    your choice of a name for this connection. Use
		    "Project X Database" for instance.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>MySQL host (IP or Name)</emphasis>; &SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>MySQL Database Name</emphasis>:
		    the database name is your project shortname as
		    displayed by CodeX after you generated your
		    project database (see above)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>User</emphasis>: the user name is
		    'cxuser'.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Password</emphasis>: No password
		    (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Port (if not 3306)</emphasis>: use
		    the default port (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		  
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>SQL command on connect</emphasis>:
		    none (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </step>
	</procedure>
      </section>

      <section id="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLJDBCDriver">
	<title>Installing and Configuring the MySQL JDBC Driver</title>

	<para>For those using a Java application based on a JDBC
	driver, the MySQL JDBC driver and installation instructions
	are available on the <ulink
	url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/en/Java.html">MySQL Java
	Connectivity</ulink> page.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="UsingYourProjectDatabaseFromMS-Access">
	<title>Using Your Project Database From MS-Access</title>

	<para>Before you use MS-Access to connect to your project
	database make sure that the MySQL ODBC driver has been
	installed on your PC (see <xref
	linkend="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLODBCDriver" />) and
	that you have generated your project database (see <xref
	linkend="GeneratingYourProjectDatabase" />). Then go through
	the following steps:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Launch MS-Access and open a new database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>In the <literal>File Menu</literal> select
	    <literal>Get External Data -> Import</literal>. </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>In the <literal>File of Types</literal> pull down
	    menu select the <literal>ODBC Databases</literal>
	    item.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select the <literal>Machine Data Source</literal>
	    tab and click on your project database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select the tables you are interested or simply click
	    on <literal>Select All</literal>.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>MS-Access will instantly (according to MS-Access
	standards :-) import your project data and you can then
	process your project data exactly as you would do for a native
	MS-Access database.</para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </section>


    <section id="TrackerImport">
      <title>Tracker Artifact Import</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>Please see <xref linkend="ArtifactImport" /></para>
    </section>


    <section id="ProjectHistory">
      <title>Project History</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The Project History provides project members with Audit
      capabilities. Clicking on this menu item shows a list of all the changes
      that have taken place in the administration of the project since its
      creation. The list of changes reports the nature of the change (e.g.
      Changed Public Info, Changed Permissions, Changed Software Map, ...) ,
      what the value was before it changed (if applicable), who changed it and
      when.</para>
    </section>


    <section id="SourceCodeAccessLogs">
      <title>Access Logs</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>Depending on the configuration of the CodeX site and on
      the configuration of each project, source code access, documents
      and file release download permissions may be granted to various
      populations.</para>

      <para>The Access Logs provide project members with a complete
      audit trail of who accessed what on the projet. The page shows
      the following information:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para>The downloaded File Releases. It basically reports who
          downloaded what file and when (date and time). The time of
          download is reported in local time relative to the project
          member time zone.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CodeX users who used CVS to checkout or update the
          sources on their local desktop machine or who browsed source
          code via the CVS Web interface.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CodeX users who accessed the source code through
          the Subversion repository or who browsed source code via the
          CVS Web interface.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CodeX users who downloaded documents, except for
          those documents marked as being accessible to anonymous
          users in your Document Manager (see <xref
          linkend="DocumentAdministration"/>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Access Logs can be filtered out by users to show accesses 
      from all users, project members or non project members
      (default). The time window can also be adjusted to show more or
      less access log history.</para>

      <figure id="FigureSourceCodeAccessLogsForACodeXProject">
        <title>Sample Access Log</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_sourcecodeaccesslogs.png" width="13cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

