<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="ProjectAdministration">
    <title>Project Administration</title>

    <para>Whenever you enter the Project Summary page of a given project or
    any of its service you&#39;ll see a new section appear in the CodeX Main
    Menu on the left hand side of the screen. This new section relates to the
    visited project and points to the Project Summary page and the Project
    Administration page.</para>

    <para>Only project members can access the Project Administration page. All
    other CodeX users are denied access to this part of a project.</para>

    <section id="ProjectAdministrationMenu">
      <title>Project Administration Menu</title>

      <para>In addition to the CodeX Main Menu that was introduced in the
      description of the Project Summary page, the Project Administration page
      has its own menu. This menu is not redundant with the page content right
      below. Except for 1 or 2 items the menu and the page content give access
      to distinct parts of the administration space. So pay attention to both
      the Page Admin menu and the Page Admin content. In the following
      sections the Location label indicates where to find the corresponding
      administrative function.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="AddingRemovingUsers">
      <title>Adding/Removing Users</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>User administration in CodeX is easy. To add a new member to a
      project team one of the project administrator just has to type the login
      name of the invited member and click on the &#34;Add User&#34; button.
      If you don&#39;t know the login name of the new project member you want
      to add, open a new browser window on CodeX and use the search box in the
      CodeX Main Menu to search for the person&#39;s real name (first or last
      name or both) and don&#39;t forget to select &#34;People&#34; in the
      Search pull-down menu. The result list will show you the user real name
      and login name.</para>

      <para>Removing a project member is even easier. Just click on the trash
      icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="PNG"
      fileref="../../icons/trash.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>) next
      to the person&#39;s name to revoke his/her membership. Revoking
      membership has absolutely no effect on the history and the data
      integrity of the project. In other words all bugs, tasks, support
      requests, ... assigned or submitted by this person will continue to show
      up as before in the project database. Only the ability of this person to
      perform project management tasks is affected. Also notice that in order
      to remove a project administrator from the project member list, another
      project administrator must first change the &#34;Project Admin&#34; flag
      of this user to &#34;No&#34; in the User Permission table. In other
      words, a Project Administrator cannot be removed from the project
      members as long as she has administrator privilege.</para>

      <para></para>
      <para><note>You have probably noticed that project member&#39;s
      name on the Project Administration page are actually hyperlinks. On this
      page as well as in many other pages throughout CodeX a click on a login
      name leads you to the user page where you can know more about the user
      (including its location, phone/fax number, etc. extracted from the Xerox
      Directory in real time) and send an e-mail message to this person
      directly via a Web form.</note></para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleProjectAdministrationPage">
        <title>A Sample Project Administration Page</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_projectadminpage.png" width="15.3cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="UserPermissions">
      <title>User Permissions</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>Project Administrators have the ability to grant different
      permissions to different users. As an example, a project member can be
      granted full administration rights on the Bug Tracking System and no
      rights at all on the Documentation Manager of the project.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleProjectMembersPermissionTable">
        <title>A sample project members permission table</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_userpermissions.png"  width="15.3cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><xref linkend="FigureASampleProjectMembersPermissionTable" />
      shows a sample project members permission table. Each column represents
      a service or a user capability and there is one line per project member.
      Let&#39;s review the column one by one:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Admin</emphasis>: A Yes/No flag
          stating whether a given project member is a project administrator,
          that is to say a project member with absolutely all rights over the
          project services, project deliverables and project members. Only
          Project Admin can access the project members permission page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS Write</emphasis>: Right now this is
          always set to Yes. All project members have write permission over
          the CVS <footnote><para>CVS stands for Concurrent Version Control.
          It is the default source code version control system offered on the
          CodeX site. CVS is used by hundreds of thousands of software
          projects allover the world. See <ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org">http://www.cvshome.org</ulink>
          for more information.</para></footnote>repository and this cannot be
          changed from the current version of the Web interface. However
          we&#39;ll see how to deny CVS write permission to project members in
          the CVS chapter (<xref linkend="VersionControlWithCVS" />).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug Tracking, Task Manager, Patch
          Manager, Support Manager </emphasis>: are listed in the upper right
          corner of the page. A click on a name will direct you to the user
          page where you can learn more about the CodeX user and send him/her
          an e-mail. Project members can be viewed via the [View members]
          pointer.</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">None</emphasis>: well, you
              can&#39;t do much with this one</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Technician Only</emphasis>:
              tool technicians can be assigned bugs/tasks/patches/support
              requests and has the ability to update these items from
              assignment to closure.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Administrator Only</emphasis>:
              tool administrators have full access to the administration part
              of the tools. As an example, they can define new tasks
              categories, new predefined values for bug fields, etc.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Technician &#38; Administrator</emphasis>:
              the one-man-can-do-it-all on that tool</para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>

              <para></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Forums, Documentation Manager</emphasis>:
          These 2 services have much less sophisticated permission schema.
          Only 3 permission levels are available:</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">None</emphasis>: there is
              nothing you can do with this service</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Moderator</emphasis>: (Forums
              only): A moderator has the ability to moderate the Web
              Discussion forum that is to say create/delete discussion forums
              for the project, delete posted messages and update the Forum
              status (public/private) as well as the Forum description</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="underline">Editor</emphasis>: (Doc Mgr
              only): An editor has the ability to review and validate a
              document prior to its publication. S/he can also update and
              delete a document.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <important>
        <title>Reminder!</title>

        <para>Don&#39;t forget to click on the &#34;Update Developers
        Permission&#34; button after making any changes in the permission
        table.</para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectPublicInformation">
      <title>Project Public Information</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The &#34;Edit Public Info&#34; item of the Project Administration
      menu allows a project member to update the following project data:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The Project Home Page</emphasis>: each
          project hosted on CodeX has its own virtual Web server available on
          the CodeX site. By default the &#34;Home Page&#34; in the Project
          Main Menu points to this location (see CHAPTER 16 for more details).
          If you want the Home Page of your project to point to some other
          locations on the Xerox Intranet (or even outside of Xerox) replace
          the default value with your own Web location. Do not confuse your
          Project Home Page with your Project Summary page. The Project Home
          Page actually points to real Web Site whereas the Public Summary
          Page is just an entry point to access software related activities
          and deliverables.</para>

          <para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The Project Description Elements</emphasis>:
          these are elements provided during the registration process as well
          as the two-line description that you have provided right after your
          project registration was confirmed.</para>

          <para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">The Project Active Services</emphasis>:
          this is the list of services that you want to enable/disable for
          your own project. (Un)Checking any of the select boxes will
          immediately (De)Activate the service. Deactivating a service just
          means that it disappears from the Project Summary page of your
          project but all existing data related to this service remains
          untouched. In other words, re-activating the service will restore
          the service in the exact same state it was when you first
          deactivated it.</para>

          <para></para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectCategorization">
      <title>Project Categorization</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is where you can categorize your project. You can define up
      to 3 values for each of the 7 criteria used in the Software Map. If you
      cannot find any matching value in the predefined list do not hesitate to
      contact the CodeX Team.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectHistory">
      <title>Project History</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>The Project History provides project members with Audit
      capabilities. Clicking on this menu item shows a list of all the changes
      that have taken place in the administration of the project since its
      creation. The list of changes reports the nature of the change (e.g.
      Changed Public Info, Changed Permissions, Changed Software Map, ...) ,
      what the value was before it changed (if applicable), who changed it and
      when.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectDataExport">
      <title>Project Data Export</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>CodeX is very appealing to many project development teams because
      it provides full-featured project development and management tools for
      free. A software project can be managed almost entirely from within
      CodeX. However at some point the project team needs to report about
      progress made, what goes well or wrong, how far you are from the end
      date, derive statistical data, etc.</para>

      <para>It is far beyond the scope of CodeX to provide project
      teams with such reporting tools. There are many specialized
      tools on the market to generate progress reports and each
      project team has its favorite one. In order to satisfy this
      diversity of needs, the CodeX Team has developed a very
      efficient system that allows the project team to export the
      project data outside of CodeX for re-use in other tools like
      Access, Excel, Crystal Report, Word, Open Office, Star Office or
      any other ad-hoc tools.</para>

      <para>CodeX provides you with 2 kinds of Data Export:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Text File Export</emphasis>:
          this is a simple text extract of your project data. It uses
          the well known CSV (Comma Separated Value) format. CSV is
          recognized by almost every Office Suite or database tool on
          the market. In case youu want to develop your own report
          application most programming languages also come with a
          standard library that knows how to parse CSV format. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Direct Database
          Connection</emphasis>: so to speak this not a Data
          Export. It is rather a direct connection to your project
          database through an ODBC or JDBC driver. If you want to
          manipulate your project data with a database tool (like
          MS-Access or an ODBC/JDBC application) this is certainly the
          best choice.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <section id="ExportedData">
      <title>Exported Data</title>
      <para>CodeX gives access to the following data (details on exported fields are listed on the CodeX page): </para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug</emphasis>: all bugs submitted to your project.</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug History</emphasis>: full
	  history of all the changes your project bugs have gone
	  through.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug-to-Bug
	  Dependencies</emphasis>: a list of all bug to bug
	  dependencies.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Bug-to-Task
	  Dependencies</emphasis>: a list of all bug to task
	  dependencies.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Task</emphasis>: all tasks
	  created in your project</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Task History</emphasis>: full
	  history of all the changes your project tasks have gone
	  through</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Task-to-Task
	  Dependencies</emphasis>: a list of all task to task
	  dependencies</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Task Assignees</emphasis>: an
	  SQL like form of task assignees. A task may be listed
	  several times if it has several assignees.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Support Request</emphasis>: all
	  support requests submitted to your project</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Survey Responses</emphasis>: all
	  responses to all the surveys you have created in your
	  project.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="TextFileExport">
      <title>Text File Export</title>

      <para>Text File Export follow the well known CSV (Comma
      Separated Values) format, recognized by almost every Office
      Suite on the market. It can easily be imported in MS-Access,
      Excel, StarCalc&hellip;</para>

      <section id="ImportingCSVFilesinExcel">
	<title>Importing CSV Files in Excel</title>
	<para>Double-clicking on any of the table export link (Bug
	Export, Task Export,..) on the Project Data Export page 
	generates and downloads a CSV file that you can save on your
	local disk or directly open in Excel or any other spreadsheet
	of your choice (StarCalc, QuattroPro,...). No particular
	setting is required.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="ImportingCSVFilesinMS-Access">
	<title>Importing CSV Files in MS-Access</title>

	<para>Before you import external data you must first create a
	new database. Then go through the following steps:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select <literal>File Menu -> Get External Data -> Import</literal></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Choose the appropriate CSV file that you have just
	    generated and then click on the
	    <literal>Import...</literal> button. A preview of the
	    imported table shows up on the screen</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Click on the <literal>Advanced...</literal> button</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Text Delimiter to " (double quote)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Date Format to <literal>YMD</literal> </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Set Date delimiter to - (dash)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Then enter the name and the type of each field in
	    the lower part of the dialog box. Remember that this
	    information is available on the Project Data
	    Export page.</para>

	    <para><note><emphasis role="bold">Important
	    Remark</emphasis>: you can leave the default field name
	    (Field1,....FieldN) as well as the default Text type in
	    most cases. However long text fields like bug/tasks
	    follow-up comments (details field) and original comment
	    must be declared as type Memo. Failing to do so will cause
	    MS-Access to corrupt the imported data. </note></para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>Once you are done with the specification of the Import,
	save it by clicking on the <literal>Save As...</literal>
	button. For future import of the same table simply click on
	the Specs... button and reload your Import
	specification. </para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="DirectDatabaseAccess">
      <title>Direct Database Access</title>

      <para>To offer maximum flexibility CodeX also provides a direct
      access to your project data via an ODBC or JDBC database
      connection. Once installed on your PC the MySQL
      ODBC (or JDBC) driver allows a transparent access to your
      project specific database tables.</para>

      <para>If you use MS-Access to generate your progress or status
      report then the 'Direct Database Access' is the easiest way to
      access all of your project data in no time.</para>


      <section id="GeneratingYourProjectDatabase">
	<title>Generating Your Project Database</title>

	<para>Before you attempt to access your project data with
	MS-Access or anyother ODBC/JDBC capable application you must
	first generate your project database. Go to the
	<literal>Project Admin -> Project Data Export</literal> and
	click on the 'Generate Full Project Database' link at the
	bottom of the page.The 'Generate Full Project Database' link
	generates a snapshot of your project data. This means you must
	click on the link again each time you want the project
	database to be updated with current data.</para>

	<para>If everything goes well your project database will be
	generated in real time and a message will tell you about the
	result of the generation process and what are the parameters
	to use to connect to the remote database from your
	desktop. Write them down and keep them in a safe
	place. </para>

	<para><note><emphasis role="bold">Remark</emphasis>: if your project
	database contains several thousands of records (tasks,
	bugs,&hellip;) it may take the project database generation may
	take several minutes to complete.</note></para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLODBCDriver">
	<title>Installing and Configuring the MySQL ODBC Driver</title>

	<procedure>
	  <step>
	    <para>First download the <ulink
	    url="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/api-myodbc.html">MySQL
	    ODBC driver</ulink> and unzip the zip archive in a
	    temporary directory of your choice.</para> </step>
	  <step>
	    <para>Run the setup program and go through the
	    installation process.<emphasis role="bold">Important
	    Remark</emphasis>: On Windows NT/2000/XP you must have
	    administrator rights to install the driver.</para>
	  </step>
	  <step>
	    <para>Add your project database to Windows Data
	    Sources. For Windows NT/2000/XP users:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para>Use your normal user account to logon.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Go to <literal>Start menu -> Settings -> Control
		Panel -> Administrative Tools -> Data Sources
		(ODBC)</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Select the "User DSN" tab and then click on the
		"Add" button</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Select the "MySQL" item from the list and then
		click on the "Finish" button</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para>A dialog box will pop up asking for the database
		following connections parameters:</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Windows DSN Name</emphasis>: is
		    your choice of a name for this connection. Use
		    "Project X Database" for instance.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>MySQL host (IP or Name)</emphasis>; codex.xerox.com</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>MySQL Database Name</emphasis>:
		    the database name is your project shortname as
		    displayed by CodeX after you generated your
		    project database (see above)</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>User</emphasis>: the user name is
		    'cxuser'.</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Password</emphasis>: No password
		    (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>Port (if not 3306)</emphasis>: use
		    the default port (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		  
		  <listitem>
		    <para><emphasis>SQL command on connect</emphasis>:
		    none (leave blank).</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </step>
	</procedure>
      </section>

      <section id="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLJDBCDriver">
	<title>Installing and Configuring the MySQL JDBC Driver</title>

	<para>For those using a Java application based on a JDBC
	driver, the MySQL JDBC driver and installation instructions
	are available on the <ulink
	url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/en/Java.html">MySQL Java
	Connectivity</ulink> page.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="UsingYourProjectDatabaseFromMS-Access">
	<title>Using Your Project Database From MS-Access</title>

	<para>Before you use MS-Access to connect to your project
	database make sure that the MySQL OBDC driver has been
	installed on your PC (see <xref
	linkend="InstallingandConfiguringtheMySQLODBCDriver" />) and
	that you have generated your project database (see <xref
	linkend="GeneratingYourProjectDatabase" />). Then go through
	the following steps:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Launch MS-Access and open a new database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>In the <literal>File Menu</literal> select
	    <literal>Get External Data -> Import</literal>. </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>In the <literal>File of Types</literal> pull down
	    menu select the <literal>ODBC Databases</literal>
	    item.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select the <literal>Machine Data Source</literal>
	    tab and click on your project database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Select the tables you are interested or simply click
	    on <literal>Select All</literal>.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>MS-Access will instantly (according to MS-Access
	standards :-) import your project data and you can then
	process your project data exactly as you would do for a native
	MS-Access database.</para>
      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

    <section id="Edit-ReleaseFiles">
      <title>Edit/Release Files</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu and Page Admin
      Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>This service allows project members to post packaged versions (zip
      or tar gzipped ) of their software on CodeX for public consumption. All
      posted file releases can be accessed from the Project Summary page.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="FileRelease" /> is entirely dedicated to
      the description of the File Release Service.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Post-EditJobs">
      <title>Post/Edit Jobs</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>CodeX offers a minimal job posting system to your project. When
      you publish a job it instantly appears under the &#34;Project Help
      Wanted&#34; section on the CodeX Main Menu and is visible to all CodeX
      users including those who are not registered users. It is an excellent
      way of calling for help either on a specific topic or to sub-contract a
      part of your work.</para>

      <important>
        <title>Important Note on Job Posting</title>

        <para>It is not the intent of the CodeX Job Posting system to replace
        PeopleNet or any other countrywide job posting system already in place
        in Xerox. The CodeX Job Posting system is intended to call for
        expertise or short mission request. One of the possible uses of the
        CodeX Job Posting system is for Projects to post 3 to 6 months jobs
        that can be sub-contracted to organizations like XConnect or XISS/XPS.
        It can also be a request for the opinion of an expert that would take
        no longer than a couple of days even a couple of hours.</para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section id="SourceCodeAccessLogs">
      <title>Source Code Access Logs</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Project Administration Menu</emphasis></para>

      <para>CodeX is about Software Sharing inside Xerox. Our goal is to make
      software re-use part of the Xerox culture. To this end, Source code
      access and file release download is granted to all registered users
      <footnote><para>Anonymous users are not granted access to the Source
      code. They must create their own account and identify themselves with
      CodeX before they can do so.</para></footnote> on CodeX. Beside that we
      also wanted the ability for project leaders to see who downloaded their
      software. The CodeX Team implemented this feature upon request of
      several project administrators shortly after the site was launched. The
      intent for the project leaders is not to construct barriers to source
      code sharing but rather to know who their community of users are and who
      is interested in their software.</para>

      <para>The Source Code Access Logs provide project members with 2 lists:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para>The first list is about File Release download. It basically
          reports who (Real Name, Login name and e-mail), downloaded what file
          and when (date and time). The time of download is reported in local
          time relative to the project member time zone.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The second list is about CodeX users who used CVS to checkout
          or update the sources on their local desktop machine.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure id="FigureSourceCodeAccessLogsForACodeXProject">
        <title>Source Code Access Logs for a CodeX project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_sourcecodeaccesslogs.png" width="13cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="ToolsAdmin">
      <title>Tools Admin</title>

      <para><emphasis>Location: Page Admin Content</emphasis></para>

      <para>Finally, you&#39;ll find here a direct link to the administration
      function of all your project services in the lower left corner of the
      Project Admin page. Only project members with Tool Administration
      permission are allowed to access the CodeX services administration
      pages.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->