<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id: ProjectSummary.xml 2448 2006-01-18 17:23:36 +0000 (Wed, 18 Jan 2006) ljulliar $
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="ProjectSummary">
    <title>Project Summary</title>

    <para>The Project Summary page is the entry point of a CodeX hosted
    project. And, for any project, it is the only page you need to know about.
    From this page both ordinary registered users and project
    members/administrators can access all project resources and services.
    Unlike the Project Administration page (see <xref
    linkend="ProjectAdministration" />), the Project Summary page is public
    and can be visited by any CodeX user including anonymous ones. In some
    sense the Project Summary page displays the public face of a project.</para>

    <section id="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage">
      <title>Accessing a Project Summary Page</title>

      <para>For project members, accessing the Project Summary page of one of
      their projects is pretty easy: go to your Personal Page and click on the
      appropriate project name.</para>

      <para>For registered users there are several ways by which you can
      access the Project Summary page of a CodeX hosted project:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>You can use the search box and look for a project name that
          you know of</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>You can explore the Software Map if you know where the project
          is</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>You can click on the Project name if it appears on the CodeX
          Site statistics on the right hand side of the CodeX home page</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>And finally you can type the Web URL to access the project
          page. All projects can be accessed at:</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
http://&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/projects/short_project_name
</programlisting>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>If your are thinking of visiting the Project Summary of a project
      on a regular basis we strongly advise you to bookmark it in your
      Personal Page the first time you access the page by using the
      &#34;Bookmark This Page&#34; link in the CodeX Main Menu. (see <xref
      linkend="LoginAndPersonalPage" />)</para>

      <tip>
        <title>The Project Summary Page is not the Project Home Page!</title>

        <para>The Project Home Page is not the same as the Project Summary
        Page. The Project Summary Page is an overview of all the software
        related activities and deliverables but it is not a substitute for a
        real Web Site where you describe what the project is about, related
        links and resources, etc. CodeX also offers a Web Site to each
        project. The &#34;Home Page&#34; item in the Project Main Menu is
        precisely a pointer to this Web Site (see <xref
        linkend="ProjectWebSite" /> for more information on your Project Web
        Site and how to use it).</para>
      </tip>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section id="ProjectSummaryPageContent">
      <title>Project Summary Page Content</title>

      <para>A sample Project Summary page is available in <xref
      linkend="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage" />. The page is split in
      several areas:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Main Menu</emphasis>: is at the
          top of the page right below the Project name. The Project Main Menu
          is a recap of all the services available for a given project. As you
          browse the various services and resources of a given project this
          menu will always be visible.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Short Description and Categorization</emphasis>:
          already described before. Next to the short description is a pointer
          to a longer description and to additional information provided by
          the creator of the project.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project members and Administrators</emphasis>:
          are listed in the upper right corner of the page. A click on a name
          will direct you to the user page where you can learn more about the
          CodeX user and send him/her an e-mail.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Latest File Release</emphasis>: show the
          list of most recent packages available for download along with their
          revision. A Release Notes icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/manual16c.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>)
          allows you to see the latest changes and developers comments
          associated with this revision. Then comes the monitor icon (<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/mail16d.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>).
          Selecting this icon will cause this package to be monitored for you.
          Anytime the project development team posts a new release, you will
          be automatically notified via e-mail. All monitored File Releases
          are listed in your Personal Page and can be cancelled from this
          page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Public Areas</emphasis>: this is an
          iconic list of all available services for this project along with
          some information next to it. Click on any of this item to access a
          service. The role of this area is pretty much equivalent to the
          Project Main Menu at the top of the screen except that it shows
          additional information about each of the service (e.g. total number
          of open bugs, tasks, ...)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Latest News</emphasis>: the last 10
          pieces of news posted by the project members. Some of this news
          might also be visible on the CodeX front page if the CodeX Team
          decided that it was worth a site announcement.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure id="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage">
        <title>A sample Project Summary Page</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_projectsummarypage.png" width="15.3cm" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

