<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="SupportRequestManager">
    <title>Support Request Manager</title>

    <para>One of the CodeX goals is to help project team to grow a community
    of users and developers around their project. The Support Request (SR)
    service is one of the communication mechanisms offered by CodeX between
    the community of users and the project team. The SR service allows any
    CodeX user to post a question to the project team. SRs are primarily
    intended for technical question about the software itself or its usage.</para>

    <para>Since the SR service is entirely Web based any CodeX user can follow
    the thread of discussions between the other users and the project team. It
    is also possible to review all the SRs that were posted in the past and
    the answer given by the project team. With the Support Request service a
    project team can easily and efficient coordinate technical support
    activities.</para>

    <section id="SupportRequestSubmission">
      <title>Support Request Submission</title>

      <para>Anyone is allowed to submit a Support Request. To submit a SR to a
      given project, first go to the Project Summary page (see <xref
      linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />) and then select either the
      &#34;Support&#34; item from the Project Main Menu in the upper part of
      the page or the &#34;Support Request&#34; item from the Public Area.</para>

      <para>From there you enter the SR Manager and the first screen you are
      faced with is the SR selection and browsing screen (more about this
      facility in <xref linkend="SupportRequestBrowsing" />). For now
      let&#39;s click on the &#34;Submit a Request&#34; item from the SR
      Manager Menu Bar in the upper part of the welcome screen (see <xref
      linkend="FigureTheSupportRequestBrowsingScreen" />).</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: make sure your SR hasn&#39;t yet been submitted</title><para>About
      to submit a support request to a CodeX Project? Before you do that, make
      sure that a similar SR hasn&#39;t yet been submitted by others. To do so
      you can either browse the SR database through the SR Selection and
      Browsing possibly using the Category criteria to narrow the number of
      selected SRs.</para></tip></para>

      <para>Select the category that is most appropriate to your request. Fill
      the Summary and the Description fields giving as much detail as possible
      like the version of the software you are using, the machine it runs on,
      etc. Then submit your request by clicking on the &#34;Submit
      Request&#34; button.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="SupportRequestBrowsing">
      <title>Support Request Browsing</title>

      <para>The Support Request Manager is organized like the Bug Tracking
      System or the Task Manager. To access the welcome screen click on the
      &#34;Support&#34; item in the Project Main Menu available at the top of
      the Project Summary page.</para>

      <para>From this screen you can select a set of support requests that
      match a set of criteria. You can select support requests based on the
      name of the User in charge of answering the SR, the status of the SR and
      its category, if any (in general, these are high level modules or
      functions of the software).</para>

      <figure id="FigureTheSupportRequestBrowsingScreen">
        <title>The Support Request Browsing screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_supportbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Like bugs and tasks the selected SRs can be sorted by clicking on
      any of the labels at the top of the SR report. And they also follow the
      same color coding schema to show the urgency of a SR. The SR Manager
      menu also offers 2 shortcuts to quickly select all SRs with status value
      at Open (&#34;Open Requests&#34; item) and those that have been assigned
      to you (&#34;My Requests&#34; item). This is mostly for project members.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="SupportRequestProcessing">
      <title>Support Request Processing</title>

      <para>Project members that have been granted Administrative rights on
      the SR Manager can process the submitted SR.</para>

      <para>Clicking on the SR ID number in the first column of the result
      list generated by the SR selection and browsing module brings you to a
      screen showing all the details of the pointed SR. A Support Request can
      be viewed as a thread of discussion between CodeX users and the project
      team. Once a SR has been submitted, the first thing to do for the
      project team is to assign the SR to a project member and a priority on a
      scale from 1 to 9 like bugs.</para>

      <para>From there the project member can post follow-up comments to the
      request either to provide an answer or to ask for more details. The
      interesting point is that the SR Manager allows any CodeX User to post
      follow-up comments to a given request. Therefore anybody can potentially
      bring additional information or answer the question.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="SupportRequestManagerE-mailNotification">
      <title>E-mail Notification</title>

      <para>The SR Manager has a sophisticated e-mail notification system.
      Each time a SR is submitted or updated an e-mail notification is sent to
      the following people:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The SR submitter (the person who initially submitted the SR)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The SR assignee (the project member to whom the SR is
          assigned)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All the people who have so far contributed a follow-up comment
          for this SR</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The e-mail addresses specified in the &#34;Other Configuration
          Settings&#34; screen of the SR Administration module (see section
          <xref linkend="SupportRequestManagerOtherConfigurationSettings" />).
          These e-mail addresses can be any email address you want including a
          distribution list that was created with the CodeX Mailing List
          manager (<xref linkend="MailingLists" />) or via MS-Exchange.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The e-mail notification consists of the SR ID number, SR summary,
      SR original description as well as all SR fields, plus all follow-up
      comments sorted by date (most recent first).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="SupportRequestManagerAdministration">
      <title>Support Request Manager Administration</title>

      <para>Project members that have been granted Administrative rights on
      the SR Manager can configure the SR Manager.</para>

      <section id="DefiningSupportRequestCategories">
        <title>Defining Support Request Categories</title>

        <para>The SR Manager allows you to define SR categories. To add or
        modify SR categories click on the &#34;Admin&#34; item in the SR
        Manager menu at the top of the screen (<xref
        linkend="FigureTheSupportRequestBrowsingScreen" />). SR categories
        generally reflects the high level modules or functionalities of your
        software. It is a convenient way to classify your support requests and
        make the SR processing easier for your team.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="DefiningCannedResponses">
        <title>Defining Canned Responses</title>

        <para>Beside Categories, the Administration module of the SR Manager
        Canned Response are pre- defined responses that you can write down
        once for all and later re-use in the SR management process. They
        generally correspond to the type of follow-up comment that SR managers
        uses on a regular basis like a &#34;thanks for posting a SR&#34;
        message or a request for more information that are very often missing
        in the submitted SR.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="SupportRequestManagerOtherConfigurationSettings">
        <title>Other Configuration Settings</title>

        <para>This SR Manager configuration module allows you to define the
        following configuration parameters:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>An introductory message that we&#39;ll show up at the top of
            the SR submission form. This is a convenient way to give
            directions and recommendations to the SR submitter. The text must
            use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great flexibility to
            shape the content of this preamble (you can use bold, italic,
            embed URL...)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A series of comma separated email addresses to which new SR
            submission and patch updates will be sent. If you want a (group
            of) person to be systematically aware of new item submission you
            can add his/her e-mail address in this text field. Checking the
            &#34;Send on all updates&#34; check box will cause e-mail
            notification to be sent on all updates in addition to the initial
            submission.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->