<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX / CodeX Team, 2001-2002. All Rights Reserved
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="SurveyManager">
    <title>Survey Manager</title>

    <para>The Survey Manager allows a project team to create surveys.
    Providing a survey service in an environment where most services are
    related to software development activities may seem a bit strange at first
    glance. However if you remember that CodeX is about source code sharing
    and community building, you&#39;ll soon realize that part of the game in
    building a strong community is to listen to the community feedback and
    make it happy.</para>

    <para>Listening to your community can be done in various ways on CodeX:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                  spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>through your project mailing lists and web forums,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>from the feedback received when you post a piece of news on your
        Project Summary page</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>or by analyzing the profile of the submitted Support Requests
        over a period of time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>All these communication channels allow CodeX users to push
    spontaneous feedback on a topic that they wholeheartedly cherish. But what
    if you want to collect the opinion of your community on a precise number
    of subjects and you want the answers to be taken from a set of possible
    choices defined by the project team? This is precisely what the Survey
    Manager is for. It allows you to:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                  spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>formulate a precise a list of questions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>define the set of possible answers for easy statistical analysis</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>make the survey accessible to virtually anybody via the Xerox
        Web</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>review the results to identify the dominant trends in your
        community of users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure id="FigureSurveyManagerWelcomeScreen">
      <title>Survey Manager Welcome screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
                     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_surveywelcome.png" width="15.3cm" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="PublishingaSurvey">
      <title>Publishing a Survey</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>You have been working hard to produce this perfectly polished
      survey and now you want to reach the broadest possible audience. With
      CodeX you can make your survey visible in a number of ways:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Through the Survey Manager itself</emphasis>:
          as soon as a survey is created it is visible in your Survey Manager
          Welcome screen (see <xref linkend="FigureSurveyManagerWelcomeScreen" />).
          So any CodeX user visiting your Project Summary page will see that
          surveys are available in the &#34;Public Area&#34; (survey count not
          null) and by clicking on &#34;Surveys&#34; she will be able to take
          whatever survey is available.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project News Service</emphasis>: when
          you have your new survey ready, make sure you publish a piece of
          news about this survey: why you did it, who is expected to take it
          and type the Web location corresponding to the survey (see below).
          By publishing a piece of news you also have a chance to see it on
          the CodeX front page if the CodeX Team decides so.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">E-mail</emphasis>: the survey you have
          created can be accessed directly via a Web pointer (URL) on the
          CodeX site. As a consequence you can push your survey to virtually
          anybody in the Corporation simply by referencing the survey Web
          pointer in an e-mail message, a web page or any kind of office
          document. Even non CodeX Users will be able to take the survey.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>All surveys created on CodeX can be accessed through the following
      Web pointer (URL):</para>

<programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
http://codex.xerox.com/survey/survey.php?group_id=N&#38;survey_id=X
</programlisting>

      <para>where N is your project ID number and X is the survey ID number as
      shown in the survey list displayed on the Survey Manager welcome screen.
      Your project ID number N is visible on the Survey Manager Administration
      screen (see <xref linkend="FigureSurveyManagerWelcomeScreen" />)</para>

      <para>Taking a survey is just a matter of accessing the survey by one of
      the previously mentioned method, answer the questions and click on the
      &#34;Submit&#34; button at the bottom of the page. A sample survey is
      shown on <xref linkend="FigureASampleSurveyTakenFromTheCodeXProject" />.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Important note: Survey Privacy</title><para>The
      information collected in these surveys are strictly internal to Xerox.
      This information is being gathered to build a profile of the projects
      and developers being surveyed. The identity of those who answer surveys
      are suppressed and not viewable by project administrators or the public
      or third parties. The information gathered is used only in aggregate
      form, not to single out specific users or developers.</para></tip></para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleSurveyTakenFromTheCodeXProject">
        <title>A sample survey taken from the CodeX project</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_surveysample.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="AdministeringSurveys">
      <title>Administering Surveys</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>Administrative functions of the Survey Manager can only be used by
      the project members. The Administration module allows you to:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Create or modify a survey</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create or modify questions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Review the survey results</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To access administrative functions of the Survey , go to your
      Project Summary page and click on the &#34;Survey&#34; item in the
      Project Main menu at the top of the screen, then select the
      &#34;Admin&#34; item in the Survey Manager menu (see <xref
      linkend="FigureSurveyManagerWelcomeScreen" />). From there you have
      access to all the Survey Administrative functions (see <xref
      linkend="FigureSurveyManagerAdministrationScreen" />).</para>

      <figure id="FigureSurveyManagerAdministrationScreen">
        <title>Survey Manager Administration screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_surveyadmin.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section id="SurveyStructure">
        <title>Survey Structure</title>

        <para>In order to understand the survey creation and update process
        you must first understand that the Survey module manages two distinct
        pools of entities: a pool of surveys and a pool of questions. As a
        consequence of this organization, creating a survey is a 2-step
        process:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>First you create a set of questions along with the related
            set of possible answers. All questions for all surveys are stored
            in a common pool.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Then you create a survey mostly by giving it a title and
            attaching a series of previously defined questions to it.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>One of the interest of managing questions and surveys separately
        is that you can create distinct surveys and re-use the same questions
        in several of them if need be.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="CreatingorEditingQuestions">
        <title>Creating or Editing Questions</title>

        <para>First thing first: if you want to collect people&#39;s opinion
        you must first define a set of questions and the possible answers for
        each of them. Designing a good survey is not an easy task and it
        requires a fair amount of work: the value derived from the survey
        results depends directly on the quality of your questions. A couple of
        advices: do not put too many questions in a survey, questions must be
        short, clear, unambiguous and non overlapping. So take some time to
        think about it with your project team.</para>

        <para>To create questions click on the &#34;Add Questions&#34; item
        either in the Survey Manager Administration menu or in the content of
        the page itself. Defining a question is simply a matter of typing the
        question itself and then choosing a response type. There are 5 types
        of possible responses (see <xref
        linkend="FigureASampleSurveyTakenFromTheCodeXProject" /> for some
        sample questions):</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Radio Buttons 1-5</emphasis>: this
            response type will force the user to give an answer to the
            question on a scale from 1 to 5 using 5 radio buttons.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Radio Button Yes/No</emphasis>: this
            is a variant of the previous one for questions calling for a Yes
            or No answer.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Text Field</emphasis>: questions for
            which you want a short free text answer (one line)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Text Area</emphasis>: same as above
            but the user can enter multiple lines of text. This is when you
            want to have a detailed answer to the question</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Comment</emphasis>: this is not really
            a question. It&#39;s a convenient way to insert comments in your
            list of questions.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">None</emphasis>: Assigning this type
            to a question will result in the de-activation of the question.
            This question will disappear from all the surveys using it. As
            usual in CodeX the question is not deleted and all the answers
            collected so far in the various survey where this question is used
            remain untouched.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>At any moment in the creation phase you can display the list of
        existing questions by clicking on the &#34;Show Existing
        Questions&#34; button at the bottom of the screen</para>

        <para>Editing questions is also possible. To do so, click on the
        &#34;Edit Existing Questions&#34; item in the Survey Manager
        Administration menu or in the content of the page itself (see <xref
        linkend="FigureSurveyManagerAdministrationScreen" />). You are then
        presented with the list of questions that are currently available in
        your question pool. Clicking on the question identifier number in the
        leftmost column allows you to change the question properties.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="underline">Remark</emphasis>: changing a
        question after responses have already been collected is a bad idea
        especially when changing the question type. In this case collected
        data will become inconsistent with the new question type. On the other
        hand, correcting a typo in the question or making the question clearer
        is perfectly OK and doesn&#39;t impact the existing set of answers.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="CreatingorEditingaSurvey">
        <title>Creating or Editing a Survey</title>

        <para>Once you have created questions in the common question pool, you
        can create a survey and attach questions to it.</para>

        <para>To create a survey click on the &#34;Add Surveys&#34; item
        either in the Survey Manager Administration menu or in the content of
        the page itself (see <xref
        linkend="FigureSurveyManagerAdministrationScreen" />). Then enter the
        following information:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>The name of the survey (give it a short title)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The list of questions attached to the survey. This is a
            comma separated list of question identifiers (IDs) that you want
            to use for this survey. To see question IDs in a separate window,
            click on the &#34;Show Existing Questions&#34; and choose the
            appropriate question IDs from the list. The questions will appear
            in the survey in the same order as in the list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The status of the survey: you can make it active or not. As
            long as a survey is inactive it doesn&#39;t show up in the welcome
            screen of the Survey Manager meaning that it is not visible to
            CodeX users. Similarly accessing the survey directly via its Web
            location will not work either.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>At the bottom of the screen is a list of all the surveys defined
        for your project. You can edit any of the survey by clicking on the
        survey ID in the leftmost column. Editing a survey can be also be done
        by clicking on the &#34;Edit Existing Surveys&#34; item in the Survey
        Manager Administration menu and then choosing the survey to edit at
        the bottom of the screen. While editing a survey you can change the
        list of questions or the order of the questions without impacting the
        current result set. If you remove a question from the survey, you
        won&#39;t be able to view the existing set of responses. However it
        does not mean they are lost. Re-inserting the question ID in the
        survey list allows you to view the set of responses again (see next
        section).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="ReviewingSurveyResults">
        <title>Reviewing Survey Results</title>

        <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

        <para>At any point in the life of the survey, project members can have
        a look at the existing set of answers that have already been given by
        the users who took the survey. To review the results of a given survey
        click on the &#34;Show Results&#34; item in the Survey Manager
        Administration menu and then click on the Survey ID number you are
        interested in.</para>

        <para>A list of all the questions attached to this survey will show up
        on the screen. Next to each question is an aggregate view of the
        existing answers. For questions of type &#34;text field&#34; or
        &#34;text area&#34; you can review the full list of answers. For radio
        buttons, the Survey Manager compute the total number of answers, the
        average value as well as the value distribution for radio button
        answers.</para>

      <para><tip> <title>Export Your Survey Results for Finer Grain
      Analysis</title> <para>If you want to further massage the
      results of your surveys remember that CodeX allows project
      administrators to export project data including survey
      results. For more details see <xref linkend="ProjectDataExport"
      /> </para></tip></para>
      
        <figure id="FigureSurveyResults">
          <title>Survey Results</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_surveyresults.png" width="11cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

      </section>
    </section>

    <para></para>
    <para></para>
    

  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->