<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="TaskManager">
    <title>Task Manager (deprecated)</title>

  <para><tip><title>** The Task Manager is DEPRECATED **</title>
  <para>In CodeX version 1.7 and above, the Task Manager has been
  discontinued. It is now replaced by the CodeX Tracker Service (see
  <xref linkend="TrackerService"/>). This chapter is included in the
  CodeX User Guide for projects that originally used the legacy Task
  Manager.</para></tip></para>

  <para>The CodeX Task Manager can be seen as a light weight project
  manager. By light weight we mean that it is nowhere near a project
  management software like CA-SuperProject, MS-Project or other
  powerful and complex desktop products available on the market. The
  CodeX Task Manager cannot build a Gantt or Pert chart, it
  doesn&#39;t have any planning capabilities. It is rather a time
  sheet tool which allows project members to track their time and
  manage other things like weekly TODO list for instance.</para>

    <para>However the CodeX Task Manager offer a number of features that makes
    it very complementary with the above mentioned project planning tools:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                  spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Like all CodeX tools, the Task Manager is entirely web based.
        Therefore any project member can update his/her time sheet regardless
        of its physical location.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tasks can be created and managed by authorized project members.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Each project member has its own time sheet showing all open
        tasks assigned to her, their priority, description, start and end
        dates, percentage completion, related tasks, follow-up comments and a
        full audit trail of the past changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Task data can be collected by the project leader(s) at any point
        in time and exported out of the CodeX project thanks to the Project
        Data Export facility (see <xref linkend="ProjectDataExport" />). This
        allows for easy generation of progress reports or project re-planning.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>As mentioned earlier in this document, the CodeX Bug Tracking system
    has undergone a number of modifications and enhancements derived from the
    CodeX users feedback. We expect the CodeX Task Manager to evolve in the
    same way in the near future. We have as an objective to keep it simple
    while providing a better integration with other tools that project teams
    are using for project planning activities. Therefore we value your
    comments on the way you work and how we could make your life easier with
    CodeX.</para>

    <section id="TaskManagerPrinciples">
      <title>Task Manager Principles</title>

      <para>Tasks can be created by any project member having the
      &#34;Tech&#34; level of permission on the Task Manager (see <xref
      linkend="UserPermissions" />). A task can be assigned to one or
      several project members and each of the project members will see the
      tasks in their own time sheet as soon as assignees are designated.</para>

      <para>Tasks are grouped under subprojects. The experience shows that
      Subprojects generally correspond to high level tasks or modules in the
      project. Note that, in its current version, the CodeX Task Manager
      offers a one level only hierarchy where to organize your tasks. In other
      words, you cannot create a subproject in an subprojects only tasks.</para>

      <para>As you already know the general rule in CodeX is that, by default,
      all information is visible to the CodeX community. This principle also
      applies to the CodeX Task Manager and by default all your project task
      are visible to the entire CodeX community. If you want some of your
      tasks to be visible only to the project members you can create a private
      subproject and assign the private tasks to it.</para>

      <para><tip><title>The CodeX Task Manager is not a project planning tool</title><para>This
      is best illustrated by the fact that CodeX does not maintain any kind of
      dependency between the task fields that are time related. Starts date,
      end date, percentage complete and total efforts are not inter-dependent.
      In other words changing any of these values will not cause CodeX to
      compute new values for the other ones. It is entirely up to the project
      members to keep the time related fields in sync.</para></tip></para>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskBrowsing">
      <title>Task Browsing</title>

      <para>To access the Task Manager of a given project, first go to the
      Project Summary page (see <xref linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />)
      and then select either the &#34;Tasks&#34; item from the Project Main
      Menu in the upper part of the page or the &#34;Project/Task Manager&#34;
      item listed the Public Area at the bottom of the Project Summary page.</para>

      <para>The welcome screen shows the list of subprojects that have been
      created in this project (<xref
      linkend="FigureATaskManagerHomePageShowing2Subprojects" />). If a
      project uses its Task Manager there is at least one subproject listed on
      the page because any new task must be assigned to a subproject.</para>

      <figure id="FigureATaskManagerHomePageShowing2Subprojects">
        <title>A Task Manager home page showing 2 subprojects</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmhomepage.png" width="13cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Also note that, when more than one subproject have been defined by
      the project team, a special subproject item called &#34;All tasks in all
      subprojects&#34; appears at the bottom of the list. This item is
      generated by CodeX and allows you to access all tasks of all subprojects
      at once.</para>

      <para>By clicking on one of the subproject label you will then be
      directed to the Task selection and browsing screen (<xref
      linkend="FigureASampleTaskManagerBrowsingScreen" />) that allows you to
      better define what set of tasks you are interested in. The Task Manager
      doesn&#39;t have the degree of customizability found in the Bug Tracking
      System. As a consequence all the screenshots used in this document that
      have been taken from a particular project on CodeX will look very
      similar for any other CodeX hosted project.</para>

      <para>The Task selection and browsing screen offers a set of 3 criteria
      to choose from:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Subproject</emphasis>: select the
          subproject that you want to explore or &#34;Any&#34; if you want the
          search operation to operate across the entire set of subprojects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Assignee</emphasis>: select the name of
          the project member the tasks have been assigned to, &#34;Any&#34; if
          you want all assignees to be part of the search or &#34;None&#34; to
          look at the tasks that have not yet been assigned to a project
          member.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: select the status of
          the tasks you are interested in, &#34;Any&#34; if you want to see
          all statuses and &#34;None&#34; for tasks that have not be given a
          status yet (more on the status values and their meaning in <xref
          linkend="TaskSubmission" />).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure id="FigureASampleTaskManagerBrowsingScreen">
        <title>A sample Task Manager browsing screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A click on the &#34;Browse&#34; button initiates the search
      operation and the matching tasks are displayed in a table format. The
      task report shows a certain number of tasks fields. Like in the Bug
      Tracking System, a click on any of the column label will instantly sort
      the list of tasks according to this criterion. Most of the columns have
      a straightforward meaning and we&#39;ll only focus on those with
      specific features:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Task ID</emphasis>: this is a unique
          task ID number. A click on this ID number will show you the task
          details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">End Date</emphasis>: overdue task have
          an end date appearing in bold characters. An asterisk (*) on the
          left hand side of the end date denotes a task that was due more than
          30 days ago.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Depend On</emphasis>: shows a list of
          task ID numbers depending on the task if any. Each task ID number is
          an hyperlink to the corresponding task details.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Project members will also find useful shortcuts in the Task
      Manager menu to quickly access all currently open tasks (&#34;Browse
      Open Tasks&#34;) and also all the tasks they are in charge of (&#34;My
      Tasks&#34;). The latter is also visible in your Personal Page.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Obtaining nice printouts of task and bug report</title><para>If
      you want to print nice reports do not forget to set up the paper
      orientation to &#34;Landscape&#34; in the print dialog box of your Web
      browser (File -&#62; Page Setup for IE) to avoid table clipping. Another
      option to generate more sophisticated printouts is to use the
      &#34;Project Data Export&#34; facility to instantly download bugs and
      tasks data in your favorite desktop application like Excel, Word, etc.
      (see <xref linkend="ProjectDataExport" />)</para></tip></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Advanced Search Mode</emphasis></para>

      <para>At any time during the search phase, you can toggle the search
      mode from Simple to Advanced and vice-versa (see the Advanced Search
      link). The Advance Search mode allows you to select multiple values for
      each selection criteria. Using this mode you could search for say tasks
      in &#34;New features&#34; and &#34;Administration - Maintenance&#34;
      subprojects which status is either open or or suspended.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskSubmission">
      <title>Task Submission</title>

      <para>First of all it is worth mentioning that unlike most other CodeX
      services, new tasks can only be created by project members with
      appropriate permissions on the Task Manager, not by ordinary registered
      users. To create a new task in a given project, first go to the Project
      Summary page (see <xref linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />) and
      then select either the &#34;Tasks&#34; item from the Project Main Menu
      and select the subproject the new task belongs to. Finally click on the
      &#34;Add Task&#34; item in the Task Manager menu (<xref
      linkend="FigureASampleTaskManagerBrowsingScreen" />) appearing in the
      upper part of the screen.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="FigureTaskSubmissionScreen" /> shows the task
      submission screen from one of the CodeX hosted project (the CodeX
      project itself actually). Let&#39;s review the task fields in order:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                    spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Percent complete</emphasis>: goes from
          &#34;Not Started&#34; to &#34;100%&#34; by step of 5%. This field
          indicates how much of the task has been completed so far.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Priority</emphasis>: task priority on a
          scale from 1 (lowest) to 9 (highest)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Task Summary</emphasis>: A one line
          description of the task</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Task Details</emphasis>: a comprehensive
          description of the task. This field accept formatted text with break
          lines. Web locations (http://...) typed in the task summary will be
          automatically transformed into hyperlink when they are later
          displayed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Start Date and End Date</emphasis>:
          calendar days at which the task is expected to start and finish</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Assigned To</emphasis>: project members
          in charge of the task (multiple selection is possible)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Dependent on Task</emphasis>: List of
          task(s) the new task depends on. Note that the Task Manager does not
          associate any semantic to the dependency link. It is a very common
          practice in CodeX to use this dependency relation as a time
          dependency but it can be any kind of dependency you see relevant for
          your own project.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Effort (Hours)</emphasis>: Initial
          estimation of the number of working hours required to perform the
          new task.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When a new task is created its status is automatically set to
      Open. This can be changed later in the Task Update screen (see below)</para>

      <figure id="FigureTaskSubmissionScreen">
        <title>Task Submission screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
                       fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmsubmission.png" width="15.3cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskUpdate">
      <title>Task Update</title>

      <para>Once a task has been created a project member with appropriate
      permissions can update any of the task field to reflect the task
      progress. Note that ordinary registered users cannot modify a task. They
      can only view the task details and post a follow-up comment.</para>

      <para>To update a task, first use the Task browsing and selection module
      to retrieve the task you are interested in (remember to use the &#34;My
      Tasks&#34; shortcut in the Task Manager menu if it&#39;s one of your
      task).</para>

      <para>All the screenshots used in this section assumes that the CodeX
      user is part of the project team. For non project members the screen
      layout is roughly the same but information shown on the screen cannot be
      changed.</para>

      <para>The Task Update screen is divided in 4 parts: <emphasis
      role="bold">Headers, Comments, Dependencies and History</emphasis>.</para>

      <section id="TaskHeaders">
        <title>Headers</title>

        <figure id="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskHeaders">
          <title>Task Update screen: the Task Headers</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmheaders.png" width="13cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This is where you&#39;ll find all the task fields associated
        with a task description. As shown on <xref
        linkend="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskHeaders" />, many of these
        fields (e.g. Status, Subprojects, Priority) are assigned a set of
        predefined values while some others have a number format (Effort) or a
        free text format (Task Summary). Most of these fields have already
        been described in <xref linkend="TaskSubmission" />. In this section
        we&#39;ll only focus on the fields that have not yet been explored:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                      spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: a task status value
            can be one of</para>

            <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
                          spacing="compact">
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">None</emphasis>: this value
                is normally not used in the CodeX system because all new tasks
                are automatically set to Open (see below). However it is
                perfectly ok to use it e.g. for tasks that have not yet been
                assigned or for pending tasks</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Open</emphasis>: this is the
                status that you should use for all on-going task. This is the
                default status when a new task is created</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Closed</emphasis>: Change the
                task status to Closed when a task is completed.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Deleted</emphasis>: Use this
                status for a task that is no longer relevant. Either because
                the project directions have changed and it doesn&#39;t make
                sense to perform this task or when this task is actually
                covered by another one. Marking the task as deleted will not
                delete it for real.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Suspended</emphasis>: the
                task is on-hold for some time. Use this transient status when
                you don&#39;t want the list of Open tasks cluttered with task
                that have been delayed by weeks or months.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="TaskComments">
        <title>Comments</title>

        <para>As many follow-up comments as needed can be attached to any
        given task. Follow-up comments are free text fields where virtually
        any kind of information or comment can be typed in. The &#34;Original
        Comment&#34; field filled out by the task submitter can actually be
        considered as the first follow-up comment in the life of a task.</para>

        <para>For your convenience, the original comment can be modified by
        using the [Edit] link next to the &#34;Original Comment&#34; field (<xref
        linkend="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskFollowupComments" />). We
        recommend using this feature only to correct typos or add pivotal
        information overlooked in the initial description. For all other
        occasions, use the follow-up comments mechanism and do not touch the
        original description. Follow-up comments allows you to track the
        history of a task, how the work was done, what source files were
        impacted, etc.</para>

        <figure id="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskFollowupComments">
          <title>Task Update screen: the Task Follow-up comments</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmcomments.png" width="15.3cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="TaskCCList">
	      <title>CC List</title>
	
	      <para>As the CodeX BTS, the Task Manager offers the same powerful email 
	      notification system (refer to the BTS for more details <xref
	      linkend="BugCCList" />).</para>
      </section>
	
      <section id="TaskAttachments">
        <title>Task Attachments</title>

        <para>In addition to comments, the Task Manager
      allows you to attach virtually any piece of information to a task
      in the form of a file. The mechanism is same as the BTS one (see <xref linkend="BugAttachments" />.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="TaskDependencies">
        <title>Dependencies</title>

        <para>The next section on the task update screen deals with
        task-to-task dependencies (see <xref
        linkend="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskDependencies" />). CodeX users
        have the ability to establish a dependency link from a task to one or
        several other tasks.</para>

        <para>The CodeX system does not impose any semantic on the nature of
        the dependency links between tasks. However it is a common CodeX
        practice to assume a time dependency between the task displayed on the
        screen and the selected tasks in the dependency list. In other words,
        the task in the dependency list must be completed first.</para>

        <figure id="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskDependencies">
          <title>Task Update screen: the Task Dependencies</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmdependencies.png" width="13cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The task dependency section also gives cross-reference
        information and shows the list of tasks and bugs that depend on the
        task you are currently viewing. Refer to <xref
        linkend="BugDependencies" /> for more information about bug-to-tasks
        dependencies.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="TaskHistory">
        <title>History</title>

        <para>The last part of the task update screen is devoted to task state
        history (see <xref linkend="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskHistory" />).
        Thanks to this section you can review the entire history of a task.
        The Task History keeps track of all the changes that occurred on all
        task fields since the task creation.</para>

        <para>The Task History shows what fields changed, what was the old
        value before the change took place, who changed it and when. Since the
        Task History only gives you the old value of a bug field it requires a
        bit of exercise to determine what the new value was right after the
        change took place.</para>

        <para>A Task Change History must be read from top to bottom. Referring
        to the task headers (<xref
        linkend="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskHeaders" />) you can see that
        task #12 has its status set to Closed and an effort of 10 hours.
        Exploring the Task Change History you can say that the status was set
        to &#34;Closed&#34; on February 9th, 2001 at 11:47am and that the task
        was &#34;Open&#34; before the change took place. Similarly the effort
        was updated at the same date and time and went down from 24 hours to
        10 hours. You can also infer from the Task Change History that the
        task priority (currently at 7) was never changed in the life of the
        task because it doesn&#39;t show up in the list. This task was given
        Priority 7 when it was first created and it never changed after that.</para>

        <figure id="FigureTaskUpdateScreenTheTaskHistory">
          <title>Task Update screen: the Task History</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_pmhistory.png" width="13cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskEmailNotification">
      <title>Email Notification</title>

    <para>The Task Manager is equipped with a powerful and flexible
    e-mail notification system. This system works as the BTS one (see <xref
        linkend="BugEmailNotification" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskManagerAdministration">
      <title>Task Manager Administration</title>

      <para>The Task Manager Administration is available under the item
      &#34;Admin&#34; in the Task Menu bar. Only project members with Task
      Administrator permission are allowed to interact with this module.</para>

      <para>The Task Administration module gives access to
      the following administrative functions:</para>

    <section id="TaskManagerAddaSubproject">
      <title>Add a Subproject</title>

      <para>This is to create a new subproject in the Task
      Manager. Subprojects generally correspond to high level modules
      or activities in the project. To create a project you must give
      it a short subproject name, a one line description and decide
      whether it is a public or private subprojects. Private
      Subprojects are only visible to project members.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskManagerUpdateaSubproject">
      <title>Update a Subproject</title>

      <para>Use this function whenever you want to update a
      subproject. You can change its name and description, whether it
      is public or private.  You can also mark a subproject as
      deleted. Deleted subprojects will disappear from the Task
      selection and browsing screen as well as all the tasks that
      belong to this subproject. At any point in time you can decide
      to re-activate a deleted subproject without loosing any
      data.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="TaskManagerPersonalConfigurationSettings">
      <title>Personal Configuration Settings</title>

      <para>This page allows a user to set up personal preferences for
      the Task Manager. In its current version it allows the user to
      specify which default date should be displayed in the task
      submission form for the 'Start Date' and 'End Date'
      fields. There are two possible choices:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Current Date</emphasis>: if you
	  choose this value, the task creation form displays the
	  current date in both the 'Start Date' and 'End Date'
	  fields. This is the default setting.</para>
	</listitem>
    
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">No Date</emphasis>: both fields
	  remain empty and the 'Start Date' and 'End Date' are
	  undefined. You may select this option if you use the task
	  manager as a simple TODO list where start and end dates do not
	  really matter.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="TaskEmailNotificationSettings">
      <title>Email Notification Settings</title> 
      <para>The Task Manager comes with a predefined set of rules to keep people involved in task
      management aware of the task life. The mechanism is the same as the BTS one (see 
      <xref linkend="BugEmailNotificationSettings" />)</para>

    </section>


    <section id="TaskManagerOtherConfigurationSettings">
      <title>Other Configuration Settings</title>

        <para>This module allows you to define the following
        configuration parameters for the CodeX Bug Tracking
        System:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>An introductory message that displays at the top of
            the Bug submission form. This is a convenient way to give
            directions and recommendations to the bug submitter. The text must
            use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great flexibility to
            shape the content of this preamble (you can use bold, italic,
            embedded URL, ...)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Other items may be added in the future.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>


  </section>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

