<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
//
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, Codendi 2007-2008.
// This file is licensed under the GNU General Public License version 2. See the file COPYING. 
//
//
//
-->
      
<chapter id="TrackerV5Service">
  <title>New Tracker Service (BETA)</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Disclaimer:</emphasis> this chapter covers the new version (aka v5) of Tracker service.
  For documentation on current tracker system see <xref linkend="TrackerService" />.</para>

  <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker is one of the most powerful and versatile
  services offered to &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; hosted projects. It allows for the tracking 
  of various artifacts like bugs, tasks, requirements, etc... and a 
  project can create and customize as many trackers as necessary.</para>

  <para>All trackers, whether predefined at the site level or created
  by a project can be fully customized. </para>

  <section id="TrackerV5TrackerPrinciples">
    <title>Terminology and common features</title>

    <para>Before we explain the features of the tracker service, it's
    worth spending some time on the terminology used in the tracker
    service as well as on some of the features that are shared by all
    trackers.</para>

    <para>As the Tracker Service is meant to track virtually any kind
    of item, the generic term &#34;<emphasis role="bold">artifact</emphasis>&#34; 
    will be used throughout this document to designate items that are being 
    tracked - be it bug, task, support request, user stories or other such type.</para>

    <para>Defining a tracker is just a matter of assigning it a name,
    choosing the fields that are going to be used in the tracker,
    and what values will be allowed in those fields.</para>

    <para>In addition to the project definable fields and field values there
    is a <emphasis role="bold">Follow-ups</emphasis> section that is permanently attached to a tracker
    artifact. This one allows you to follow the artifact lifecycle (values changed 
    and free text comments attached to an artifact and posted by users).
    In this section you can also add a <emphasis role="bold">follow-up comment</emphasis>
    that will be added in the follow-ups flow.
    </para>
  </section>


  <section id="TrackerV5EnteringtheTrackerService">
    <title>Entering the Tracker Service</title>

    <para>To enter the Tracker service of a given project, first go to
    the Project Summary page (see <xref
	linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />) and either click
    the &#34;Trackers&#34; item in the Project Main Menu located in the
    upper part of the page or you can directly choose a tracker from the
    trackers listed in the Public Area of the Project Summary page.</para>

    <para>You will be presented with a list of trackers available for
    this particular project (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5WelcomeScreen"
	/>. Select the tracker you are interested in. Entering the
    tracker will give you access to various tracker functions
    depending on the permissions you have with this tracker. You may
    be able to submit new artifacts, update existing ones, search
    and browse the artifact database or configure the tracker.</para>

    <figure id="TrackerV5WelcomeScreen">
      <title>Tracker Welcome Screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerwelcomescreen_new.png" width="14.5cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    

  </section>

  <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmission">
    <title>New Artifact Submission</title>

    <para>To submit a new artifact to a given project you must first
    access the appropriate tracker of that project as indicated in the
    section above (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5EnteringtheTrackerService" />.</para>

    <para>When entering a given tracker you are presented with the
    artifact selection and browsing screen (more about this facility
    in <xref linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactBrowsing" />). For now let&#39;s click
    on the &#34;Submit new artifact&#34; item (or whatever the artifact
    name is) from the Tracker Menu Bar in the upper part of the welcome
    screen (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen"
	/>).</para>

    <figure id="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheProject">
      <title>A sample artifact submission screen (the artifact is of type &#34;bug&#34; here)</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactsubmission_new.png" width="14.5cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><xref linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheProject"
	/> shows a sample submission screen from one of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; hosted
    projects. Because of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker high level of
    customizability no two submission screens look alike. Depending on
    the project more or less fields may appear on the tracker
    submission form and the name of artifact managed by the tracker
    may change as well.</para>

    <para>In the example provided on <xref
    linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheProject" /> the
    artifact type is a bug (also know as &#34;defect&#34; in corporate
    language). The user is asked to give a one-line description for the bug and a longer
    text entry field where you can fully characterize the bug. Then, he has to choose a bug Category
    and a Severeity. After clicking on the Submit button, a unique ID is automatically
    assigned to the submitted artifact.</para>

    <para>When submitting a new artifact, make the Summary and the
    detailed description as explicit as possible.  Do not use a
    clueless summary like: &#34;Service X doesn&#39;t work&#34; or
    &#34;Blocking problem in Document Mgr&#34;. Explain the exact
    nature of the artifact by giving an explicit Summary and
    Description to the person in charge. A unique ID is automatically
    assigned to the submitted artifact.</para>

    <para>The values proposed by a field could depend upon other field value. If javascript is activated in your browser, fields will be filtered dynamically. Otherwise, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; will ensure that the values you submit are correct.</para>

    <para>As explained above, artifact submission forms vary from one
    project to another depending on the fields used by the
    tracker. The submission form can also vary according to the
    permission level. Depending whether you are a project member or an
    ordinary registered user the artifact fields displayed on the
    screen may differ. As an example, on <xref
    linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheProject" />, the bug
    submitter using the form is probably a project member because
    giving access to the &#34;Assigned to&#34; field to an ordinary
    registered user doesn&#39;t make much sense. It is very unlikely
    that users external to the project team know enough about the
    project organization to correctly assign the bug. That's the reason why 
    artifact fields shown to users on the submission form can be
    configured in the Tracker Administration module (see <xref
    linkend="TrackerV5Administration" />)</para>

    <para>In any case don&#39;t forget to click on the
    &#34;Submit&#34; button when you are finished !</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: make sure your artifact hasn&#39;t yet been
    submitted</title><para>About to submit a bug or a support request
    to a &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Project? Before you do that, make sure that others
    haven&#39;t yet submitted a similar artifact. To do so you can
    either browse the artifact database through the Artifact Selection
    and Browsing facility or you can use the search box in the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
    Main Menu and search by keywords.</para></tip></para>

  </section>

  <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactBrowsing">
    <title>Artifact Browsing</title>

    <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; offers the ability to browse the artifact database
    according to a variable set of criteria.</para>

    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactSelectionCriteria">
      <title>Selection Criteria</title>

      <para>The upper part of the artifact browsing screen is devoted to the
        selection criteria. <xref
	  linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" /> shows the
        default set of selection criteria that is available when a new tracker
        is created. You can select bugs by Category (the module in which the
        bug occurred), Group (nature of the bug like Crash, Documentation
        Typo, ...), Status (e.g. Open, Closed, ...) and Assignee (the person
        in charge of the bug). But you may also add or remove criteria 
        by using the "Toggle criteria" link.(for more details, see <xref
        linkend="TrackerV5Reports" />)</para>

      <para>How selection criteria are filled out depend on their
      field type. The Tracker Service currently has several types
      of fields used as search criteria:</para>

      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactSelectBoxField">
	<title>Select Box Field and Multiple Select Box Field</title>

	<para>A select box field can take its value in a set of
	predefined values. By default, only one value can be selected at a time. If you
	want to select multiple values at once, use the Advanced Search
	facility by clicking on the + icon. A multi select box appears and allows the user to select multiple
	values for the same field.</para>

	<para>There might be 2 specific values in the list of choices:
	&#34;Any&#34; matches any value in the list and &#34;None&#34; matches the
	items where no value has been assigned yet</para>
      </section>


      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactTextField">
	<title>Text Field</title>

        <para>A Text field can contain any kind of text. There are two
        ways to query a text field:</para>


	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Keyword
	    search</emphasis>: you can type a series of space
	    separated keywords that will ALL be searched for in the
	    text field (including as substring in
	    words)</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	    expression</emphasis>: You can also specify a <ulink
	    url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/regexp.html">MySQL
	    Extended Regular Expression</ulink> as a matching criteria
	    (mind the surrounding /.../ !)</para>

	    <para>Examples:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para>/^[Aa]ddition/ : matches any text field starting
		with either &#34;addition&#34;or &#34;Addition&#34;</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>/foo|bar|dim/ : matches text fields containing the string &#34;foo&#34;, &#34;bar&#34; or &#34;dim&#34;</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactDateField">
	<title>Date Field</title>

	<para>A date criteria follows the following pattern:
	YYYY-MM-DD where YYYY is the year number, MM is the month
	number and DD is the day number.</para>

	<para>Examples: 1999-03-21 is March 21st, 1999, 2002-12-05 is
	Dec 5th, 2002. </para>
	
	<para>You can search an exact date (using = in the operator select box),
	all dates before a certain date (using &lt;) or all dates after (using &gt;).
	</para>
	<para>By cliking the + icon, you can use the advance search and search for dates 
	between two specific dates.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactIntegerField">
	<title>Integer Field</title>

	<para>An integer field can take positive or (possibly)
	negative values and has no decimal part.</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1, +2, -100&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an integer field. Here
	are the values you can specify in a integer query field:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Integer</emphasis>: if you type a single integer the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 610)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &gt;= or =&lt; followed by an integer
	    the search will look for integer values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120 , &lt; -30)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the &#34;integer1-integer2&#34; notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. 800 - 900 for integers
	  between 800 and 900, -45 - 12 for integers between -45 and
	  +12)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/regexp.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be used as a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all integer
	  values starting with a &#34;4&#34;, ending with an &#34;8&#34; with any
	  number of digits in between.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactFloatingPointNumberField">
	<title>Floating Point Number Field</title><para>A floating
	point number field can take positive or (possibly) negative
	values, may have a decimal part or use the exponential
	notation for large values.. .</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1.23, -2.456, 122.45E+12&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an floating point number
	field. Here are the values you can specify in such a
	field:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Number</emphasis>: if you type a single number the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 2.35)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &gt;= or =&lt; followed by a number
	    the search will look for all values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120.3 , &lt; -3.3456E-2)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the &#34;number1-number2&#34; notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. -1.2 - 4.5 for numbers greater than or equal to -1.2 and lesser than or equal to 4.5)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.0/en/regexp.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be used as a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all 
	  values starting with a &#34;4&#34;, ending with an &#34;8&#34; with any
	  number of characters in between including the decimal point.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5SearchResults">
      <title>Tracker Search Results</title>
      
      <para>Based on your selection of search criteria, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; runs a
      query against the tracker database, selects the matching
      artifacts, and displays them right below the selection
      criteria. Columns displayed in the artifact list are entirely
      configurable by the user. (see <xref
	  linkend="TrackerV5Reports" />). Therefore, the artifact browsing
      screen might look completely different from the one shown in
      <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" />.</para>

      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen">
	<title>A sample Tracker browsing screen</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Results are listed by chunks of N
      artifacts where N is user-definable. If more than N artifacts
      are retrieved from the tracker database you are invited to click
      on the navigation bar to display the next or previous chunk of
      artifacts.</para>

      <para>To access a given artifact from the list of results,
      simply click on the icon <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
          format="PNG" fileref="../../icons/artifact-arrow.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>.</para>

      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactListSorting">
	<title>Artifact List Sorting</title>

	<para>By default, artifacts are sorted by the chronological order of the submission on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.</para>

	<para>The list of artifacts can be sorted by any of the
	columns displayed on the screen by clicking on the column
	heading. Clicking twice on the same heading toggles the sort
	order between ascending to descending.  The currently displayed
        sorting direction is shown by a small up or down arrow next to
	the sort criteria right above the artifact list. </para>

	<para>For more sophisticated sorting you can also use the
	multi-column sort.  In this mode sort criteria accumulates as
	you click on column headings.  So you can for instance click
	&#34;Severity&#34; first and &#34;Assigned To&#34; second to see who in the
	team is assigned critical bugs and how many.At any point in
	the multi-column sort process, a click on one of the sort
	criteria displayed in the list (criteria 1 > criteria 2 >
	criteria 3...)  will bring you backward in the sort criteria
	list. Using this feature you can easily test various sorting
	strategies.</para>

      </section>
      
    <section id="TrackerV5ExportSearchResults">
        <title>Export Tracker Search Results</title>
        <para>In the report "options" menu, "Export all report columns" and "Export all columns" links allow
        to export all artifacts of your search result into CSV format. 
        Using this facility you can easily select the tracker
        artifacts that you want to process with other tools outside 
        &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;. </para>
        <para>See <xref linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactImport" /> for how to import artifacts 
        from CSV file.</para>
    </section>
    
      <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactPrinterFriendlyVersion">
	<title>Printer Friendly Version</title>

	<para>At any point in the process of browsing the tracker
	database you can click on the &#34;Printer Version&#34; link 
    (in the report "options" menu) to display a simplified and non-decorated artifact list that
	prints nicely or can be copy-pasted in a document of your
	choice. For better readability we strongly advise you to print
	the list of results in landscape format.</para>
      </section>


	<section id="TrackerV5ArtifactCharts">
	 <title>Graphical visualization</title>
	 <para>You can also view graphical results of your search by adding a Charts tab.
     There are four types of graphs supported : Pie, Bar and Gantt charts, but also Burndown charts used in Scrum methodology.
     Like the list of artifact (table renderer), the graphical view respond to the 
     selection criteria.
     For more details, see <xref linkend="TrackerV5ReportRendererCharts" />.
	 </para>
	</section>
</section>

    <section id="TrackerV5Reports">
	<title>Tracker Report Management</title>

	<para>Tracker reports allow the definition of a specific
	layout of the artifact search and browsing screen where one
	can choose the selection criteria and the renderers, which present the search result.
    &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; is proposing two kinds of renderers : "Table" and "Charts".
    The "Table" renderer presents the list of matching artifacts using columns.
    The "Charts" renderer gives a graphical visualization of the results.
    Depending on the project, users may enjoy the ability to 
	choose from several graphical tracker renderers available in the renderer tabs section.
    
    Depending on the project, users may enjoy the ability to choose from several tracker reports
	by using the upper pull-down menu of the artifact browsing
	screen. If no project or user specific tracker report has been
	defined, the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; &#39;Default&#39; report is the only one
	available.</para>


     <para>Any &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; user with access to the tracker can define his
	 own personal report, choosing his own search criteria and adding renderers (tables and charts). 
     In this case the report is a personal one
	 and is only visible to this particular user. On the contrary,
	 tracker administrators have the ability to define project-wide
	 graphical reports that all users will be able to use.
	 </para>
     <section id="TrackerV5ReportSetting">
      <title>Tracker Report Setting</title>
      <para>
       The current report is defined at the top left of the report page (see 
       <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" />).
       If several reports are available, a select box will allow to change the 
       current report.
      </para>
      <para>
       For each report, if you are granted enough to do it, you can either save, 
       save as, change the visibility from public to private, set the current as 
       the default tracker report or delete it.
      </para>
      <para>
            Be careful! When you are tracker admin, updating a public report will
            update the report for every other tracker user. Keep this in mind 
            before saving your modifications.
      </para>
     </section>
     <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererAdd">
      <title>Adding a renderer</title>
      <para>
       You can add as many renderers as you want in any tracker report. 
       Renderer are ordered in tabs. Adding a renderer is easy: simply select 
       the [+] tab on the right of the renderer tabs (see 
       <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" />).
       Select the kind of renderer you want to add (either table or charts), give 
       the renderer a name and a description, and select the submit button.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <title>Ordering report renderers</title>
          <para>
            Renderers can be easily reordered: just drag and drop the tabs!
          </para>
      </tip>
     </section>
     
     <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererTable">
      <title>Table renderer</title>
       <para>
        Table renderer is a textual renderer, usually displayed in a table.
        Columns of the table are tracker fields, and rows of the table are 
        the artifacts.
        <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" />) shows an example 
        of a table renderer.
       </para>
       <para>
        You can select the fields of the renderer (using the Toggle columns link),
        reorder the fields using drag and drop, 
        sort artifact list by fields (by clicking on the field name in the table header),
        browse artifact list selecting the number of displayed artifacts at once
       </para>
       <para>
       It is possible to add aggregates functions on table renderer on specific fields.
       For int, float, select box and multi select box fields, an icon <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="../../icons/sum--plus.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject> is displayed under each column.
       </para>
       <para>
          Simply click on it to add one or several aggragate functions.
       Aggregates functions available are:
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Count</emphasis> (only for int, float, select box and multi select box fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Count Group By</emphasis> (only for int, float, select box and multi select box fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Average</emphasis>  (only for int and float fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Maximum</emphasis>  (only for int and float fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Minimum</emphasis>  (only for int and float fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Std Deviation</emphasis>  (only for int and float fields)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Sum</emphasis>  (only for int and float fields)</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       </para>
     </section>
     
     <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererCharts">
      <title>Charts renderer</title>
       <para>
        Charts renderer allows to add charts in your report.
        &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; provides four kind of graphs: pie, bar, gantt and burndown charts.
        <figure id="TrackerV5FigureChartsTrackerBrowsingScreen">
         <title>A sample charts renderer screen</title>
            <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
               <imagedata format="PNG"
                 fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_graphs_renderer.png" width="15.3cm" />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
       </para>
       <para>
        You can add as many graphs as you want in a charts renderer. To add a graph,
        click on the selected graph icon on the top of the current renderer.
        Regarding the chart type, you will then provide a name, a description,
        and the fields required to build the chart.
       </para>
       <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererChartPie">
        <title>Pie Chart</title>
        <para>
          <figure id="TrackerV5FigurePieChartEdition">
          <title>Pie chart edition screen</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackergraphpie.png" width="15.3cm" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
       </section>
       <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererChartBar">
        <title>Bar Chart</title>
        <para>
          <figure id="TrackerV5FigureBarChartEdition">
          <title>Bar chart edition screen</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackergraphbar.png" width="15.3cm" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
       </section>
       <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererChartGantt">
        <title>Gantt Chart</title>
        <para>
          <figure id="TrackerV5FigureGanttChartEdition">
          <title>Gantt chart edition screen</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackergraphgantt.png" width="15.3cm" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
       </section>
       <tip>
        <title>Gantt charts</title>
        <para>
         Warning! If you're dealing with big projects and your dates spread on 
         several years, don't display your gantt chart by day. The chart will
         be too large. Please chnage the time scale to week, month or year.
        </para>
       </tip>
       <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererChartBurndown">
        <title>Burndown charts</title>
        <para>
          <figure id="TrackerV5FigureBurndownChartEdition">
          <title>Burndown Graph edition screen</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_v5_trackergraphburndown.png" width="15.3cm" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
       </section>
     </section>
     
     <section id="TrackerV5ReportRendererUpdate">
      <title>Updating/removing a renderer</title>
      <para>
        Depending on your permissions, you will be able to update a renderer,
        by clicking the down arrow next to the renderer name.
      </para>
      <para>
        Available actions are title and description update, or renderer deletion.
      </para>
     </section>
     <tip>
      <title>Adding renderers in dashboards</title>
      <para>
       Every renderer (either table or charts) can be displayed in your dashboard.
       To do it, select the link "add to my dashboard" or "add to project dashboard" in the "Options"
       menu.
      </para>
     </tip>
   
    </section>

  
  </section>
  <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactUpdate">
    <title>Artifact Update</title>

    <para>Selecting an artifact from the list generated by
    a search operation will bring you to a screen with all the artifact
    details. Depending on the permissions you have on this tracker 
    (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5FieldPermissionsManagement" />), the 
    detailed view is made of text fields and menus that you
    can update with new values. If you are an
    anonymous user or a registered user who does not belong to the
    project team, most of the fields will likely appear as immutable
    text. By default, non-project members cannot edit any of the artifact
    fields. They can only submit a follow-up comment.</para>

    <para>The Artifact Update screen is divided in several parts:
    <emphasis role="bold">Header and Comments.</emphasis></para>

    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactHeaders">
      <title>Header</title>

      <para>The header zone is where you&#39;ll find all the fields
      associated with an artifact. As shown on <xref
      linkend="TrackerV5FigureHeaderOfArtifactUpdateScreen" />, many of these
      fields are assigned a set of predefined values (Status,
      Category, Resolution) while some others have a number format
      (Effort) or a free text format (Summary). For more clarity, 
      the fields are grouped in field sets.
      The set of fields used in a given tracker, as well as the related set of predefined
      values and the field sets can be configured by project members who have
      administration permissions on this tracker. (see <xref
      linkend="TrackerV5Administration" /> for more details on the
      Tracker configuration).</para>
      
      <section id="TrackerV5DynamicFields">
        <title>Dynamic Fields</title>
        <para>Some fields have a particular behaviour and some explanations seem necessary.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatically edit fields</emphasis>: &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; 
                    includes fields that are automatically set : "Artifact ID", "Last Update Date", "Submitted By" and "Submitted On".
                    The users can't edit that fields.
                 </para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Cross-Reference</emphasis>: &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; offers another dynamic field which has the ability to
                    cross-reference any artifact, or any other &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; object from within a follow-up
                    comment.
                  </para>
                  <para>When typing a follow-up comment, any text that follows the
                    pattern &#34;XXX #NNN&#34; will be interpreted as a reference to the
                    artifact XXX number NNN, where NNN is the unique artifact ID, and XXX is the 
                    tracker short name (e.g. &#34;bug #123&#34;, &#34;task #321&#34;,
                    &#34;req #12&#34;, etc.).
                    If you don't know the tracker short name or don't want to specify it, you
                    may simply use  &#34;art #NNN&#34;.
                    Each time &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; displays a piece of text that follows this pattern it will
                    auto-magically create an hyperlink to the web page showing all
                    the details of the artifact.
                  </para>
                  <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; reference patterns may be used to reference artifacts, as well as source
                     code commits, documents, files, etc. Please refer to 
                     <xref linkend="ReferenceOverview" /> for more details on References.
                  </para>

                  <para>Furthemore references concerning artifacts, svn revisions and
                    cvs commits are stored in the database. They are displayed in the next section, ordered 
                    by type and initial reference direction.
                  </para>
                  
            </listitem>
            <!--<listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Permissions on artifacts</emphasis>: Users that have 
                    permission to access that field can restrict access to artifact. Those permissions are 
                    a complement to the permissions defined at tracker level. 
                </para>
                <para>The user just has to edit the artifact and update permissions 
                    like in the example below (where the artifact is currently restricted to 
                    project admins and members).
                </para>
      
                <figure id="TrackerV5FigureArtifactPermissions">
                    <title>Permission on an artifact</title>
        
                        <mediaobject>
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata format="PNG"
                              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactpermissions.png" />
                          </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                 </figure>
            </listitem>-->
        </itemizedlist>
        
      </section>
      
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureHeaderOfArtifactUpdateScreen">
	<title>Header of Tracker Update screen (artifact fields)</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactupdateheader.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactComments">
      <title>Comments</title>

      <para>As many follow-up comments as needed can be attached to
      any given artifact. Follow-up comments are free text fields
      where virtually any kind of information or comment can be typed
      in.</para>
      
      <para>Follow-up comments have several of interesting capabilities and extensions:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Changeset</emphasis>: 
      Each follow-up comment has a part dedicated to the artifact history. 
      This keeps track of all changes that occurred on all artifact fields since
      the creation of the artifact.
      The artifact history shows what fields changed, what the old value was befor the change took place, who changed it and when.
      </para>
        
    </listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Canned Responses</emphasis>: it
	  is not infrequent to see the project members in charge of
	  the artifact classification and dispatch process to post the
	  same follow-up comments again and again. Typical examples of
	  repeatedly posted comments are: a thank you message to the
	  originator, a request for the originator to provide commonly
	  missing information like version numbers or type of machine
	  used, etc. Rather than typing the same comments all the
	  time, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows project members to create a predefined
	  set of responses. Each canned response is defined by a name
	  and by the body of the response.</para>

	  <para>Posting a canned response is just a matter of
	  selecting the appropriate response from the pull down menu
	  in the artifact update screen and submitting the
	  changes. <!--Defining a new Canned Response can be done on the
	  fly from the artifact update form by clicking on the
	  &#34;define a new Canned Response&#34; link.--></para>
	</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>


      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFollowupCommentsAttachedToAnArtifact">
	<title>Follow-up comments attached to an artifact</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactupdatecomments.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactMassChange">
      <title>Artifact Mass Change</title>
      <para>
       Tracker admins have the ability to update many artifacts at once.
       This feature can be convenient to assign all bugs or tasks of a team 
       member to another if the person is moving on another project for instance.
      </para>
      <para>
       To do this, select the "mass change" link in the "options" menu of the tracker report.
       Please note that only tracker admins have access to that option.
      </para>
      <para>
       You will be able to update any kind of field (except the semantic title field).
       Number of artifacts to be updated are displayed with their artifact Ids.
       By default, all fields have the "value" set to "unchanged".
       If you don't want to update a field, please keep the value unchanged.
       To update a field for every artifacts, just update it.
       You can also add a follow-up comment.
      </para>
      <para>N.B. The artifact mass change feature allows to by-pass any workflow on field(s)</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureArtifactMassChange">
        <title>Artifact Mass Change</title>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackermasschange.png" width="15.3cm" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactLinkTabs">
        <title>Artifact Link</title>
        <para>
        Artifact link field provides a very powerful way to link an artifact to others. Any artifact from any accessible tracker
        can be linked to the current edited artifact.
        Artifact are displayed as a regular tracker report where each tab is a list of artifact of a given tracker according to
        the default renderer of the default selected report.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Linking an artifact</title>
            <para>Click on the sheet icon on the right hand side of the input text field. Then a modal window is opening.
            There one can check or unckeck artifacts. Tracker/Report can be selected, and search criteria specified to browse trackers.
            Once artifact selection is done, selected artifacts are added to the input text field (comma separated), and can be viewed in trackers tabs.
            Note that these advanced functionalities are not available at artifact creation.
            <figure id="TrackerV5HowToLinkAnArtifact">
                <title>How to link an artifact</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata format="PNG"
                                fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_linkingartifact.png" width="15.3cm" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
             </figure>
             <figure id="TrackerV5ModalWindowLinkAnArtifact">
                <title>Browse existing artifacts</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata format="PNG"
                                fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_modalwindowlinkingartifact.png" width="15.3cm" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
             </figure>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Creating an artifact</title>
            <para>As linking another artifacs to a currently edited one, it is possible to create a artifact in different tracker (e.g. sub-tasks addition)
            any created artefact is set as "to be linked", this means that right after creating it is added to its tracker tab, and in the input field text.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Managing linked artifacts</title>
            <para>Linked or "to be linked" artifacts can be managed in the artifact link tabs view. Not yet linked artifacts are highlighted.
           All artifacts can be unckeck (by clicking the red cross).
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5EmailNotification">
        <title>E-mail Notification</title>

        <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker is equipped with a powerful and flexible
    e-mail notification system. Unless otherwise instructed by the
    project administrators or the users themselves, the e-mail
    notification system follows simple default rules. Whenever an
    artifact is created or updated - whether with an additional
    follow-up comment or a change in any of the
    artifact fields - an e-mail message is sent to:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
	<para>The artifact submitter (the person who initially submitted the artifact)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The artifact assignee (the person to whom the artifact is
          currently assigned if the option "Send notifications to selected people" 
          of the field which refers to the assignee has been checked by the tracker admin)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>All users who posted at least one follow-up comment to
	the artifact.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>    

    <para>The e-mail message generated by the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker first
    shows the most recent changes that occurred on the artifact in
    case of an update. It is then followed by a complete snapshot of
    the artifact. Web pointers are also included in the message to
    quickly and easily access the artifact form on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.</para>

  </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5ArtifactImport">
        <title>Tracker Artifact Import</title>

        <para>Project Administrators have the means to import
        artifacts into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; trackers using the well known
        CSV (Comma Separated Value) format supported by all
        of the major office productivity suites. The artifact
        import functionality greatly facilitates the migration
        and integration of external project tracking and management
        tools into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; trackers.</para>

        <para>The import is divided into three steps:

            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">CSV file submission. </emphasis>
                        The project administrators can access the Import
                        functionality from the tracker administration screen or 
                        over the Project Administration Menu. Enter/choose 
                        the tracker to update and specify the CSV file to 
                        import. In this step you can also check the option
                        to send a mail notification to all users concerned by the artifact
                        changes due to the import. If you don't check this
                        option no notification will be sent.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">CSV file parsing. </emphasis>
                        If no parse errors were found in the uploaded file, 
                        a parse report is shown to validate that the information 
                        to import is correct.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Database update. </emphasis>
                        Depending on the parsed information
                        new artifacts are created or existing ones updated.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>When to use the Import</title>
            <para>You will find below a couple of suggestions regarding
                the use of the tracker import feature:

                <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Initial import from a project management software
                        to your &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; task tracker.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Migration of your legacy defect tracking system
                        into your new &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; defect tracker.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Migration of artifacts from one &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; tracker
                        to another.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Exporting Excel Sheets in CSV Format</title>
            <para>To export an Excel sheet to CSV format, simply follow the steps below:
                <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select <literal>File -> Save As</literal>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In the dialog window choose 
                            <literal>CSV</literal> as the <literal>Save 
                            as type</literal>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>CSV File Parsing</title>
            <para>The CSV format that is accepted as import input 
            is accessible over the CSV file submission screen. 
            This page allows manual validation of the tracker 
            field names (shortname), indicating which fields are mandatory in
            case of a new artifact submission. In addition, it gives
            you a sample CSV file.
            As for the export feature, you can specify the separator
            used in the CSV file you want to import as well as the date format 
            (See <xref linkend="UserPreferences" />).
            If you already use the Tracker
            Artifact Export (see <xref linkend="ProjectDataExport" />)
            you will notice that the format of the files to import
            and the exported files are exactly the same. 
            This means that if you changed your CSV separator for exporting 
            data, you must use the same to import those data.
            You can refer to the export format especially
            for the date formats as well as the format of the
            follow-up comments (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactComments" />).
            The first record in the CSV import file is always the 
            header row containing all the tracker field names that 
            will be used in the following artifact records.</para>
            
            <para>Depending on whether you want to import new artifacts
            or update the ones that already exist in the tracker you
            need to provide different information. Nevertheless,
            you can mix in one CSV file the submission of new artifacts
            and the update of existing ones. </para>
            
            <para>For the artifact creation you need to provide
            information on all fields that are specified
            as mandatory in the CSV import format except the Artifact 
            ID which must not be specified. You may omit
            the submitter and submission date. The artifact
            submitter is then automatically set to the
            user importing the CSV file and the submission date
            will be the date of the import.</para>
            
            <para>For the artifact update you need to provide the
            artifact identifier of the artifacts to update in the 
            special column 'aid'. Beside
            this, you only need to provide the fields you want
            to update. All fields not specified in the CSV file 
            will remain unchanged.</para>

            <para>The parsing method checks several potential errors 
                in the CSV file:
                <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Omission of mandatory fields when submitting
                        new artifacts </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Not the same number of columns in the header 
                        row and an artifact row</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Unknown tracker field name</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Field values that do not correspond to the 
                        predefined field values of a (multi) select box field
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Unknown artifact identifier</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Wrong date value</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                All other potential errors have to be checked manually
                by looking at the parse report table.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>The Database Update</title>

            <para>If you import new artifacts, all 
            non-mandatory fields that are omitted in the CSV 
            file will be initialized to their default value.</para>
            
            <para>The submitter and submission date of an existing
            artifact is never changed by an import even if the
            import file contains relevant information.</para>
            
            <para>If an error occurs for some artifact during 
            the database update the following artifacts in the CSV
            file are not imported any more.</para>
            
            <para>Each import is tracked in the project history 
            (<xref linkend="ProjectHistory" />). On the other
            hand, no e-mail notification is sent in response to 
            the import.</para>
        </section>

        <para>
            <tip id="TrackerV5ExcelAndRegionals">
                <title>Tip: Excel and Regionals</title>
                <para>
                If a .csv file is opened in Excel, any change to the spreadsheet 
                (even something as simple as a column resizing) may cause 
                Excel to modify and update the .csv file. Changes that may 
                occur include: dates, times and numbers converted to 
                the same format as those used by your system's regional 
                settings, single line feeds converted to line feed 
                and carriage return, extra commas appended to certain lines.
                </para>

                <para>
                The updated date format might not be compatible with the 
                &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; date format and potentially cause troubles when 
                importing such updated CSV files back into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.
                On the other hand &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;-exported CSV files might not open correctly
                under Excel in certain Regionals.
                </para>

                <para>
                If you have a .csv file that either will not open correctly under 
                Excel or was opened in Excel and will not import 
                into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; please try the following:
                Make sure all applications are closed. Change your system's 
                regional settings (Start > Settings > Control Panel > Regional 
                Options) to use the English with the following formats: 
                Date = MM/dd/YYYY Time = hh:mm. Using Excel, open the 
                .csv files that don't import, make a column width change, 
                save the files and exit Excel. Go back and restore your 
                original regional settings. Import the "fixed" .csv file into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;.
                </para>
            </tip>
        </para>
    </section>
  
  <section id="TrackerV5DefaultTrackerAccessPermissions">
    <title>Default Tracker Access Permissions</title>

    <para>Depending on the class of citizen a user belongs to and the
    level of permissions granted as a project member, the various
    features of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker may or may not be accessible. Please
    note that the default access permissions listed below may change
    for a particular tracker if the tracker administrator modifies the
    access permission settings. For more information on how to
    configure tracker access permissions see <xref
    linkend="TrackerV5PermissionsManagement"/>. Default permission
    settings are summarized in the table below:</para>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>Default Tracker Access Permissions</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
	<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="200pt" />

	<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="250pt"  />

	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Tracker Feature</entry>
	    <entry>Access Permission</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>

	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactSubmission">New Artifact
	      Submission</link></entry> <entry>By default any &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
	      visitor, whether logged in or not, has the ability to
	      submit a new artifact to a tracker. The tracker
	      administrator has the ability to limit the scope of this
	      feature to &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; registered users (anonymous users are
	      requested to login first) or to the project members if
	      the tracker is made private.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactBrowsing">Artifact
	      Browsing</link></entry> <entry>Searching the Artifact
	      database and browsing the results is available to all
	      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; visitors (whether registered or not) unless the
	      tracker has been made private by the project
	      administrator. If so the tracker is only visible to
	      project members.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactUpdate">Artifact
	    Update</link></entry> <entry>By default only project
	    members can update an artifact. Non members have only
	    limited access and can only add a comment or attach a
	    file.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactImport">Tracker
	      Administration - Artifact Import</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission can import data into trackers.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerV5Creation">Tracker
	      Creation</link></entry> <entry>Only available to project
	      administrators.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerV5GeneralSettings">Tracker
	      Administration - General Settings</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerV5FieldUsageManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Field Usage Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerV5SemanticManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Semantic Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5Workflow">Tracker
	      Administration - Workflow Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission can define and configure 
	      workflow.</entry>
	  </row>
      <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5PermissionsManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Permissions Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission can define tracker permissions.</entry>
	  </row>
      <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5CannedResponses">Tracker
	      Administration - Canned Responses Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission can define canned responses.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerV5EmailNotificationSettings">Tracker
	      Administration - Email Notification
	      Settings</link></entry> <entry>Only Project
	      administrators can add email addresses in the global
	      email notification field. Project members can watch artifacts
	      of other team members. Any registered &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; user can
	      customize her notification preferences.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerV5AdminStructureExport">Tracker
	      Administration - Structure Export</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission can export tracker structure.
	    </entry>
	  </row>

	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>


  <section id="TrackerV5Creation">
    <title>Tracker Creation</title>

    <para>Before one can define what fields and field values to use in
    a tracker, it must first be created. Tracker creation can be
    accessed from the &#34;Create a New Tracker&#34; menu item that is
    available in the tracker servide page.</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: Use the predefined trackers
      first!</title> <para>When a new project is created on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; a
      number of trackers are automatically created for this
      project. This would typically be a bug tracker, a task tracker
      and a user story tracker. If your project manages this type
      of artifact please use the predefined trackers first. Of course,
      you are free to define new fields or customize existing ones in
      each of the trackers.</para></tip></para>

    <para>To define a new tracker you must provide the following
      information (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureCreateANewTracker"
	/>): </para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationName">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: this is the
	  name of your tracker. A tracker is typically named after the
	  type of artifact it is going to manage. This name will be
	  used by &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; in the title of the various screens of the
	  trackers. Typical examples of tracker names are: Action
	  Requests, Support Requests, Requirements, Defects,
	  Bugs&hellip;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationDescription">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A longer
	  description of what this tracker is all about and the type
	  of managed artifacts.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationShortName">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Short name</emphasis>: this is a
	  short name that best describe the type of artifact managed
	  in this tracker. This name must be quite short as it is used
	  in various screens of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker like the artifact
	  update form where it appears in the tracker menu and also 
          next to the artifact ID. Following the examples
	  given for the Name field above, short names can be: AR for
	  Action Request, SR for Support Requests, Reqt for
	  Requirements, bug for Bugs&hellip;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure id="TrackerV5FigureCreateANewTracker">
      <title>Creation of a new tracker (here a defect tracking system)</title>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackercreatenewtracker.png" width="13cm"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The next step is to decide upon the set of fields
      available for this tracker. In order to avoid the pain of
      defining the most common type of trackers again and again
      (e.g. Bug tracker, Support Request tracker, etc.) &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; offers
      the ability to create a new tracker from a set of
      templates. Those templates are either &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;-wide templates (also
      known as site templates), project specific templates or an xml file.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remark</emphasis>: using a template
      doesn't mean you have to stick to the list of fields and field
      values defined in this template. You can always add or remove
      fields or fine-tune the field settings afterwards.</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationFromTemplate">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;-wide Template</emphasis>:
	  these are templates that have been defined by the
	  administrators of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; site because it is expected that
	  most project needs them. It is also a way to ensure a
	  certain level of harmonization across projects that will
	  make developers' life easier. The list of available
	  templates may vary from one &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; site to another but you
	  will typically find templates for Bugs, Tasks, etc. A
	  specific tracker called &#34;Empty&#34; allows you to create a
	  virgin tracker with no predefined fields other than the
	  minimal set of required fields. See <xref
          linkend="TrackerV5TrackerTemplates" /> for more explanations
          on the semantic of those templates.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationFromProjectTemplate">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Project Templates</emphasis>: in
	  case you have already defined a tracker that suits your
	  needs or you have seen a tracker from another project that
	  you'd like to reuse, you just have to specify the project ID
	  and tracker ID either by hand or from the pull down menus
	  and click on the create button to create the exact same
	  tracker in your project (<emphasis
	  role="bold">Note</emphasis>: this does not copy the
	  artifacts of the original tracker but only the field
	  settings).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="TrackerV5CreationFromXML">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">XML file</emphasis>:
     &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows you to create trackers from XML file.
     The expected XML file describes the structure of the trackers, the fields
     used, the values of the fields, and the permissions. XML schema is available 
     in /src/www/tracker/resources/tracker.rnc. Most of the time, you will use an XML
     file coming from a tracker structure export (See <xref
      linkend="TrackerV5AdminStructureExport" />). This feature is really convenient 
     to copy a tracker from a server to another.
     <emphasis
	  role="bold">Note</emphasis>: this does not copy the
	  artifacts of the original tracker but only the structure).
    </para>
      </listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>

  </section>


  <section id="TrackerV5TrackerTemplates">
    <title>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;-wide Tracker Templates</title>

    <para>The standard trackers provided for each new &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; project are:
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>Bugs</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Tasks</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>User stories</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Change Requests</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Requirements</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Risks</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
	Each of those templates have predefined fields that correspond
	to the specific work processes around bugs, tasks etc. In
	the following, we give a short overview of these different
	work processes. For each of those templates, the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team
	also tried to maintain a fair balance between sophistication
	and ease of use. As a consequence, fairly simple and
	straightforward templates are configured by default for all
	new hosted projects. Then it is up to the project members to
	decide how much information they want to see attached to an
	artifact and customize their tracker configuration
	accordingly.
	</para>

    <section id="TrackerV5BugTemplate">
      <title>The Bug Tracker Template</title> 

      <para>One of the golden rules in a collaborative project
      environment is to let your project community test the software
      and freely report on any defect (or bug) they have seen. The Bug
      template was developed with this objective in mind.</para>

      <para>The template Bug Tracker comes pre-configured with a set
      of fields (used or not) that are probably enough for the
      majority of projects hosted on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;. You can either decide that
      the template is lacking some critical fields that you can create
      or, on the contrary, switch some fields to the "Unused" status
      to make the tracker simpler.</para>

    </section>


    <section id="TrackerV5TaskTemplate">
      <title>The Task Tracker Template</title>

      <para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Task tracker is a task manager and not a project
      management software like CA-SuperProject, MS-Project or other
      powerful and complex desktop products available on the
      market. The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Task Tracker cannot build a Pert
      chart, it doesn&#39;t have any planning capabilities. It is
      rather a time sheet tool which allows project members to track
      their time and manage other things like weekly TODO list for
      instance.</para>

      <para>However the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Task Tracker offer a number of
    	  features that makes it very complementary with the above
    	  mentioned project planning tools:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
	spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>Like all &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; tools, the Task Tracker is entirely web
	  based.  Therefore any project member can update his/her time
	  sheet regardless of its physical location.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Tasks can be managed by authorized project
	  members.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Each project member has its own time sheet showing all
	  open tasks assigned to her, their priority, description,
	  start and end dates, percentage completion, related tasks,
	  follow-up comments and a full audit trail of the past
	  changes.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>Task data can be collected by the project leader(s) at
	  any point in time and exported out of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; project
	  thanks to the Project Data Export facility (see <xref
	  linkend="ProjectDataExport" />). This allows for an easy
	  generation of progress reports or project
	  re-planning.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
    <section id="TrackerV5ScrumTemplate">
      <title>The User Story Template</title>

      <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; makes it easy to implement the Scrum methodology, by providing
      a User Story tracker to each project. You will find a comprehensive
      description of Scrum on <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrum_(development)">
      Wikipedia</ulink>.</para>

      <para>The User Story tracker contains artifacts called "User Stories", that
      describe needs expressed by the customers of the project. The tracker has
      been customized to capture customer requirements: it is possible to 
      define the customer value of each story, its acceptance criteria, its
      effort, etc.
      </para>
    
      <para>Other optional fields are available, and of course, each project may
      customize the tracker to fit the way it implements the methodology</para>

      <para>At the beginning of a Scrum project, each customer user story must 
      be stored. During the first Sprint Meeting, a few stories are selected by the team to be implemented 
      in the first iteration. The team then affects the stories to team members ('Owner') and can start 
      developing.</para>
     
      <para>At the end of the Sprint (after two to four weeks), the team meets
      for the new Sprint Meeting. User stories selected in the past Sprint are updated, 
      and new stories are selected for the next Sprint.</para> 

    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5ChangeRequestTemplate">
      <title>The Change Request Tracker Template</title>
      <para>
       This tracker allows to submit change requests for your application adjustment. 
       This is of great importance for change management process (ITIL, PRINCE2, ...).
       A change request is declarative, i.e. it states what needs to be accomplished, 
       but leaves out how the change should be carried out.
      </para>
      <para>
       When submitting a change request, you have to provide:
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
         <para>The impacted product (Product, version)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The approval status (approved by, disposal)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The change request description (description, justification, impact if no change)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The change impact analysis (Objectives, deliverable, risks, schedule, budget)</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
       You can set permission to allow only client and project manager groups 
       to access this tracker. For instance:
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
         <para>only client can set the "priority" field</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>only project manager can set the "approved by" and "disposal" fields</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>both can describe impacts fields</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
       As for all trackers, tracker administrator can customize the fields according to the internal process.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5RequirementsTemplate">
      <title>The Requirements Tracker Template</title>
      <para>
       This tracker helps software engineers to identify a necessary attribute, 
       capability, characteristic, or quality of a system in order for it 
       to have value and utility to a user.
      </para>
      <para>
       All system Requirements are also an important input into the verification process, 
       since tests should trace back to specific Requirements.
       This tracker is really useful for Requirements management processes such CMMI.
      </para>
      <para>
       When submitting a Requirement, you have to fulfill:
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
         <para>The designed Product (Product, version)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The Requirement characteristics (type, nature, complexity, priority)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The Requirement description (origin, description, proposed solution)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>The Requirement state (state, satisfied by)</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
       You then can link (using artifacts references) a requirement to a test case/result artifact, 
       or other requirements artifacts for traceability/satisfaction.
      </para>
      <para>
       You can set permission to allow only client and project manager groups to access this tracker.
      </para>
      <para>
       As for all trackers, tracker administrator can customize the fields according to the internal process.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5RiskTemplate">
      <title>The Risk Tracker Template</title>
      <para>
       This tracker aims to support Risk management. It provides information for identification, 
       assessment, and prioritization of risks during the project lifecycle.
       You can minimize, monitor, and control the probability and/or impact of unfortunate events 
       or to maximize the realization of opportunities.
       Risks may be linked (using artifacts references) to actions/task/documentation for minimizing 
       likelihood or impact.
      </para>
      <para>
       When assessing a Risk, you have to set:
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
         <para>Rate of occurrence (likelihood, tendency)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Impacts</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Timescale for Risk occurrence</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Action for risk reduction (action, responsible)</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
       You may use the query form to filter the risks :
       <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
         <para>select the "likelihood" field value "any" if you wish to get all predefined risks</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>select the "likelihood" field value"high", "medium" and "low" if you wish to review your assessed risks</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="TrackerV5Administration">
    <title>Tracker Administration</title>

    <para>As we went through the description of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker
    features, we referred several times to the flexibility of this
    system and how easy it is to customize your own tracker. This can
    be done through the Tracker Administration available in the menu bar of each tracker.</para>

    <para>The configuration settings for a given tracker is divided
      in ten sections:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">General
      Settings</emphasis>: name, description and some other general
      purpose parameters are defined in this section.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Permissions
        Management</emphasis>: allows you to give different
      access permissions to different users depending on their
      role.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Field
	Usage</emphasis>: this is where you will build the tracker.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Semantic</emphasis>: 
      this section allows you to define some fields semantic.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Fields Dependencies
      </emphasis>: allows you to define how values in one field depend upon other field values.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Canned
	Responses</emphasis>: allows you to create some pre-defined
	follow-up comments that your team is using on a regular basis.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Workflow</emphasis>: allows you to define
      a workflow
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Email Notification
	Settings</emphasis>: fine tuning of the global and personal
	email notification settings.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CSV Import</emphasis>: allows you to import 
      data (artifacts) in the tracker with a CSV format</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>: allows you to export 
      the tracker in a xml format</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="TrackerV5GeneralSettings">
      <title>General Configuration Settings</title>

      <para>This module allows you to define a series of properties
      for your tracker. Some of those properties have already been
      defined in the tracker creation form while some others are only
      available on this configuration page. The properties are as
      follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsName">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: this is the
	  name of your tracker. More precisely you want to name your
	  tracker after the type of artifact that are going to be
	  managed in your tracker. This name will be used by &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; in
	  the title of the various screens of the trackers. Typical
	  example of tracker names are: Action Requests, Support Requests,
	  Requirements, Defects or Bugs&hellip;</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsDescription">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A longer
	  description of what this tracker is all about and the type
	  of artifact that it manages.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsShortName">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Short name</emphasis>: this is a
	  short name that best describe the type of artifact managed
	  in this tracker. This name must be quite short as it is used
	  in various screens of the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker like the artifact
	  update form next to the artifact ID. Following the examples
	  given for the Name field above, short names can be: AR for
	  Action Request, SR for Support Requests, Reqt for
	  Requirements, bug for Bugs&hellip;</para>
	</listitem>

    <!--
    <listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsAllowArtifactDuplication">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Allow artifact duplication</emphasis>: 
      if artifact duplication is allowed or not. If it is, only project members
      are able to duplicate artifacts.</para>
	</listitem>
    -->
    
    <listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsInstantiateForNewProjects">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Instantiate for new projects</emphasis>: 
          This parameter is only displayed when working on a &#34;template&#34; type of project (see <xref linkend="ProjectType" />).
          If the parameter is selected, then projects created from this template project will have this tracker created.
          If not selected, the tracker will not be available in the new project.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsSubmitInstructions">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Submit instructions</emphasis>:
	  an introductory message that displays at the top of the
	  artifact submission form. This is a convenient way to give
	  directions and recommendations to the submitter. The text
	  must use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great
	  flexibility to shape the content of this preamble (you can
	  use bold, italic, colors, embedded URL&hellip;)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerV5GeneralSettingsBrowseInstructions">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Browse
	    instructions</emphasis>: an introductory message that
	    displays at the top of the artifact searching and browsing
	    screen.  The text must use HTML tags for formatting which
	    gives a great flexibility to shape the content of this
	    preamble (you can use bold, italic, colors, embedded
	    URL&hellip;)</para>
	</listitem >
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>


    <section id="TrackerV5PermissionsManagement">
      <title>Permissions Management</title>

      <para>This module is used to give different
      access permissions to different users depending on their
      role. </para>

      <para>Access permissions to a tracker can be defined at two
       levels: </para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <!--<para><emphasis role="bold">Tracker/Artifact
	  level</emphasis>: at this level, you can define the group
	  of users who have access to only certain artifacts or have no
	  access at all.</para>-->
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Tracker
	  level</emphasis>: at this level, you can define the group
	  of users who have access or not to the tracker.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Field level</emphasis>: this is a 
          more fine-grained level, where access permissions can be 
          defined field by field. Using this feature you can specify 
          which groups has read-only permission on a field, which ones 
          can modify it or which ones do not have access to it at 
          all. </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>All access permissions are defined for groups of users
      rather than individuals. See <xref linkend="UserGroups" /> for more
      information on how project administrators can define and manage
      groups of users.</para>

      <section id="TrackerV5AndArtifactPermissionsManagement">
        <title>Tracker <!--and Artifacts-->Permissions Management</title>

        <para>When entering this module, a list of user groups appears
        along with their access permissions. The user group list first
        shows groups of users defined at the system level like
        all_users, registered_users, project_members, etc. These are
        groups that &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; manages for you so you don't have to keep
        them up to date when new users subscribe to the site or become
        member of your project. The second part of the user group list
        shows all groups of users defined at the project level (see
        <xref linkend="UserGroups" /> for more information on how to
        define and manage groups of users).</para>

        <para>Each group can be associated with the following access
        permissions:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

  	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">&hyphen;</emphasis>:
	    this level of permission that displays as a hyphen
	    means that the group has no specific permission.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">access to all
	    artifacts</emphasis>: when granted this permission a user
	    group has access to all the artifacts of the
	    tracker.</para>
	  </listitem>
      
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">access to artifacts assigned
	    to group</emphasis>: when granted this permission a group
	    of users can only see those artifacts that have been
	    assigned to one or several members of this group.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">access to artifacts submitted
	    by group</emphasis>: when granted this permission a group
	    of users can only see those artifacts that have been
	    submitted by one or several members of this group.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">access to artifacts assigned
	    to or submitted by group</emphasis>: when granted this
	    permission a group of users can only see those artifacts
	    that have been submitted by or assigned to one or several
	    members of this group.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
<!--
      <para>
        <tip>
          <title>Example: Using tracker access permissions with your clients</title>
    <figure id="TrackerV5PermissionsExample">
      <title>A sample tracker permissions screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerpermissions.png" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

	  <para>As an example of how you can use these permissions
	  let's assume that you have created a tracker where several
	  of your customers can report defects on your software. In
	  such a situation, you may decide that a customer from a
	  given company should only see those defects that were
	  submitted by its employees and not those submitted by other
	  companies.</para>

	  <para>To achieve this you just need to create a group called
	  'company_A' in which you include the login names of all the
	  users working for company A. Then do the same with the group
	  'company_B' for company B. Those two groups will then be
	  given the 'access to artifacts submitted by group' type of
	  permission. In addition you probably want to grant 'access
	  to all artifacts' to the project members or to the
	  'tracker_administrators' groups so that your team members can
	  manage artifacts from any customer.</para>

          <para>In this example:</para>
          <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
            <listitem><simpara>a user which is not logged-in will not have access to artifacts,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a user which is logged-in will not have access to artifacts,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a project member will have access to all artifacts,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a project admin will have access to all artifacts, since a project admin is a project member,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a tracker admin will have access to all artifacts, since a tracker admin is a project member,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a member of ugroup Company_A will only have access to artifacts submitted by members of the ugroup Company_A (the same for Company_B),</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a project member which is also member of ugroup Company_A will have access to all artifacts since he is a project member,</simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>a member of ugroup Company_C will not have access to artifacts (if he is not also member of a ugroup like project_member, Company_A or Company_B).</simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

	  </tip>
        </para>
        -->
      </section>

      <section id="TrackerV5FieldPermissionsManagement">
        <title>Field Permissions Management</title>

        <para>Beside defining access permissions for the tracker and
        its artifacts (see <xref
        linkend="TrackerV5AndArtifactPermissionsManagement"/>) it is
        sometimes necessary to restrict access to certain fields of
        the tracker to a given population. As an example if you share
        a defect tracking system with your customers you may want to
        hide some fields from the view of your customer or prevent
        them from modifying certain fields. This is precisely what
        this module is meant for.</para>

        
        <para>When using this configuration module, you can toggle the
        display between two different views: you can either view all
        user groups permissions for a given field OR for a given user
        group you can view all the field permissions defined for
        it. The experience shows that the view by field is often the
        preferred one when you configure a tracker for the first time
        whereas the view by group of users is more convenient to
        adjust the permission settings later on (see <xref
        linkend="UserGroups" /> for more information on how to define
        and manage groups of users).</para>

        <para>Each group of users can be granted the following
        permissions for a given field:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

  	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Can submit</emphasis>: this
	    permission determines whether a group of users can define
	    the initial value of a field when an artifact is first
	    submitted. If not checked, this field will not be visible
	    on the submission screen for this user group.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Read-only</emphasis>: if
	    granted read-only permission a group of users only has
	    read access to a field. In other words the users see the
	    value of the field but cannot modify it.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>: if granted
	    update permission, a group of users can see the current
	    value of a field and also modify it.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">-</emphasis>: this level of permission that displays as a hyphen
	    means that the group has no specific permission, like in tracker permissions.</para>
	  </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Important Note</emphasis>: the
        permissions associated with a field apply in many areas of a
        tracker. For instance if a group of users has no access to a
        given field, this field becomes invisible on the initial
        submission form, on the artifact search form as well as in the
        table of results returned by the search, in the artifact
        update form, in the history of changes associated with each
        artifact and finally in the email notification sent to this
        group of users.</para>

      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5FieldUsageManagement">
      <title>Field Usage Management</title>

      <para>When a tracker is first created, it comes pre-configured
      with a set of fields inherited form the template that was used
      to create it. For the majority of projects hosted on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; it is
      very likely that the standard Tracker templates (e.g Bugs,
      Tasks, User strories) will cover most of the needs.</para>

      <para> However &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; gives you the ability to customize your trackers. 
      It can be a variation on an
      existing template with some fields or structural elements addition or removal or it can
      be an entirely new tracker created from an empty
      template.</para>
      
      <para>The Field Usage Manager is divided in two parts : a fields palette 
      on the left and a tracker visualization on the right (see 
      <xref linkend="TrackerV5AdminFieldUsageOverview" />)</para>
      
      <figure id="TrackerV5AdminFieldUsageOverview">
       <title>Tracker Admin Field Usage Overview</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_tracker_admin_field_usage_overview.png" />
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <section id="TrackerV5FieldTypes" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
        <title>Tracker Fields Palette</title>
        <para>The palette allows the user to choose the elements he wants
        to add to his tracker. The field usage manager palette consists of 4 groups: </para>
        <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Fields</emphasis>: 
                    These are regular fields (int, float, list, etc.) that the user
                    will be able to update. These fields have no special behaviour.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Dynamic Fields</emphasis>:
                    These fields have a special behaviour. Their value cannot be
                    updated by the user. The value is determined dynamically 
                    (e.g. the user that submitted the artifact, the Id of the 
                    artifact, the artifact submission date, etc.).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Structural Elements</emphasis>:
                    These elements are not real fields. There are really useful 
                    to enhance the artifact presentation. They can be containers 
                    (fieldset, columns) or decorative elements (line break, text).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Unused Fields</emphasis>:
                    In this section, you will find all the fields that are not 
                    used in the tracker definition. If you remove a used field 
                    from your tracker definition, it won't be deleted but placed 
                    in this unused field section. It will then be easier to use it
                    again. If you really want to delete it, delete it from the 
                    unused field section.
                    Unused fields are also used in tracker template definition.
                    You can find here some fields that the team didn't decide to 
                    introduce in the template but that makes sense however. It is 
                    easy then to add such a field whereas creating from scratch.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5FieldFields" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
        <title>Fields</title>
        <para>Find below a detailed description of each type:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">String</emphasis>: allows the user
            to enter free text in a one-line text field. The summary of a
	        defect or a task is a good example of a one-line text field.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Text</emphasis>: allows 
            the user to enter free text in a multi-line text
	        area. The field &#34;Original Submission&#34; that is used to describe in
	        details a defect, a task, etc. is of type &#34;Text&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Select Box</emphasis>: a
	        &#34;Select Box&#34; field takes its value from a predefined list
	        of values defined by the tracker administrator. The predefined values 
	        can either be a static list of values or a dynamic list (of users for instance).
	        Depending on the browser you use it may be displayed slightly
	        differently but it is generally shown as a pull-down menu
	        with the list of predefined values. At any
	        given time this type of field can only be assigned one
	        single value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Multi-Select
	        Box</emphasis>: like the Select Box field described above
	        this field takes its value from a predefined list of
	        values or users. As opposed to the Select Box field, the
	        Multi-Select Box can be given multiple values at once by
	        the end user. As an example, this type of field can be
	        used to assign several persons to a given task in a task
	        tracker.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Date</emphasis>:
            one-line field that only accept ISO formatted dates
            (YYYY-MM-DD). For user convenience, each date field comes with 
            a calendar.</para>
        </listitem>
      	<listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">File upload</emphasis>:
	        this field allows to add any kind of files. Users can add several
	        files in the same file updload field. A typical example of file 
	        upload file is an attachment section of defect or bugs artifacts.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Integer</emphasis>:
	        one-line field that only accept well-formed integral
	        numbers (e.g 3, -100, 2345&hellip;)</para>
        </listitem>	  
        <listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Float</emphasis>:
	        one-line field that only accept well-formed floating point
	        numbers (e.g 3.56, -100.3, 2345, 34E+6&hellip;)</para>
        </listitem>      
      	<listitem>
	        <para><emphasis role="underline">Open List</emphasis>:
	        this field allows to have a list of values, but the values are not 
	        predefined. The list is "open". It means that users can use an 
	        existing value, but can also add a new value. This new value will
	        be part of the existing ones the next time! Moreover, this field 
	        provides autocompletion (typing the beginning of a word, the system
	        suggests values starting with the entered text).
	        This fields accepts multi values.
            </para>
            <para>Like the standard lists, open lists can be linked with static 
            values or with users.
            </para>
            <tip>
             <title>Use open list field to add people in CC</title>
             <para>Former trackers version of &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; contained 
             a section called CC that was used to notify people of artifact 
             updates. This section no more exists, but can be easily replaced 
             by an open list field, linked with users. Don't forget to check 
             the notify option when defining your field!</para>
            </tip>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="underline">Artifact link</emphasis>:
            this field allows to make specific reference or dependance to other 
            artifacts. A typical use for this kind of field is a reference from 
            a task to several sub-tasks. This field is multi valued.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="underline">Permissions on artifact</emphasis>:
            this field allows to define specific permissions on an artifact.
            The artifact submitter can then choose to restrict the access of the
            artifact to a group of users.
            </para>
        </listitem>
	  
	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5FieldDynamicFields" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
        <title>Dynamic Fields</title>
        <para>Find below a detailed description of each type:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
             <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Artifact ID</emphasis>:
                this is the unique identifier of the artifact. It can be
                useful to make reference to the artifact. The artifact Id 
                cannot be updated and is determined by the system. This is a
                read only field.
                </para>
             </listitem>

	         <listitem>
	           <para><emphasis role="underline">Last Update Date</emphasis>:
	           this field is a read only field and cannot be updated by the user.
	           This field is automatically set to the date of the artifact was 
	           updated last time. Each artifact modification will update this field
	           (field update, follow-up comment, etc.). This field can be useful 
	           in a report sorted on this field to follow the activity of the tracker.
	           </para>
	         </listitem>
             
	         <listitem>
	           <para> <emphasis role="underline">Submitted By </emphasis>:
	           this field is a read only field and cannot be updated by the user.
	           This field is automatically set to the user that submitted the 
	           artifact.
	           </para>
	         </listitem>
	         <listitem>
	           <para><emphasis role="underline">Submitted On</emphasis>:
	           this field is a read only field and cannot be updated by the user.
	           This field is automatically set to the date of the artifact was 
	           created.
	           </para>
	         </listitem>
             
	         <listitem>
	           <para><emphasis role="underline">Cross References</emphasis>:
	           this field is automatically updated with existing references from 
	           and/or to this artifact. It displays all references from or to 
	           this artifact, grouped by reference type (artifact, document, wiki, etc.).
	           </para>
	         </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
        
   <section id="TrackerV5FieldStructuralElements" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
        <title>Structural Elements</title>
        <para>Find below a detailed description of each type:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	          <listitem>
	            <para><emphasis role="underline">Fieldset</emphasis>:
	            this structural element allows to group several fields together.
	            Fields are stacked one above the other.
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
              
	          <listitem>
	            <para><emphasis role="underline">Column</emphasis>:
	            this structural element allows to add columns in the artifact form.
	            Columns are aligned one next to the other. You can use columns if
	            you want to put several fields on the same row.
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
              
	          <listitem>
	            <para> <emphasis role="underline">Line Break</emphasis>:
	            this structural element adds an invisible line break in the artifact 
	            form. Use this field to arrange the different elements.
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
              
	          <listitem>
	            <para><emphasis role="underline">Separator</emphasis>:
	            this structural element adds a visible line break in the artifact 
	            form. Use this field to arrange the different elements.
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
              
	          <listitem>
	            <para><emphasis role="underline">Static Text</emphasis>:
	            this element allows to add static text in the artifact form.
	            You can use the rich text editor to add color, formatting, etc.
	            You can use this field to add instructions, ot just for decoration.
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
    </section>
	        
    <section id="TrackerV5FieldUnusedElements" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
        <title>Unused Elements</title>
        <para>Unused fields is not a kind of fields, but all the fields that are not 
            used in the tracker definition. Select one of these fields to use it again.
        </para>
    </section>
    
  </section>


  <section id="TrackerV5CreationandModificationofaTrackerField">
	<title>Creation and Modification of a Tracker Field</title>
    <section id="TrackerV5AddFieldToTracker">
        <title>Add a field to a tracker</title>
        <para>To add a field to a tracker, you just have to choose a field type 
        on the fields palette. Simply click on it, and a property field form will 
        appear instead of the palette!</para>
        <para>Depending on the fields, the properties can change. But, here is the properties
        that can be tuned :</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Label</emphasis>: this
	            is the name of the field. Although you are entirely free
	            to change the name of a field, we recommend that you only
	            change it for a new name with a similar meaning. If you
	            want to change the name for something radically different
	            then we recommend that you create an entirely new field
	            and you leave the existing field in the list of unused
	            fields.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a
                longer description of the purpose of this field.</para>
            </listitem>
             <listitem>
	    <para id="TrackerV5FieldDisplaySize" xreflabel="Field Display
	    Size"><emphasis role="bold">Size</emphasis>: this
	    property allows you to define how much space a field is
	    going to take on the screen. It has a different meaning
	    and a different format depending on the field type.</para>


	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Multi-Select
		  Box</emphasis>: the display size is made of a single
		  number which indicates how many of the values
		  associated with this field are visible at once. A
		  reasonable value for the size of multi-select box is
		  between 2 and 5.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">String, Integer
		Float Fields</emphasis>: "maxchars" and "size" can be filled where "size"
        is the number of character visible at once in
		the field display window and "maxchars" is the maximum number
		of characters that can be typed for this field. If
		"Size" is less than "Maxchars" then the text will shift in the
		visible window as more text is entered. The maximum
		value of "Size" is 255.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Date Field</emphasis>: A date
		always follows the same pattern (YYYY-MM-DD) and
		therefore it always has a fixed length of 10
		characters.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Text </emphasis>: for text areas, "rows"
          and "cols" can be filled, 
		  where "cols" is the number of
		  columns in the text area (the width in number of
		  characters) and "rows" is the number of rows or lines of
		  text. Note that the number of lines is not limited
		  to "rows". If the text typed in the field has more than "rows"
		  lines then a scrollbar will show up to navigate
		  through the text.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank</emphasis>: this
	     is the position of the field on the form. Positions are relatives
	     one against another.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis role="bold">Required</emphasis>: determines whether 
        leaving the field blank in the artifact
	    submission or update form is allowed or not. If checked
	    the tracker won't accept the form unless the field is
	    given a value. The fields that must be filled out are
	    marked with a red start on the submission and modification
	    forms</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis role="bold">Default value</emphasis>: This applies to 
         one-line fields with no restricted set of values. For those the default
         value can be defined. It is the value which will be displayed 
         at the artifact submission.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para><emphasis role="bold">Values</emphasis>: This 
         applies to &#34;Select Box&#34;, &#34;Multi-Select Box&#34; and 
         &#34;Text Box List&#34; type of fields
         where the list of values you are going to choose will show up
         in the pull-down menus when an artifact is submitted or
         updated.</para>
         <para>You can bind those fields to :</para>
         <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Add the values</emphasis>: To configure values 
                simply add values in the text area (one per row). Check "alphabetically sort values"
                will sort automatically your values.
                </para>
                <para>&SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows to add what we call "decorator" to each value but only on edition mode (see <xref
                linkend="TrackerV5ModifyFieldOfTracker" />)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Binding a field to a list of users</emphasis>: 
                the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker offers the ability
	            to associate  &#34;Select Box&#34;, &#34;Multi-Select Box&#34; and 
                &#34;Text Box List&#34; type of fields with a list of predefined values
	            that is actually dynamically generated by the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; system. A
	            typical example of this is when one would like to create a new
	            select box showing the list of project members. Instead of
	            creating and maintaining the list of values manually, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
	            builds this list for you and allows you to bind it to a field
	            of type select box.</para>
                <para>Note that if you decide to bind a select box to a list
                of dynamically generated values you can no longer create your
                own values. The following lists are currently available
                (others may be added in the future):</para>
                
	            <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	              <listitem>
	                <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis> :
	                list of people belonging to the project.</para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Administrators</emphasis> :
	                project members who have been granted the status of
	                project administrators.</para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para><emphasis role="bold">Artifact
	                Submitters</emphasis>: the full list of people who once
	                submitted an artifact to the tracker.</para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Defined User Groups</emphasis>: 
                        you can bind a select box to any of the user groups that
                        are defined by the project. To see how to define such
                        user groups refer to <xref linkend="UserGroups" />.
                        </para>
	              </listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
                
            </listitem>
            
         </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5ModifyFieldOfTracker">
        <title>Modify the field of a tracker</title>
        <section id="TrackerV5EditFieldOfTracker">
            <title>Edit the field of a tracker</title>
            <para>In order to make some change on a field, you can simply edit 
            it by clicking on the Edit icon.</para>
            <para>The edition mode allow fields configuration not available at the creation :</para>
            <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Change the field name</emphasis>:
                  the field name is different from the field label. Field name 
                  is an internal name for the field. It is used in SOAP API for 
                  instance. It must not contain any special characters. Only lower case 
                  letters and "_" are authorized.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Add a decorator</emphasis>:
                 List values can be embellished with a decorator. A decorator 
                 is a colored square. You can choose the color for each value 
                 in a large palette of colors.
                 (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerAdminFieldUsageEdition" />).
                 Decorators can be used to get a quick visual indicator feedback 
                 for the user. For instance, the values for the priority of a bug 
                 can be given a color with the meaning "the darker the more important".
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Add values</emphasis>
                 You can easily add new values to the list by selecting the
                 "add new values" link below existing values.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Hide values</emphasis>
                 You can easily hide existing values by clicking the hide icon next 
                 to the value. If the eye is open, the value is available. 
                 If the eye is medium closed, then the value is hidden. 
                 Just click again to enable the value. Artifact with hidden values 
                 will still be set to the hidden values. But hidden values won't be 
                 proposed anymore for new artifacts.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Remove values</emphasis>
                 You can remove a list value by clicking the cross icon next to the value.
                 It is impossible to delete values if there are some artifacts with this value.
                 In this case, you can hide the value.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Access directly to the field permissions manager</emphasis>
                 Editing a field, you can access the permissions administration of 
                 this field selecting the "edit permission" link.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                 <para><emphasis role="bold">Configure notifications</emphasis>:
                    if the field is a "Select Box", a "Multi Select Box" or a 
                    "Text Box List" bind to a list of users, a checkbox 
                    "Send notifications to selected people" will be displayed. If 
                    checked, all selected users of an artifact will receive a email 
                    if the artifact is modified.
                 </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <figure id="TrackerV5FigureTrackerAdminFieldUsageEdition">
             <title>Tracker Admin Field Edition</title>
             <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
               <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_tracker_admin_field_usage_edition.png" />
              </imageobject>
             </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
        </section>
        <section id="TrackerV5DeleteFieldOfTracker">
            <title>Delete the field of a tracker</title>
            <para>In order to delete a field, simply click on the Delete icon 
            on the visualization tracker page. The field won't be deleted since it will be 
            now present in the "Unused Elements" part of the palette.
            </para>
            <para>
             Please note that you won't be able to remove a field if this field 
             is used in tracker semantic, or in tracker workflow.
            </para>
            <para>
            To delete definitively that field, click on the trash icon in
            the "Unused Elements" part of the palette.</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>

  </section>
      
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5SemanticManagement">
        <title>Semantic </title>
        
        <para>
            As trackers can be fully customized, you may need a way to define 
            what is the title of your artifacts, when you consider an artifact 
            to be open or close, or the field used to define the contributor (or assignee)
            of an artifact. This feature is provided by the admin section 
            "Semantics".
        </para>
        <para>
            Most of the trackers you will use already defined a semantic. 
            This is the case for instance for all tracker templates (see 
            <xref linkend="TrackerV5TrackerTemplates" />).
        </para>
        <para>
            To define or update a semantic field, select the pencil icon next to the
            semantic property. Semantic admin section lets you define the following 
            semantic properties:
        </para>
        
        <section id="TrackerV5SemanticManagementTitle">
            <title>Title</title>
            <para>
                The title of an artifact is a field that sum up the best the artifact.
                For instance, it can be the field <emphasis role="bold">summary</emphasis> 
                for a bug tracker, the field <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis> 
                for a contact tracker, or the field <emphasis role="bold">I want to</emphasis> 
                for a Scrum user story tracker.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can choose any <emphasis role="bold">text field</emphasis> 
                as the title of your artifacts.
            </para>
            <para>
                This semantic information is used in the edition page of an existing artifact, 
                next to the ID. It is also displayed in <emphasis role="bold">My artifacts</emphasis> widget.
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="TrackerV5SemanticManagementStatus">
            <title>Status</title>
            <para>
                The status of an artifact is a field that describes the stage of the artifact.
                If you set a semantic for status, please define the values that mean <emphasis>open</emphasis>
                for this field.
            </para>
            <para>
                The most commom case is a field <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis> 
                with the value <emphasis role="bold">open</emphasis> for open values.
                All other values will be considered as <emphasis role="bold">closed</emphasis>
                values. But you may want to define any other semantic.
                You can choose any <emphasis role="bold">selectbox field</emphasis> 
                (single or multi) as the status of your artifacts.
            </para>
            <para>
                This semantic information is used in <emphasis role="bold">My artifacts</emphasis> 
                widget (this widget displays only <emphasis>open</emphasis> artifacts that belongs to you).
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="TrackerV5SemanticManagementContributor">
            <title>Contributor / Assignee</title>
            <para>
                The contributor of an artifact (or assignee) is a field that is bound to 
                users. The contributor(s) of an artifact are the person(s) who are responsible 
                for the work needed to complete the artifact.
                For instance, it can be the field <emphasis role="bold">assigned_to</emphasis> 
                for a bug tracker, the field <emphasis role="bold">owner</emphasis> 
                for a task tracker.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can choose any <emphasis role="bold">user list field</emphasis> 
                as the contributor of your trackers.
            </para>
            <para>
                This semantic information is used to define specific permissions on a tracker 
                (for instance restrict tracker access to a group of assignee people).
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="TrackerV5SemanticManagementTooltip">
            <title>Tooltip</title>
            <para>
                The tooltip of an artifact is a piece of information that is displayed
                when you hover an artifact reference with your mouse.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can select all the fields you want to compose the artifact tooltip.
            </para>
        </section>
        
    </section>
    
    
    
    <section id="TrackerV5FieldDependenciesManagement">
      <title>Field Dependencies</title>

      <para>Field dependencies allow us to link source field values to target field values. In other words, the values proposed to a final user for a field will depend upon the value selected for another field.</para>
      <para>As an example, if you define a field Operating System(Linux, MacOS X, MS Windows, NetBSD) and a field Version(2.0, 2.1, 2.2, 2.4, 2.6, 3.0, 10.1, 10.2, 10.3, 10.4 (Tiger), NT, 2000, XP), you can define dependencies in the tracker administration interface:</para>

      <orderedlist numerotation="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><para>First, select the source field "Operating System" then the target field "Version".</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>To create dependencies between each "Operating System" values and the corresponding versions, you just have to check the corresponding box in the matrix.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>First, you select a source field.</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldChooseSource">
        <title>Source field selection</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_01.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Once the source field selected (here, "Operating System"), you can select the target field.</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldChooseTarget">
        <title>Target Field Selection</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_02.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Then submit, and a matrix with all values is displayed:</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesMatrix">
        <title>Dependencies Matrix</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_03.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>You can now check the boxes corresponding to the dependencies. In the example, if the source field value is "Linux", the corresponding target values are "2.0", "2.2", "2.4", "2.6".</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesMatrixFilled">
        <title>A Filled Field Dependencies Matrix </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_04.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Once a field dependency has been created, it appeared at the "Choose Source/Target" page as a quick link if you need to edit it. Note that to delete a field dependency, you need to empty the matrix.</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureExistingFieldDependencies">
        <title>Display of existing Field Dependencies</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_05.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Once dependencies are defined, the final user (when submitting/updating an artifact) will see the Version options filtered according to the selection of the Operating System:</para>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesFinalUserLinux">
        <title>Proposed versions for Linux</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_07.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesFinalUserMac">
        <title>Proposed versions for MacOS X</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_08.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesFinalUserWin">
        <title>Proposed versions for MS Windows</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_09.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureFieldDependenciesFinalUserBSD">
        <title>Proposed versions for NetBSD</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfielddependencies_10.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When you define your dependencies, please be aware of the following points:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Only <emphasis>Select Boxes</emphasis> and <emphasis>Multi Select Boxes</emphasis> can have dependencies,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The cyclic dependencies are forbidden (Field 1 => Field 2 => ... => Field 1),</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A field can depend upon only one field,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Javascript must be allowed on the browser to manage dependencies,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a field is not the target of a dependency, then it will propose all its values. On the opposite, it will propose only those which satisfy the dependencies.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5CannedResponses">
      <title>Canned Responses</title>

      <para>One frequently sees project members in
	charge of the artifact classification and dispatch process
	posting the same follow-up comments repeatedly. Typical
	examples of repeated posted comments are: a thank you
	message to the originator, a request for the originator to
	provide commonly missing information like version numbers or
	type of machine used, etc. (see <xref
	  linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerCannedResponses" /></para>

      <para>Rather than repeatedly typing the same follow-up
	comments, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows project members to create a predefined
	set of responses. After these canned responses have been
	defined, posting a follow-up comment is just a matter of
	selecting the appropriate response from the pull down menu in
	the artifact update form.</para>

      <figure id="TrackerV5FigureTrackerCannedResponses">
	<title>Definition of Canned Responses</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackercannedresponses.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerV5Workflow">
        <title>Workflow Manager</title>
        <section id="TrackerV5WorkflowOverview">
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>
             A Workflow can help you control the artifact lifecycle, ensure that 
             your teams follow the rule of your company methodology (CMMi, etc.).
            </para>
            <para>
             Each tracker can have it's own workflow, designed by the tracker administrator.
            </para>
            <para>
             For now, a tracker can have only one workflow defined on one field.
             This field must be a list field (select box).
            </para>
            <para>N.B. Worflow is not taken into account in artifacts mass change</para>
        </section>
        <section id="TrackerV5WorkflowAdd">
            <title>Add a workflow to a tracker</title>
	    <figure id="TrackerV5ManageWorkflowScreen">
	      <title>Default workflow on Bugs template</title>
	      <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata format="PNG"
			     fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_manage_workflow.png" width="15.3cm" />
		</imageobject>
	      </mediaobject>
	    </figure>
             <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">First, select the field</emphasis>:
                    you choose the field on which applies the workflow. 
                    A workflow applies on "Select Box" field type (except if it's bound to users).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Then, define transitions</emphasis>:
                    the states the artifact should take from it's beginning to it's end.</para>
		    <para>By default, no transitions are allowed (it's not possible to change the values of selected field). You authorize a transition by clicking on the bullet that cross "FROM" row and "TO STATE" Column. Arrow icon: the transition can happens, grey bullet: the transition is forbidden.</para>
                    <para>Once you defined all your transition, click on Submit button to save it.</para>
                    <para>For instance, in <xref linkend="TrackerV5ManageWorkflowScreen" />, various transitions have been defined: 
		    on artifact submission, defined by fake state "new artifact", the only value available for the field "Status" will be "New".
                    Then, once Status is "New", possible changes will be "Unconfirmed", "Verified" and "Closed".
                    </para>
                </listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
	     <para>To delete the workflow, simply, click on the red cross near to the field name. Transitions are deleted too.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="TrackerV5WorkflowPostFunctions">
	  <title>Define rules on transitions</title>
	  <figure id="TrackerV5FigureTrackerWorkflowTransitionsPermissions">
	    <title>Define workflow transitions</title>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata format="PNG"
			   fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_manage_workflow_transitions.png" width="15.3cm" />
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <para>For a given transition, you can select the people allowed to perform it and actions exectued after the transition happens (if allowed).</para>
            <section id="TrackerV5WorkflowTransitionsUgroup">
                <title>Groups that may make the transition</title>
                <para>
                 Once the transition is defined, you can refine who can make 
                 the transition. To do this, click the "[details]" link next to the 
                 transition. Then, select the group of users you allow to do the
                 transition (see <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerWorkflowTransitionsPermissions" />).
                </para>
            </section>
	    <section id="TrackerV5WorkflowTransitionsPostActions">
	      <title>Post actions</title>
	      <para>You can define a list of actions after the execution of a transition. As of today, only actions on date fields are available.</para>
	      <para>For instance, you can set a date field to the date of transaction execution. It might be used to set automatically the close date of an artifact (eg. when it's state move from Resolved to Closed).</para>
	    </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5EmailNotificationSettings">
      <title>Email Notification Settings</title>

      <para>As explained earlier in <xref
	  linkend="TrackerV5EmailNotification" /> the Tracker comes
      with a predefined set of rules to keep relevant people aware of
      the artifact life. The default rules can however be complemented
      or tuned in a number of ways:</para>

      <section id="TrackerV5GlobalEmailNotification">
	<title>Global Email Notification</title>

	<para>In addition to the default notification rules, the
	tracker administrators have the ability to specify a list of
	email addresses to which submissions of new
	artifacts (and optionally artifact updates) will be
	systematically sent. To add an email address, click the "add" link.
	You can add as many email addresses as required.
	<!--Note that in this case notifications will
	be sent to users regardless of their personal preferences
	defined (see section &#34;<xref
	linkend="TrackerV5EventRoleBasedEmailNotification" />&#34;
	below).--></para>
    
    <para>You can choose to disable the permission check for global 
    email notification.
    This can be useful if the email address is a mailing list,
    because individual permissions can't be checked for each
    member of the mailing list. So for mailing lists, if the check box
    "check permissions" is checked, the notifications will be send to each 
    member with the permissions of an anonymous user.
    </para>

	<para>This feature is typically used to send submissions of
	new artifacts to a number of well identified persons in the
	team who are in charge of qualifying and dispatching the
	artifacts.</para>

	<para><tip>
	    <title>Tip: Create a Distribution List to notify several people</title>
	    
	    <para>If you want to notify many people at once, we suggest
	  that you use the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Mailing Lists service to create a
	  distribution lists (see <xref linkend="MailingLists"
		/>). Once the Mailing List is up and running type the e-mail
	  address in the Global Email Notification field.</para>

	    <para>Creating a Mailing List on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; has several
	  advantages: first individuals can (un)subscribe by
	  themselves and second all messages sent to a &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; mailing
	  list are kept in an archive that can serve as an audit
	  trail for your tracker.</para>
	  </tip>
        </para>

      </section>

<!--
      <section id="TrackerV5Watchers">
	<title>Tracker Watchers</title>

	<para>The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker offers to all project members the
	ability to be carbon-copied on all email notifications sent to
	some other project members.</para>

	<para>Here are a couple of examples where the tracker watch
	feature can be extremely useful:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Backups</emphasis>: when a
	    team member is away from the office it is often convenient
	    to delegate her artifact management activity to another
	    person in the team who is acting as a backup. Becoming the
	    backup of another team member is as easy as inserting her
	    name in the Watchers field of the backup person when
	    the team member quits and remove it when the team member
	    returns.</para>

	    <para>As soon as you specify a person name in the 
	    watchers field you'll start receiving all the artifact
	    notification of this person and you can act accordingly on her
	    behalf.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">QA Contacts</emphasis>:
	    another possible use is for the QA team members to fill
	    the tracker watcher field with the names of the software
	    engineers whom QA activity they are responsible for.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><para>Remark: The goal of the tracker watch feature is not
	to spy on you. To make sure that you are only watched by
	authorized persons, &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; always shows you the list of &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
	users who are currently watching your email 
	notifications. </para></note>

      </section>
-->
      <!--<section id="TrackerV5EventRoleBasedEmailNotification" xreflabel="Event/Role Based Notification Settings">
	<title>Event/Role Based Notification Settings</title>

	<para>This is the most sophisticated part of the customization
	process. It allows any user to specify what types of events
	they wants to be notified of by email. Note that these settings
	are project and user specific so you can tune your own email
	notification preferences for each tracker you are involved
	with.</para>

	<para>The customization matrix (see <xref
	    linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix" />) presents you with a
	series of check boxes. Each check box allows you to specify
	what kind of events you want to be aware of depending on
	the role you play with respect to the artifact.</para>

	<para>There are 4 roles defined with respect to an artifact:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Submitter</emphasis>: you are
	    the person who initially reported the artifact by filling
	    out the artifact submission form.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Assignee</emphasis>: you were
	    assigned the artifact and you are therefore responsible
	    for managing it.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">CC</emphasis>: you are
	    mentioned in the list of CC names (see <xref
	    linkend="ArtifactCCList" />).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Commenter</emphasis>: you have
	    once posted a follow-up comment in the artifact.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>For each of these roles you can instruct the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;
	Tracker to send email notifications to you only when some
	specific events occur. Nine different events (see the right
	most column on <xref linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix"
	    />) are monitored by the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Tracker. The description of the
	events is self explanatory and only appeal one comment: the
	first 8 events in the list can only occur on artifact
	updates. Only the last event relates to the submission of a
	new artifact.</para>

	<para>Let's review the sample matrix shown on <xref
	    linkend="TrackerV5FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix" /> and see, step by
	step, how this user has configured her notification
	settings:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>First let's look at the Commenter
	  column. The Commenter column says that this user has decided
	  that if she is involved in an artifact as a Commenter (she just
	  posted a follow-up comment at some point in time) then she is
	   only interested in receiving email notification when the
	  status of the artifact goes to &#34;Closed&#34; or when any of the fields
	  Priority, Status and Severity is modified. All other events
	  will be ignored by the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; tracker and no notification
	  will be sent to this user.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Second, looking at the matrix by row, one
	  can see that the user said that when she makes a
	  modification to an artifact herself (Event &#34;I am the
	  author of the change&#34;) she doesn't want to receive any
	  email notification whatever their role in this artifact
	  is. Please note that the event &#34;I am the author of the
	  change&#34; overlaps with other events. So in our example,
	  the submitter will not get a notification when she adds a new
	  artifact. Even if the event &#34;A new artifact has been
	  submitted&#34; is marked</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
            <para>Finally, the user also said that when a new artifact
            is submitted to the project and is immediately assigned to
            her (Assignee role), she wants to be notified. However if
            she is the submitter of the new artifact then she is not
            interested in receiving the notification.</para>

	    <para>Note that the Commenter role is meaningless for the
	    event &#34;A new artifact has been submitted&#34; because
	    follow-up comments can only be added at update time not at
	    creation time. Also, the event &#34;I'm added or removed
	    from this role&#34; is meaningless for the Submitter and
	    the Commenter because these roles can not be modified in
	    an artefact.</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="TrackerV5FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix">
	  <title>Configuration of the Personal Notification Matrix</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackernotificationmatrix.png" width="12.5cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>
      -->

      <!--<section id="TrackerV5ToggleEmailNotification">
	<title>Suspend Email Notification</title>

	<para>Sometimes, it can be convenient to suspend all email
        notifications for one specific tracker, for instance during 
        maintenance tasks. By selecting this option, 
        a tracker administrator disables both global notifications and
        event/role notifications.</para>

	<para>This feature is typically used when doing mass-changes 
        or for testing purposes.</para>

      </section>
      -->

    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5AdminCSVImport">
        <title>Tracker Artifact Import</title>
        <para>
        &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows you to import artifacts in a tracker from 
        a CSV file. See <xref linkend="TrackerV5ArtifactImport" /> for more details about 
        this feature.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerV5AdminStructureExport">
     <title>Tracker Structure Export</title>
     <para>
      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; allows you to export the structure of the trackers into 
      an XML file. The &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; tracker templates are provided under 
      the form of such XML files.
      This feature is also really convenient to copy a tracker from a 
      &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; server to another.
     </para>
     <para>
      To export the structure of your tracker, please go to the admin part of 
      your tracker, and select the Export link.
      This will open a browser window to choose the location of the exported file.
     </para>
     <para>
      <emphasis
	   role="bold">Note</emphasis>: this does not copy the
	   artifacts of the tracker but only the structure 
	   (general settings, fields, values, workflow, 
	   semantic, canned responses and permissions).
     </para>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

