<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
//	Originally written by Laurent Julliard 2003, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
      
<chapter id="TrackerService">
  <title>Tracker Service</title>

  <para>The CodeX Tracker is one of the most powerful and versatile
  services offered to CodeX hosted projects. Originally CodeX was
  provided with individual tracking services that were only able to
  track certain types of predefined artifacts like defects (bugs),
  support requests or tasks. It soon appeared that there was a need
  not only to expand the type of artifacts that one can track in a
  project, but also to be able to instantiate the Tracker service as
  many times as necessary in the context of a single project.</para>

  <para>Beside defects, tasks and support requests, project teams may
  want to track other artifacts such as requirements or action requests.
  This is now possible using the CodeX Tracker. Beside the usual trackers 
  (defects, tasks, support requests) that come standard in the Tracker 
  service, other type of trackers can be created at any time and in 
  unlimited numbers under the same CodeX project. 
  All trackers, including the predefined ones, can be fully customized. </para>

  <section id="CodeXTrackerPrinciples">
    <title>CodeX Tracker Terminology</title>

    <para>Before we explain the features of the tracker service, it's
    worth spending some time on the terminology used in the tracker
    service as well as on some of the features that are shared by all
    trackers.</para>

    <para>As the Tracker Service is meant to track virtually any kind
    of item, the generic term &#34;artifact&#34; will be used throughout this
    document to designate items that are being tracked - be it bug,
    task, support request or other such type.</para>

    <para>Defining a tracker is just a matter of assigning it a name,
    choosing the fields that are going to be used in the tracker,
    and what values will be allowed in those fields.</para>

    <para>In addition to the project definable fields and field values there
    are other fields that are permanently attached to a tracker
    artifact. These are:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

      <listitem>
	<para> <emphasis role="bold">Follow-up
	    comments</emphasis>: all artifacts have the full list of
	    free text comments posted by users attached to it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">File attachment</emphasis>:
	    all artifacts can have any number of files attached to
	    it. File attachments generally contains supplementary
	    information that help better characterize the nature of
	    the artifact.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">CC list</emphasis>: any number
	    of users can be notified of modification to an
	    artifact by including their CodeX user name or email
	    address in the CC list.</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </section>


  <section id="EnteringtheTrackerService">
    <title>Entering the Tracker Service</title>

    <para>To enter the Tracker service of a given project, first go to
    the Project Summary page (see <xref
	linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />) and either click
    the &#34;Trackers&#34; item in the Project Main Menu located in the
    upper part of the page or you can directly choose a tracker from the
    trackers listed in the Public Area of the Project Summary page
    (see <xref linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />).</para>

    <para>You will be presented with a list of trackers available for
    this particular project (see <xref linkend="TrackerWelcomeScreen"
	/>. Select the tracker you are interested in. Entering the
    tracker will give you access to various tracker functions
    depending on the permissions you have with this tracker. You may
    be able to submit new artifacts, update existing ones, search
    and browse the artifact database or configure the tracker.</para>

    <figure id="TrackerWelcomeScreen">
      <title>Tracker Welcome Screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerwelcomescreen.png" width="14.5cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    

  </section>

  <section id="ArtifactSubmission">
    <title>New Artifact Submission</title>

    <para>To submit a new artifact to a given project you must first
    access the appropriate tracker of that project as indicated in the
    section above (see <xref linkend="EnteringtheTrackerService" />.</para>

    <para>When entering a given tracker you are presented with the
    artifact selection and browsing screen (more about this facility
    in <xref linkend="ArtifactBrowsing" />). For now let&#39;s click
    on the &#34;Submit a New Artifact&#34; item (or whatever the artifact
    name is) from the Tracker Menu Bar in the upper part of the welcome
    screen (see <xref linkend="FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen"
	/>).</para>

    <figure id="ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject">
      <title>A sample artifact submission screen (the artifact is of type &#34;bug&#34; here)</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactsubmission.png" width="14.5cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><xref linkend="ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject"
	/> shows a sample submission screen from one of the CodeX hosted
    projects. Because of the CodeX Tracker high level of
    customizability no two submission screens look alike. Depending on
    the project more or less fields may appear on the tracker
    submission form and the name of artifact managed by the tracker
    may change as well.</para>

    <para>In the example provided on <xref
	linkend="ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" /> the
    artifact type is a bug (also know as &#34;defect&#34; in corporate
    language). The user is asked to choose a bug Category, a bug
    Group, a Priority and an Assignee from a series of pull down
    menus. Then comes a one-line description for the bug and a longer
    text entry field where you can fully characterize the bug.</para>

    <para>When submitting a new artifact, make the Summary and the
    detailed description as explicit as possible.  Do not use a
    clueless summary like: &#34;Service X doesn&#39;t work&#34; or
    &#34;Blocking problem in Document Mgr&#34;. Explain the nature of
    the bug. Giving an explicit Summary and Description is immensely
    helpful to the project members in charge of the bug classification
    and characterization. A unique ID is automatically assigned to
    the submitted artifact.</para>

    <para>As explained above, artifact submission forms vary from one
    project to another depending on the fields used by the
    tracker. The submission form can also vary according to the
    citizen class the user belongs to. Depending whether you are a
    project member or an ordinary registered user the artifact fields
    displayed on the screen may differ. As an example, on <xref
	linkend="ArtifactSubmissionScreenFromTheCodeXProject" />, the bug
    submitter using the form is probably a project member because
    giving access to the &#34;Assigned to&#34; field to an ordinary
    registered user doesn&#39;t make much sense. It is very unlikely
    that users external to the project team know enough about the
    project organization to correctly assign the bug. Therefore bug
    fields shown to project members and registered users on the
    submission form can be configured in the Tracker Administration
    module (see <xref linkend="TrackerAdministration" />)</para>

    <para>In any case don&#39;t forget to click on the
    &#34;Submit&#34; button when you are finished !</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: make sure your artifact hasn&#39;t yet been
    submitted</title><para>About to submit a bug or a support request
    to a CodeX Project? Before you do that, make sure that others
    haven&#39;t yet submitted a similar artifact. To do so you can
    either browse the artifact database through the Artifact Selection
    and Browsing facility or you can use the search box in the CodeX
    Main Menu and search by keywords.</para></tip></para>

  </section>

  <section id="ArtifactBrowsing">
    <title>Artifact Browsing</title>

    <para>CodeX provides project members, ordinary registered users
    and even anonymous users with the ability to browse the artifact
    database according to a variable set of criteria.</para>

    <section id="ArtifactSelectionCriteria">
      <title>Selection Criteria</title>

      <para>The upper part of the artifact browsing screen is devoted to the
        selection criteria. <xref
	  linkend="FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" /> shows the
        default set of selection criteria that is available when a new project
        is created. You can select bugs by Category (the module in which the
        bug occurred), Group (nature of the bug like Crash, Documentation
        Typo, ...), Status (e.g. Open, Closed, ...) and Assignee (the person
        in charge of the bug). Other projects may show more, less or different
        selection fields depending on the configuration put in place by the
        project administrators.</para>

      <para>How selection criteria are filled out depend on their
      field type. The Tracker Service currently has 6 different types
      of fields used as search criteria:</para>

      <section id="ArtifactSelectBoxField">
	<title>Select Box Field</title>

	<para>A select box field can take its value in a set of
	predefined values. If you are using the simple search
	interface only one value can be selected at a time. If you
	want to select multiple values at once, use the Advanced Search
	facility.</para>

	<para>There might be 2 specific values in the list of choices:
	&#34;Any&#34; matches any value in the list and &#34;None&#34; matches the
	items where no value has been assigned yet</para>
      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactMultipleSelectBoxField">
	<title>Multiple Select Box Field</title>

	<para>A multiple select box field takes it's value from a set of
	predefined values. While the select box field introduced above
	only allows one to select only a single field value, the
	multiple select box field allows the user to select multiple
	values for the same field. If you are using the simple search
	interface only one value can be selected at a time. If you
	want to select multiple values at once, use the Advanced Search
	facility.</para>

	<para>There might be 2 specific values in the list of choices:
	&#34;Any&#34; matches any value in the list and &#34;None&#34; matches the
	items where no value has been assigned yet</para>
      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactTextField">
	<title>Text Field</title> <para>A Text field can contain any
	kind of text. There are two ways to query a text
	field:</para>


	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">

	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Keyword
	    search</emphasis>: you can type a series of space
	    separated keywords that will ALL be searched for in the
	    text field (including as subtring in
	    words)</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline"></emphasis>Regular
	    expression: You can also specify a <ulink
	    url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	    Extended Regular Expression</ulink> as a matching criteria
	    (mind the surrounding /.../ !)</para>

	    <para>Examples:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para>/^[Aa]ddition/ : matches any text field starting
		with either &#34;addition&#34;or &#34;Addition&#34;</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>/foo|bar|dim/ : matches text fields containing the string &#34;foo&#34;, &#34;bar&#34; or &#34;dim&#34;</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactDateField">
	<title>Date Field</title>

	<para>A date criteria follows the following pattern:
	YYYY-MM-DD where YYYY is the year number, MM is the month
	number and DD is the day number.</para>

	<para>Examples: 1999-03-21 is March 21st, 1999, 2002-12-05 is
	Dec 5th, 2002. </para>

      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactIntegerField">
	<title>Integer Field</title>

	<para>An integer field can take positive or (possibly)
	negative values and has no decimal part.</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1, +2, -100&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an integer field. Here
	are the values you can specify in a integer query field:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Integer</emphasis>: if you type a single integer the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 610)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &gt;= or =&lt; followed by an integer
	    the search will look for integer values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120 , &lt; -30)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the &#34;integer1-integer2&#34; notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. 800 - 900 for integers
	  between 800 and 900, -45 - 12 for integers between -45 and
	  +12)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be used as a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all integer
	  values starting with a &#34;4&#34;, ending with an &#34;8&#34; with any
	  number of digits in between.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactFloatingPointNumberField">
	<title>Floating Point Number Field</title><para>A floating
	point number field can take positive or (possibly) negative
	values, may have a decimal part or use the exponential
	notation for large values.. .</para>

	<para>Examples: 0, 1.23, -2.456, 122.45E+12&hellip;</para>

	<para>There are several ways to query an floating point number
	field. Here are the values you can specify in such a
	field:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Single
	    Number</emphasis>: if you type a single number the field
	    will be matched against this value (e.g. 2.35)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Inequality</emphasis>: if
	    you use &gt;, &lt;, &gt;= or =&lt; followed by a number
	    the search will look for all values which are greater,
	    lesser, greater or equal, lesser or equal to the integer
	    value (e.g. &gt; 120.3 , &lt; -3.3456E-2)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Range</emphasis>:
	  if you use the &#34;number1-number2&#34; notation the search
	  engine will look for all values greater or equal to integer1
	  and lesser or equal to integer2 (e.g. -1.2 - 4.5 for integers greater than or equal to -1.2 and lesser than or equal to 4.5)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">Regular
	  expression</emphasis>: <ulink
	  url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/P/a/Pattern_matching.html">MySQL
	  Extended Regular Expression</ulink> can also be usedas a
	  matching criteria (e.g. /^4.*8$/ will look for all integer
	  values starting with a &#34;4&#34;, ending with an &#34;8&#34; with any
	  number of characters in between including the decimal point.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="TrackerQueries">
      <title>Favorites and Predefined Tracker Queries</title>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: save and re-use your tracker queries</title><para>If
        you often run the same queries against a tracker with the same set of
        selection criteria, it is probably a good idea to save this query for
        later re-use. To do this: select the appropriate tracker report, then
        choose your search criteria, click on the &#34;Browse&#34; button to
        run the query. Finally click on the &#34;Bookmark this Page&#34; item
        in the CodeX Main Menu. A new bookmark will show up in your Personal
        Page. A click on this bookmark will run the exact same query again.</para></tip></para>

      <para>Your favorite queries can be saved via the CodeX
      bookmark mechanism as explained in the Tip box but there are
      also shortcuts in the Tracker Menu Bar for the most common
      queries. They are:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Open Artifacts</emphasis>: display all the
            bugs that are not yet closed for this project.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">My Artifacts</emphasis>: display the bugs
            assigned to you (based on the CodeX account you are currently
            using)</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Also notice that CodeX always keeps track of the last run
      query. Next time you enter the tracker welcome screen, CodeX will
      use the same set of selection criteria in the selection fields
      and display the list of matching artifacts accordingly.</para>

      <section id="TrackerAdvancedSearchMode">
	<title>Advanced Search Mode</title>

	<para>At any time during the search phase, you can toggle the search
          mode from Simple to Advanced and vice-versa (see the Advanced Search
          link). The Advance Search mode allows you to select multiple values
          for each selection criteria. Using this mode you could search for
          both open and suspended bugs assigned to project members A and B.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerSearchResults">
      <title>Tracker Search Results</title> 
      
      <para>Based on your selection of search riteria, CodeX runs a
      query against the tracker database, selects the matching
      artifacts, and displays them right below the selection
      criteria. Columns displayed in the artifact list are entirely
      configurable by the project team (see <xref
	  linkend="TrackerReports" />). Therefore, the artifact browsing
      screen might look completely different from the one shown in
      <xref linkend="FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen" />.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleTrackerBrowsingScreen">
	<title>A sample Tracker browsing screen (the artifact is of type &#34;bug&#34;)</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactbrowsing.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Artifact severity is color coded. Colors associated with
      severity levels may vary from one CodeX site to another and it
      is therefore shown at the bottom of the list of results generated
      by the search.  Finally, results are listed by chunks of N
      artifacts where N is user-definable. If more than N artifacts
      are retrieved from the tracker database you are invited to click
      on the navigation bar to display the next or previous chunk of
      artifacts.</para>

      <para>To access a given artifact from the list of results,
      simply click on the corresponding &#34;Artifact ID&#34;.</para>

      <section id="ArtifactListSorting">
	<title>Artifact List Sorting</title>

	<para>By default, artifacts are sorted by ID which happens to
	be the chronological order in which they have been submitted
	and stored in the CodeX database.</para>

	<para>The list of artifacts can be sorted by any of the
	columns displayed on the screen by clicking on the column
	heading. Clicking twice on the same heading toggles the sort
	order beween ascending to descending.  The currently displayed
        sorting direction is shown by a small up or down arrow next to
	the sort criteria right above the artifact list. One exception
	to this rule is for sorting by Severity. Severity being shown
	as a color code and not as a column per se, there is a special
	link at the bottom of the screen to sort the list of results
	by Severity.</para>

	<para>For more sophisticated sorting you can also activate the
	multi-column sort.  In this mode sort criteria acccumulates as
	you click on column headings.  So you can for instance click
	&#34;Severity&#34; first and &#34;Assigned To&#34; second to see who in the
	team is assigned critical bugs and how many.At any point in
	the multi-column sort process, a click on one of the sort
	criteria displayed in the list (criteria 1 > criteria 2 >
	criteria 3...)  will bring you backward in the sort criteria
	list. Using this feature you can easily test various sorting
	strategies.</para>

	<note><para>Note:Sorting criteria, like selection criteria,
	are also saved into your preferences and the same sorting
	criterion is re-used in subsequent queries.</para></note>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: keep an eye on unassigned
	artifacts</title><para>In most cases when an artifact is submitted by a
	person external to the project team, the assignee is given
	the value &#34;None&#34;. In other words the artifact has been
	submitted but it is awaiting an assignment by the project
	member in charge of the artifact dispatch. Since nobody is in
	charge, the artifact can be completely overlooked by the project
	team. Two solutions can help with this problem: 1) Use a an
	e-mail address where all new submissions are sent (see <xref
		linkend="TrackerReportManagement" />) and/or 2) Assign somebody in
	the team the responsibility to run a query once or twice a
	day to collect the artifacts with Assignee field set to &#34;None&#34;
	and give him/her the responsibility to assign the
	bugs.</para></tip></para>

      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactPrinterFriendlyVersion">
	<title>Printer Friendly Version</title>

	<para>At any point in the process of browsing the tracker database
	you can click on the &#34;Printer Version&#34; link to display
	a simplified and non-decorated artifact list that will print
	nicely. For better readability we strongly advise you to print
	the list of results in landscape format.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="TrackerReports">
	<title>Tracker Reports</title>

	<para>Tracker reports allow for the definition of a specific
	layout of the artifact search and browsing screen where one
	can choose the selection criteria and the columns used in the
	list of matching artifacts. Depending on the project, users
	may enjoy the ability to choose from several tracker reports
	by using the upper pull-down menu of the artifact browsing
	screen. If no project or user specific tracker report has been
	defined, the CodeX &#39;Default&#39; report is the only one
	available.</para>

	<para>Any CodeX user (even those who do not belong to a
	project) can define her own personal tracker. In this case the
	reports will only be visible to this particular user. On the
	contrary, Project Administrators have the ability to define
	project-wide reports that all users will be able to use. See
	<xref linkend="TrackerReportManagement" /> for more details on
	managing tracker reports.</para>
      </section>

    </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ArtifactUpdate">
    <title>Artifact Update</title>

    <para>Selecting an artifact ID from the list results generated by
    a search operation will bring you to a screen all the artifact
    details. If you are a administrator of the project the artifact 
    belongs to or have technician permissions on that tracker 
    (see <xref linkend="UserPermissions" />), the 
    detailed view is made of text fields and menus that you
    can update with new values. On the other hand, if you are an
    anonymous user or a registered user who does not belong to the
    project team, most of the fields will appear as immutable
    text. Non-project members cannot edit any of the artifact
    fields. They can only submit a follow-up comment, add themselves
    in the CC list or attach new files to the artifact.</para>

    <para>All the screen shots used in this section assume that the
    CodeX user is part of the project team. For non-project members
    the screen layout is basically the same but the information shown
    on the screen cannot be changed.</para>

    <para>The Artifact Update screen is divided in several parts:
    <emphasis role="bold">Header, Comments, CC List, Artifact
    Attachments, Dependencies and History.</emphasis></para>

    <section id="ArtifactHeaders">
      <title>Header</title>

      <para>The header zone is where you&#39;ll find all the fields
      associated with an artifact. As shown on <xref
	  linkend="FigureHeaderOfArtifactUpdateScreen" />, many of these
      fields are assigned a set of predefined values (Status,
      Category, Resolution) while some others have a number format
      (Effort) or a free text format (Summary). The set of fields used
      in a given tracker, as well as the related set of predefined values
      can be configured by project members with appropriate
      permissions. (see <xref linkend="TrackerAdministration" /> for more
      details on the Tracker configuration)</para>

      <figure id="FigureHeaderOfArtifactUpdateScreen">
	<title>Header of Tracker Update screen (artifact fields)</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactupdateheader.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactComments">
      <title>Comments</title>

      <para>As many follow-up comments as needed can be attached to
      any given artifact. Follow-up comments are free text fields
      where virtually any kind of information or comment can be typed
      in. The &#34;Original Submission&#34; field filled out by the
      artifact submitter can actually be considered as the first
      follow-up comment in the life of an artifact.</para>

      <para>Follow-up comments have several of interesting capabilities and extensions:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Canned Responses</emphasis>: It
	  is not infrequent to see the project members in charge of
	  the artifact classification and dispatch process to post the
	  same follow-up comments again and again. Typical examples of
	  repeatedly posted comments are: a thank you message to the
	  originator, a request for the originator to provide commonly
	  missing information like version numbers or type of machine
	  used, etc. Rather than typing the same comments all the
	  time, CodeX allows project members to create a predefined
	  set of responses. Each canned response is defined by a name
	  and by the body of the response.</para>

	  <para>Posting a canned response is just a matter of
	  selecting the appropriate response from the pull down menu
	  in the artifact update screen and submitting the
	  changes. Defining a new Canned Response can be done on the
	  fly from the artifact submission form by clicking on the
	  &#34;define a new Canned Response&#34; link.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Comment Types</emphasis>: In
	  order to avoid the exponential growth of new artifact fields
	  to store all sorts of free text information, CodeX offers an
	  interesting mechanism called Comment Types. The project team
	  has the ability to define a list of labels that can be used
	  to characterize the nature of a follow-up comment. This is a
	  very helpful feature to define the nature of the information
	  contained in a follow-up comment and to quickly identify
	  these comments in the long list of follow-up
	  comments. Typical examples of such comment types are: 
	  &#34;Workaround&#34; for a comment where you explain how to
	  work around a bug, &#34;Impacted Files&#34; to give the list
	  of source files impacted by the bug resolution (assuming
	  your artifacts are bugs), &#34;Test case&#34; to document
	  how to test the code in the future to make sure that this
	  case will be tested in the future test suite, etc. Comment
	  types are defined in the Tracker Administration module (see
	  <xref linkend="TrackerAdministration" />)</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Cross-References</emphasis>:
	  While typing a follow-up comment, you can use some special
	  text pattern to refer to other artifacts or CVS commits
	  (check-ins). These pattern while be automatically displayed
	  as hyperlinks when the follow-up comment is displayed on the
	  screen. See <xref linkend="ArtifactCrossReferencing" /> for
	  more details about the cross-referencing mechanism.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>


      <figure id="FigureFollowupCommentsAttachedToAnArtifact">
	<title>Follow-up comments attached to an artifact</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactupdatecomments.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactCCList">
      <title>CC List</title>

      <para>As explained later in this chapter (see <xref
	  linkend="TrackerEmailNotification" />) the CodeX Tracker offers
      a powerful email notification system for those users who, at
      some point, were involved in the life of the artifact whether as
      a submitter, an assignee or as a person who posted a follow-up
      comment (commenter).</para>

      <para>Sometimes it is however helpful to involve other people in
      the email notification process even if they did not play an
      explicit role in the life of the artifact so far. For instance,
      you may want a QA contact or the originator of the artifact when
      different from the submitter to receive a carbon-copy (CC) of
      the email notifications. This is precisely what the CC List is
      intended for. Inserting CC names in the CC list will allow these
      people to receive updates notifications for this specific
      artifact.</para>

      <section id="ArtifactCCNames">
        <title>CC Names</title>

        <para>The CC names can be either email addresses or a
        CodeX login name if the user has a CodeX account.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX login name</emphasis>:
            when the person you want involve in the notification
            process has a CodeX account use it in place of her email
            address. Using the CodeX login name give to the recipient
            the ability to customize the kind of update events they
            want to receive. For more information on how to customize
            notification preferences for a given project see <xref
		linkend="TrackerEmailNotificationSettings" />.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Email Address</emphasis>:
            there is no restriction on the type of email address you
            can type. It can be either individuals or mailing list - see
            <xref linkend="MailingLists" />. Unlike CC names entered
            as login names, CC names added in the form of email
            addresses have no customization capabilities and 
            receive all bug updates.</para>
          </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="ArtifactAddingDeletingCCNames">
        <title>Adding and Deleting CC Names</title>

        <para>Several CC names can be added at once by separating them
        with commas or semi-column in the &#34;Add CC&#34; field. Using the
        comment field, one can also explain why these CC names were
        added and/or who they are.</para>

        <para>CC names addition and deletion is subject to a number of
        permission rules:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>Adding a CC name: Anonymous users cannot add CC
            names. Any other CodeX user who is logged in can add CC
            names and the CC list will clearly show who added this
            entry and when.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Deleting a CC name: users with Tracker Administrator
            permissions on a given project (see <xref
		linkend="UserPermissions" />) can delete any entry in the
            CC list for any bug of this project. All other users can
            delete CC entries that were either added by themselves or
            entries where the CC name matches their own name or email
            address in any CodeX projects. In other words a CodeX user
            has the right to undo what they have done or remove themself
            from a CC list in any project. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactAttachments">
      <title>Artifact Attachments</title>

      <para>In addition to comments, the CodeX Tracker 
      allows you to attach virtually any piece of information to an artifact
      in the form of a file. Typical examples of artifact attachments are
      application screen shots in PNG, GIF, JPEG or whatever image
      format is appropriate; it can also be core dumps, a binary image
      of program that crashed or even a simple text file showing a
      stack trace or an error message.</para>

      <para>Artifact attachments can be of any type (image, video,
      sound, text, binary&hellip;) and a comment field can be
      optionally used to annotate the attachment. The maximum size of
      a file attachment is site dependent. The default is 2
      MByte.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactDependencies">
      <title>Artifact Dependencies</title>

      <para>The next section on the artifact update screen deals with
      artifact dependencies (see <xref
	  linkend="FigureArtifactDependencies" />). CodeX users have the
      ability to establish a dependency link from an artifact to one
      or several other artifacts belonging to any of the tracker of
      any CodeX project. This is made possible by the fact that
      artifacts have a unique ID across the entire CodeX
      system.</para>

      <para>The CodeX system does not impose any semantic on the
      nature of these dependency links. As a project team, you are
      free to agree on a specific meaning for these links. However, in
      order to guide the CodeX users, a number of ways in which these
      dependencies are commonly used are listed below: </para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>Assuming your artifact is a bug, when a bug is closed
	  with Resolution field set to &#34;Duplicate&#34; then a
	  bug-to-bug dependency for this bug means the bugs it depends
	  on is considered as the &#34;master&#34; bug by the project
	  members. All other bug submissions that are actually a
	  duplicate of this master will be made dependent on the
	  master bug (probably the first one that was
	  submitted)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>For all other value of the Resolution field a
	  bug-to-bug dependency link could mean that this particular
	  bug cannot be resolved as long as the bug it depends on is
	  not resolved itself.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>A dependency between a artifact of type bug and an
	  artifact of type task generally means that a task has been
	  created to cover or encompass the work required to resolve
	  the bug.  Creating a task to fix a bug generally happens
	  when the bug fix implies a major rework or because the work
	  that is being done in the related task will resolve the bug
	  as a side effect.</para>

	  <figure id="FigureArtifactDependencies">
	    <title>Artifact Dependencies</title>

	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata format="PNG"
		  fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactupdatedependencies.png" width="15.3cm" />
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To create an artifact dependency, type one or
      several artifact IDs (comma separated) and submit the form. The
      cross-referenced artifacts appear in a table right below the
      input field showing their description as well as the tracker and
      the project they belong to.</para>

      <para>To delete an artifact dependency simply click on the
      wastebasket icon to the right of the artifact description line
      and confirm or cancel when asked by the dialog box.</para>

      <para>The dependency section shows the artifact dependencies in
      both ways (cross-reference): it shows the list of artifact(s)
      the displayed artifact depends on but also the list of artifacts
      that depend upon the one you are browsing.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactCrossReferencing">
      <title>Artifact Cross-Referencing</title>

      <para>In addition to the rather formal way of expressing a
      depency between two artifacts presented in
      <xref linkend="ArtifactDependencies"/>, CodeX offers the ability to
      cross-reference any artifact from within a follow-up
      comment.</para>

      <para>When typing a follow-up comment, any text that follows the
      pattern &#34;XXX #NNN&#34; will be interpreted as a reference to the
      artifact XXX number NNN, where NNN is the unique artifact ID, and XXX is the 
      tracker short name (e.g. &#34;bug #123&#34;, &#34;task #321&#34;,
      &#34;req #12&#34;, etc.).
      If you don't know the tracker short name or don't want to specify it, you
      may simply use  &#34;art #NNN&#34;.
      Each time CodeX displays a piece of text that follows this pattern it will
      automagically create an hyperlink to the web page showing all
      the details of the artifact.</para>

      <para>A follow-up comment can contain a reference to an artifact
      of any nature and from any project. It is <emphasis
      role="bold">not</emphasis> limited in scope to the artifact
      belonging to the same tracker or the same project. This is made
      possible because an artifact has a unique ID across the entire
      CodeX site.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Important Notes</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can also use the pattern &#34;commit #NNN&#34; in a
	  follow-up comment to refer to the commit with ID number NNN
	  as listed in your CVS tracking database. This is very
	  useful for instance when you want to close a defect or a
	  task artifact with a reference to the corresponding source
	  code modifications. Conversely your commit message can also
	  contain a reference to the originating artifact therefore
	  ensuring a two directional cross-reference between source
	  code modifications and the related artifact. For more
	  details about the CVS tracking database see <xref
	      linkend="CVSWebInterface"/>.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>If the referenced artifact belongs to another project, or if
          the artifact name (&#34;XXX&#34; above) does not match the short name
          of the tracker it belongs to, a message will be diplayed on top of the
          target page to warn the user that she was redirected to another project,
          or that she should check the tracker name.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>If a project uses one of the legacy bug tracking
	  system, task manager or support request manager, it is also
	  possible to refer to one of those by using the patterns &#34;bug
	  #NNN&#34;, &#34;task #NNN&#34; or &#34;sr #NNN&#34;. If there is a
          tracker with the same short name (e.g. a &#34;bug&#34; tracker), the
          system should be smart enough to link to the right page.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="ArtifactHistory">
      <title>Artifact History</title>

      <para>The last part of the artifact update screen is devoted to
      the artifact history (see <xref linkend="FigureArtifactHistory"
	  />). The artifact history keeps track of all the changes that
      occurred on all artifact fields since the creation of the
      artifact.</para>

      <para>The artifact history shows what fields changed, what the old value 
      was before the change took place, who changed it and
      when. Since the artifact history only shows the old value of a 
      field it requires a bit of work to determine what the new
      value was right after the change took place.</para>

      <para>Let&#39;s take an example: <xref
	  linkend="FigureArtifactHistory" /> shows the history of a sample
      artifact. Let's assume that the current value of the Severity
      field of this artifact is currently &#34;9-Critical&#34;. You
      won't see this value in the change history because this is the
      current value of the Severity field and it is therefore only
      visible in the artifact form. What the sample change history
      tells us when you start reading it from the top is that the
      Severity field was modified on Oct 10th, 2003 at 11:01am by user
      &#34;ljulliar&#34; and the previous Severity level was
      &#34;5-Major&#34;. As there is no other Severity item in the
      history list you can safely assume that &#34;5-Major&#34; was
      the Severity value assigned to the artifact when it was first
      created.</para>

      <figure id="FigureArtifactHistory">
	<title>Artifact History</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifacthistory.png" width="13.5cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>



  <section id="ArtifactMassChange">
    <title>Artifact Mass Change</title>
  
    <para>CodeX provides project administrators with the possibility to
    update several artificats in one step: delete/add the same CC 
    name entry or file attachment to a set of artifacts, assign a list of 
    artifacts to a person, etc... A typical application of the 
    mass update feature is when a person leaves a project and all the 
    artifacts that are assigned to her have to be reaffected to another 
    person.</para>

      <section id="MassChangeSelectionCriteria">
        <title>Selection Criteria</title>

        <para>The artifacts to be updated can be selected according
        to a set of criteria. These criteria are the same as for artifact
        browsing. For fine-grained control you may also select individually 
        all artifacts concerned by the mass change. Please see the
        <xref linkend="AccessingAProjectSummaryPage" />
        for more detail on how to fill out the selection criteria.</para>
	<para>In the sample screen in <xref linkend="MassChangeSelection" /> 
	hitting the left button "Mass Change Selected Items" will select
	the three items checked individually, hitting the right button
	"Mass Change All Items" will select all nine items corresponding to
	the selection criteria. </para>

        <figure id="MassChangeSelection">
    <title>Artifact Selection screen for the artifact mass
change</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_masschangeselection.png"
width="14.5cm" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="Update">
        <title>Update</title>
    
        <para>Once you have selected all the artifacts to be updated you can
        now proceed to affect these changes via the Update screen. The Update 
        screen for the Mass Change is very similar to the normal Artifact 
        Update screen. It is divided into the following parts: Header, Comments, 
        CC List, Artifact Attachments, and Dependencies.</para>

	<figure id="MassChangeUpdateHeader">
    <title>Header of Artifact Update screen for the artifact mass change</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_masschangeupdate_header.png"
width="14.5cm" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
        </figure>


        <para>In the Header zone you find all the fields associated to the
        artifact. Only those that are changed from Unchanged to a defined
        value will be taken into account for the update. In our example in
	<xref linkend="MassChangeUpdateHeader" /> only the "Assigned to" field
	of the three artifacts will be updated to a new value. All other
        fields remain unchanged. </para>

	<figure id="MassChangeUpdateCC">
    <title>CC list of Artifact Update screen for the artifact mass change</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_masschangeupdate_cc.png"
width="14.5cm" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The CC List zone differs from the normal Artifact CC List zone
        in that it contains all the CC names of the selected artifacts
        with the information of in how many artifacts a CC name is used. If
	you add a CC Name it will be added to all the three artifacts. In our
	example in <xref linkend="MassChangeUpdateCC" />, there is one CC 
	Name used in one of the three selected artifacts.
	By checking the "Delete?" box, the given CC Name will be deleted from 
	this artifact.</para>

        <para>Equally, the Attachment zone contains any files attached
        to the selected artifacts with the information as to how many of those
        artifacts each file is attached to. The Dependencies zone is 
        structured in the same manner.</para>

	<para>Each mass change is tracked in the project history 
	(<xref linkend="ProjectHistory" />). On the other
	hand, no e-mail notification is sent in response to the mass change.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  

  <section id="TrackerEmailNotification">
    <title>E-mail Notification</title>

    <para>The CodeX Tracker is equipped with a powerful and flexible
    e-mail notification system. Unless otherwise instructed by the
    project administrators or the users themselves, the e-mail
    notification system follows simple default rules. Whenever an
    artifact is created or updated - whether with an additional
    follow-up comment, a new attachment or a change in any of the
    artifact fields - an e-mail message is sent to the following
    actors:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
	<para>The artifact submitter (the person who initially submitted the artifact)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The artifact assignee (the project member to whom the artifact is
          currently assigned)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>The people on the CC list if any (the persons who are
	listed in the CC list of a given artifact)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>All users who posted at least one follow-up comment to
	the artifact.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Beside these simple rules, the Administration module of the
    CodeX Tracker allows CodeX users to customize the email notification
    process. For further information see <xref
	linkend="TrackerEmailNotificationSettings" />). </para>

    <para>The e-mail message generated by the CodeX Tracker first
    shows the most recent changes that occurred on the artifact in
    case of an update. It is then followed by a complete snapshot of
    the artifact. Web pointers are also included in the message to
    quickly and easily access the artifact form on CodeX.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="TrackerReporting">
    <title>Tracker Reporting</title>

    <para>As explained earlier in this document (<xref
	linkend="ProjectDataExport" />), CodeX can export your project data
      outside of the CodeX system for re-use in another tool or document.
      However for simple statistics, you can also use the Tracker Reporting
      module. This function can be accessed from the Tracker Menu Bar via the item
      &#34;Reporting&#34;.</para>

    <figure id="FigureValueDistributionOfTheCategoryFieldForTheCodeXProject">
      <title>Sample value distribution of the Category field for the CodeX
        project</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_artifactreporting.png" width="13cm"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Tracker Reporting mechanism allows you to see how your
    artifacts (open only or all of them) are distributed across the
    set of predefined values used in the various fields of type
    select-box. For instance you might want to see how your artifacts
    are distributed across the status, category or resolution values
    (see <xref
	linkend="FigureValueDistributionOfTheCategoryFieldForTheCodeXProject"
	/> for an example of how the bug artifacts of the CodeX project
    are distributed across the various CodeX modules stored in the
    Category field).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ArtifactImport">
    <title>Tracker Artifact Import</title>

      <para>Project Administrators have the means to import
    artifacts into CodeX trackers using the well known
    CSV (Comma Separated Value) format supported by all
    of the major office productivity suites. The artifact
    import functionality greatly facilitates the migration
    and integration of external project tracking and management
    tools into CodeX trackers. </para>

    <para>The import is divided into three steps:

    	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    	<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CSV file submission. </emphasis>
      	The project administrators can access the Import
      	functionality from the tracker browsing screens or 
	over the Project Administration Menu. Enter/choose 
	the tracker to update and specify the CSV file to 
	import.</para>
    	</listitem>
   
    	<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CSV file parsing. </emphasis>
      	If no parse errors were found in the uploaded file, 
      	a parse report is shown to validate that the information 
      	to import is correct.</para>
    	</listitem>
   
    	<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Database update. </emphasis>
      	Depending on the parsed information
      	new artifacts are created or existing ones updated.
      	</para></listitem>
    	</itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>When to use the Import</title>
	<para>You will find below a couple of suggestions regarding
	  the use of the tracker import feature:

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>Initial import from a project management software
	  to your CodeX task tracker.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Migration of your legacy defect tracking system
	  into your new CodeX defect tracker.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Migration of artifacts from one CodeX tracker
	  to another.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
    </section>

    <section>
	<title>Exporting Excel Sheets in CSV Format</title>
	  <para>To export an Excel sheet to CSV format, simply follow the steps below:
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem><para>Select <literal>File -> Save As</literal>
		</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>In the dialog window choose 
		<literal>CSV</literal> as the <literal>Save 
		as type</literal></para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CSV File Parsing</title>
	<para>The CSV format that is accepted as import input 
	is accessible over the CSV file submission screen. 
	This page allows manual validation of the tracker 
	field labels, indicating which fields are mandatory in
      	case of a new artifact submission. In addition, it gives
      	you a sample CSV file. If you already use the Tracker
      	Artifact Export (see <xref linkend="ProjectDataExport" />)
      	you will notice that the format of the files to import
      	and the exported files are exactly the same. You can
      	refer to the export format especially
      	for the date formats as well as the format of the
      	follow-up comments (see <xref linkend="ArtifactComments" />).
      	The first record in the CSV import file is always the 
      	header row containing all the tracker field labels that 
      	will be used in the following artifact records.</para>

    	<para>Depending on whether you want to import new artifacts
      	or update the ones that already exist in the tracker you
      	need to provide different information. Nevertheless,
      	you can mix in one CSV file the submission of new artifacts
      	and the update of existing ones.</para>
     
    	<para>For the artifact creation you need to provide
      	information on all fields that are specified
      	as mandatory in the CSV import format. You may omit
      	the submitter and submission date. The artifact
      	submitter is then automatically set to the
      	user importing the CSV file and the submission date
      	will be the date of the import.</para>

    	<para>For the artifact update you need to provide the
      	artifact identifier of the artifacts to update. Beside
      	this, you only need to provide the fields you want
      	to update. </para>

    	<para>The parsing method checks several potential errors 
	in the CSV file:
 	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem><para>Omission of mandatory fields when submitting
	new artifacts </para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Not the same number of columns in the header 
	row and a artifact row</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Unknown tracker field label</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Field values that do not correspond to the 
	predefined field values of a (multi) select box field
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Double submission (i.e. submission of a new 
	artifact with exactly the same summary as an existing
	artifact)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Unkown artifact identifier</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	All other potential errors have to be checked manually
	by looking at the parse report table.
	</para>
    </section>

    <section>
	<title>The Database Update</title>

	<para>If you import new artifacts, all 
	non-mandatory fields that are omitted in the CSV 
	file will be initialized to their default value.</para>
	
	<para>If you want to update the CC list or
      	dependencies list of an existing artifact, be aware 
	that the import will delete all former CC names or 
	dependencies of the artifact and put the CC names 
	or dependencies from the import file instead.
	All follow-up comments in the import file are simply
	added. There is no verification if the same follow-up
	comment already exists.
	The submitter and submission date of an existing
	artifact is never changed by an import even if the
	import file contains relevant information.</para>

	<para>If an error occurs for some artifact during 
	the database update the following artifacts in the CSV
	file are not imported any more.</para>

	<para>Each import is tracked in the project history 
	(<xref linkend="ProjectHistory" />). On the other
	hand, no e-mail notification is sent in response to 
	the import.</para>
    </section>

  </section>
      

  <section id="TrackerAccessPermissions">
    <title>Tracker Access Permissions</title>

    <para>Depending on the class of citizen a user belongs to and
      the level of permissions granted as a project member, the
      various features of the CodeX Tracker may or may not be
      accessible. Access permissions are summarized in the table
      below:</para>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>Tracker Access Permissions</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
	<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="200pt" />

	<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="250pt"  />

	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Tracker Feature</entry>
	    <entry>Access Permission</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>

	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="ArtifactSubmission">New Artifact
	      Submission</link></entry> <entry>By default any CodeX
	      visitor, whether logged in or not, has the ability to
	      submit a new artifact to a tracker. The project
	      administrator has the ability to limit the scope of this
	      feature to CodeX registered users (anonymous users are
	      requested to login first) or to the project members if
	      the tracker is made private.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="ArtifactBrowsing">Artifact
	      Browsing</link></entry> <entry>Searching the Artifact
	      database and browsing the results is available to all
	      CodeX visitors (whether registered or not) unless the
	      tracker has been made private by the project
	      administrator. If so the tracker is only visible to
	      project members.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="ArtifactUpdate">Artifact
	      Update</link></entry> <entry>Same as New Artifact
	      Submission (see above).</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="ArtifactMassChange">Mass Update of Artifacts
	      </link></entry> <entry>Only available to project
	      administrators and project members with Admin. and 
              Tech. permission on this tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="ArtifactImport">Tracker Artifact
	      Import</link></entry> <entry>Only available to project
	      administrators and project members with Admin. and 
              Tech. permission on this tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerFieldUsageManagement">Tracker
	      Creation</link></entry> <entry>Only available to project
	      administrators.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerFieldUsageManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - General Settings</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerFieldUsageManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Field Usage Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerFieldValuesManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Field Values Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only available to project administrators and
	      project members with Admin. permission on this
	      tracker.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link linkend="TrackerReportManagement">Tracker
	      Administration - Reports Management</link></entry>
	    <entry>Only Project administrators can define project
	        wide tracker reports that will be available to
	        all users. All other CodeX users (except anonymous
	        users) can define personal tracker reports.</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry><link
	      linkend="TrackerEmailNotificationSettings">Tracker
	      Administration - Email Notification
	      Settings</link></entry> <entry>Only Project
	      administrators can add email addresses in the global
	      email notification field. Project members must at least
	      have Tech. permission on the Tracker to watch artifacts
	      of other team members. Any registered CodeX user can
	      customize her notification preferences.</entry>
	  </row>

	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>


  <section id="TrackerCreation">
    <title>Tracker Creation</title>

    <para>Before one can define what fields and field values to use
      in a tracker it must first be created. Tracker creation can be
      accessed from the &#34;Create a New Tracker&#34; menu item available in
      the Tracker Administration section.</para>

    <para><tip><title>Tip: Use the predefined trackers
      first!</title> <para>When a new project is created on CodeX a
      number of trackers are automatically created for this
      project. This would typically be a bug tracker, a task tracker
      and a support request tracker. If your project manages this type
      of artifact please use the prefined trackers first. Of course,
      you are free to define new fields or customize existing ones in
      each of the trackers.</para></tip></para>

    <para>To define a new tracker you must provide the following
      information (see <xref linkend="FigureCreateANewTracker"
	/>): </para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem id="TrackerCreationName">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: this is the
	  name of your tracker. A tracker is typically named after the
	  type of artifact it is going to manage. This name will be
	  used by CodeX in the title of the various screens of the
	  trackers. Typical examples of tracker names are: Action
	  Requests, Support Requests, Requirements, Defects,
	  Bugs&hellip;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem id="TrackerCreationDescription">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A longer
	  description of what this tracker is all about and the type
	  of managed artifacts.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem id="TrackerCreationShortName">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Short name</emphasis>: this is a
	  short name that best describe the type of artifact managed
	  in this tracker. This name must be quite short as it is used
	  in various screens of the CodeX Tracker like the artifact
	  update form next to the artifact ID. Following the examples
	  given for the Name field above, short names can be: AR for
	  Action Request, SR for Support Requests, Reqt for
	  Requirements, bug for Bugs&hellip;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure id="FigureCreateANewTracker">
      <title>Creation of a new tracker (here a defect tracking system)</title>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackercreatenewtracker.png" width="13cm"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The next step is to decide upon the set of fields
      available for this tracker. In order to avoid the pain of
      defining the most common type of trackers again and again
      (e.g. Bug tracker, Support Request tracker, etc.) CodeX offers
      the ability to create a new tracker from a set of
      templates. Those templates are either CodeX-wide templates (also
      known as site templates) or project specific templates.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Remark</emphasis>: using a template
      doesn't mean you have to stick to the list of fields and field
      values defined in this template. You can always add or remove
      fields or fine-tune the field settings afterwards.</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem id="TrackerCreationFromCodeXTemplate">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">CodeX-wide Template</emphasis>:
	  these are templates that have been defined by the
	  administrators of the CodeX site because it is expected that
	  most project needs them. It is also a way to ensure a
	  certain level of harmonization across projects that will
	  make developers' life easier. The list of available
	  templates may vary from one CodeX site to another but you
	  will typically find templates for Bugs, Tasks, etc. A
	  specific tracker called &#34;Empty&#34; allows you to create a
	  virgin tracker with no predefined fields other than the
	  minimal set of required fields.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem id="TrackerCreationFromProjectTemplate">
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Project Templates</emphasis>: in
	  case you have already defined a tracker that suits your
	  needs or you have seen a tracker from another project that
	  you'd like to reuse, you just have to specify the project ID
	  and tracker ID either by hand or from the pull down menus
	  and click on the create button to create the exact same
	  tracker in your project (<emphasis
	  role="bold">Note</emphasis>: this does not copy the
	  artifacts of the original tracker but only the field
	  settings).</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>


  <section id="TrackerAdministration">
    <title>Tracker Administration</title>

    <para>As we went through the description of the CodeX Tracker
    features, we referred several times to the flexibility of this
    system and how easy it is to customize your own tracker. This can
    be done through the Tracker Administration module available under
    the &#34;All Trackers Admin&#34; menu item in the Tracker Menu
    bar.</para>

    <para>The top level administration screen shows a list of existing
    trackers for your project. From this page, existing trackers can
    be configured and new ones can be created (see <xref
    linkend="FigureTrackerTopAdminPage" />). This section focuses on
    the configuration of an existing tracker. Creation of new tracker
    is covered in <xref linkend="TrackerCreation" />.</para>

    <figure id="FigureTrackerTopAdminPage">
      <title>Tracker Administration - Top Level Page</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackertopadminpage.png" width="13cm"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The configuration settings for a given tracker is divided
      in six sections:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">General
	Settings</emphasis>: name description, access permission and
	privacy are defined in this section</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Canned
	Responses</emphasis>: allows you to create some pre-defined
	follow-up comments that your team is using on a regular basis.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Field
	Usage</emphasis>: this is where you'll decide what fields to
	use in your tracker.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage Field
	Values</emphasis>: this section allows you to define the lists
	of values to be used by certain fields.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Manage
	Reports</emphasis>: search and browsing templates for the
	artifact search screen are defined here.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Email Notification
	Settings</emphasis>: fine tuning of the global and personal
	email notification settings.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="TrackerGeneralSettings">
      <title>General Configuration Settings</title>

      <para>This module allows you to define a series of properties
      for your tracker. Some of those properties have already been
      defined in the tracker creation form while some others are only
      available on this configuration page. The properties are as
      follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsName">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: this is the
	  name of your tracker. More precisely you want to name your
	  tracker after the type of artifact that are going to be
	  managed in your tracker. This name will be used by CodeX in
	  the title of the various screens of the trackers. Typical
	  example of tracker names are: Action Requests, Support Requests,
	  Requirements, Defects or Bugs&hellip;</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsDescription">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: A longer
	  description of what this tracker is all about and the type
	  of artifact that it manages.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsShortName">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Short name</emphasis>: this is a
	  short name that best describe the type of artifact managed
	  in this tracker. This name must be quite short as it is used
	  in various screens of the CodeX Tracker like the artifact
	  update form next to the artifact ID. Following the examples
	  given for the Name field above, short names can be: AR for
	  Action Request, SR for Support Requests, Reqt for
	  Requirements, bug for Bugs&hellip;</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsPublicTracker">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Public tracker</emphasis>:
	  checking this box (default) will make this tracker
	  public. Public trackers can be viewed by all CodeX users
	  where as Private trackers can only be accessed by project
	  team members. In order to support the information sharing
	  culture promoted by CodeX we strongly advise you to make
	  your trackers public.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsAnonymousSubmission">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Allow anonymous
	  submission</emphasis>: checking this box (default)
	  allows users who are not registered or not logged in to
	  submit a new bug or update an existing bug. If you want to
	  avoid anonymous follow-up comments or unknown artifact
	  submitter you should uncheck this box.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsSubmitInstructions">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Submit instructions</emphasis>:
	  an introductory message that displays at the top of the
	  artifact submission form. This is a convenient way to give
	  directions and recommendations to the submitter. The text
	  must use HTML tags for formatting which gives a great
	  flexibility to shape the content of this preamble (you can
	  use bold, italic, colors, embedded URL&hellip;)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem id="TrackerGeneralSettingsBrowseInstructions">
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Browse
	    instructions</emphasis>: an introductory message that
	    displays at the top of the artifact searching and browsing
	    screen.  The text must use HTML tags for formatting which
	    gives a great flexibility to shape the content of this
	    preamble (you can use bold, italic, colors, embedded
	    URL&hellip;)</para>
	</listitem >
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerCannedResponses">
      <title>Canned Responses</title>

      <para>One frequently sees project members in
	charge of the artifact classification and dispatch process
	posting the same follow-up comments repeatedly. Typical
	examples of repeated posted comments are: a thank you
	message to the originator, a request for the originator to
	provide commonly missing information like version numbers or
	type of machine used, etc. (see <xref
	  linkend="FigureTrackerCannedResponses" /></para>

      <para>Rather than repeatedly typing the same follow-up
	comments, CodeX allows project members to create a predefined
	set of responses. After these canned responses have been
	defined, posting a follow-up comment is just a matter of
	selecting the appropriate response from the pull down menu in
	the artifact update form.</para>

      <para>Also note that defining a new Canned Response can be
	done on the fly from the artifact update form by clicking on
	the &#34;define a new Canned Response&#34; link (see <xref
	  linkend="FigureFollowupCommentsAttachedToAnArtifact"
	  />).</para>

      <figure id="FigureTrackerCannedResponses">
	<title>Definition of Canned Reponses</title>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	      fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackercannedresponses.png" width="15.3cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section id="TrackerFieldUsageManagement">
      <title>Field Usage Management</title>

      <para>When a tracker is first created, it comes pre-configured
      with a set of fields inherited form the template that was used
      to create it. For the majority of projects hosted on CodeX it is
      very likely that the standard Tracker templates (e.g Bugs,
      Tasks, Support Requests) will cover most of the needs.</para>

      <para> However CodeX gives you the ability to customize the list
      of fields for your trackers. It can be a variation on an
      existing template with some field addition or removal or it can
      be an entirely new tracker created from an empty
      template.</para>

      <para>As an example, the Bug Template offers a list of about
	30 predefined fields that you can choose from and customize
	for your own project Bug tracker. Although the list of
	predefined fields is quite rich, there might still be cases
	when one would like to use other fields in their own bug
	tracker. Should this happen, there are two ways to solve the
	problem:</para>

      <procedure>

	<step>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Define your own custom
	    fields</emphasis>: in addition to the list of predefined
	    fields, CodeX gives tracker administrators the ability
	    define new fields. Note that you can also tune predefined
	    fields to suit your needs or even delete them if you want
	    to do some clean-up in the list of fields..</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Ask the Site
	    Administrator</emphasis>: if you think that the missing
	    field is not specific to your project and should be part
	    of a good bug tracking system, then we urge you to contact
	    the CodeX Site Administrators and ask them to create the
	    new field. By doing so CodeX will over time offer a richer
	    and more pertinent set of standard fields.</para>
	</step>	  

      </procedure>
      
      <section id="TrackerFieldTypes" xreflabel="Tracker Field Types">
	<title>Tracker Field Types</title>

	<para>The fields of a tracker can be of several types: Select
	Box, Multi-Select Box, Text Area, Text Field, Integer Field,
	Float Field and Date Field.</para>

	<para>Find below a detailed description of each type:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Select Box</emphasis>: a
	    &#34;Select Box&#34; field takes its value from a predefined list
	    of values defined by the Project Administrator. Depending
	    on the browser you use it may be displayed slightly
	    differently but it is generally shown as a pull-down menu
	    with the list of values that you have defined. At any
	    given time this type of field can only be assigned one
	    single value. An example of such a field is the &#34;Category&#34;
	    field int he bug template.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Multi-Select
	    Box</emphasis>: like the Select Box field described above
	    this field takes its value from a predefined list of
	    values. As opposed to the Select Box field, the
	    Multi-Select Box can be given multiple values at once by
	    the end user. An example of such a field is the &#34;Assigned
	    To&#34; field of the task manager where a task can be assigned
	    to multiple project members at once.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para> <emphasis role="underline">Text Area</emphasis>:
	    allows the user to enter free text in a multi-line text
	    area. The field &#34;Original Submission&#34; that is used to describe in
	    details a defect, a task, etc. is of type &#34;Text
	    Area&#34;.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Text Field</emphasis>:
	    allows the user to enter free text either in a one-line
	    text field or in a multi-line text area. The summary of a
	    defect or a task is a good example of a one-line text
	    field.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Date Field</emphasis>:
	    one-line field that only accept ISO formatted dates
	    (YYYY-MM-DD)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Integer Field</emphasis>:
	    one-line field that only accept well-formed integral
	    numbers (e.g 3, -100, 2345&hellip;)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="underline">Float Field</emphasis>:
	    one-line field that only accept well-formed floating point
	    numbers (e.g 3.56, -100.3, 2345, 34E+6&hellip;)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerFieldList">
	<title>Tracker Field List</title>

	<para>To decide what field to use and what field not to use
	select the item &#34;Manage Field Usage&#34; on the welcome
	page of any Tracker Administration screen. The Field Usage screen
	(<xref linkend="FigureTrackerFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject"
	    />) shows you a sample list of fields available in the tracker
	of a CodeX project. The screen is divided in 3 parts:</para>

	<procedure>
	  <step>
	    <para>the list of tracker fields currently in use by this
	specific project</para>
	  </step>
	  
	  <step>
	    <para>the list of unused tracker fields (not shown on
	      <xref
		linkend="FigureTrackerFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject"
		/>)</para>
	  </step>
	  
	  <step>
	    <para>a form to create new tracker fields (not shown on
	      <xref
		linkend="FigureTrackerFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject"
		/>)</para>
	  </step>
	</procedure>


	<para>Information displayed on the Tracker Field list page are as follows:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>: the
	    name of the field.  To change the propertiers of a field
	    simply click on the field name.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis>:tracker
	      fields can be of several types: Select Box, Multi-Select
	      Box, Text Field, Text Area, Date Field, Integer Field or
	      Float Field. For a detailed description of the field
	      types see <xref linkend="TrackerFieldTypes" /></para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on Screen</emphasis>:
	      the rank number indicates in which order the fields will
	      appear on the artifact submission form and the artifact
	      update form. Fields with a smaller rank number are
	      displayed first.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:</para>
	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Required</emphasis>:
		required fields are always in use. They are often
		fields considered vital for a tracker like Artifact
		ID, Submitter,etc. So you cannot remove them from the
		list of fields in use by your tracker but you can
		however customize them to a certain extent.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Used</emphasis>: the field is used by your project.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Unused</emphasis>:
		the field is not used by your project. Not that an
		unused field is just a &#34;hidden&#34; field. if you change
		the status of a field from used to unused all the data
		associated with this field are preserved.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete?</emphasis>: when a
	    field is deleted, it completely disappears from the list
	    of available fields. Furthermore all the data associated
	    with this field is destroyed from all artifacts.</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>


	<figure id="FigureTrackerFieldUsageScreenOfACodeXHostedProject">
	  <title>Field Usage screen of a project tracker</title>

	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfieldusage.png" width="15.3cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>


      <section id="CreationandModificationofaTrackerField">
	<title>Creation and Modification of a Tracker Field</title>

	<para>The forms used for the creation of a new tracker field
	  or the modification of an existing one being very similar
	  both are covered in the same section.</para>

	<para>The field creation form is available at the bottom of
	  the tracker field list where as the field update form can be
	  accessed by clicking on the field label located on the left
	  hand side of the field list.</para>


	<para><tip><title>Tip: Use Predefined Fields
	First!</title><para>At any time in the life of your project
	you can enrich your trackers with new custom fields. However
	before you decide to create a new field make sure that there
	isn't a predefined field that already plays the same role. By
	using predefined fields whenever possible, you'll contribute
	to keep the global CodeX environment consistent and make it
	easier for visitors, contributors or new team members to
	switch from project to another.</para></tip></para>


	<para>Properties that can be tuned for a tracker field are
	  as follows:</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>: this
	    is the name of the field. Although you are entirely free
	    to change the name of a field, we recommend that you only
	    change it for a new name with a similar meaning. If you
	    want to change the name for something radically different
	    then we recommend that you create an entirely new field
	    and you leave the existing field in the list of unused
	    fields.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a
	    longer description of the purpose of this field.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field
	      Type</emphasis>:tracker fields can be of several types:
	      Select Box, Multi-Select Box, Text Area, Text Field,
	      Integer Field, Float Field and Date Field. For a
	      detailed description of the various field types see
	      <xref linkend="TrackerFieldTypes" /></para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para id="FieldDisplaySize" xreflabel="Field Display
	    Size"><emphasis role="bold">Display Size</emphasis>: this
	    property allows you to define how much space a field is
	    going to take on the screen. It has a different meaning
	    and a different format depending on the field type.</para>


	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Select
		Box</emphasis>: the display size does not
		apply to a select box. Any input typed in the
		display size field will be silently ignored.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Multi-Select
		  Box</emphasis>: the display size is made of a single
		  number which indicates how many of the values
		  associated with this field are visible at once. A
		  reasonable value for the size of multi-select box is
		  between 2 and 5.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Text Field, Integer
		Field, Float Field</emphasis>: for all one-line 
		fields, the display size follows the pattern &#34;V/M&#34;
		where V is the number of character visible at once in
		the field display window and M is the maximum number
		of characters that can be typed for this field. If
		V is less than M then the text will shift in the
		visible window as more text is entered. The maximum
		value of M is 255.</para>

		<para>A display size of &#34;10/40&#34; means a field that
		  accepts 40 characters maximum and the field display
		  is 10 characters in width. </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Date Field</emphasis>: A date
		always follows the same pattern (YYYY-MM-DD) and
		therefore it always has a fixed length of 10
		characters.</para>
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Text
		  Area</emphasis>: for text areas, the display size
		  follows the pattern &#34;C/R&#34; where C is the number of
		  columns in the text area (the width in number of
		  characters) and R is the number of rows or lines of
		  text. Note that the number of lines is not limited
		  to R. If the text typed in the field has more than R
		  lines then a scrollbar will show up to navigate
		  through the text.</para>

		<para>A display size of 60/7 means a text area with
		  7 lines that are 60 characters long.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank on screen</emphasis>:
	    this arbitrary number allows you to define the position of
	    this field on the artifact submission form and the
	    artifact update form relative to other fields. The fields
	    with smaller values will appear first on the screen. The
	    rank values doesn't have to be consecutive values. It is a
	    good idea to use values like 10,20,30,... so that it is
	    easy for you to insert new fields in the future without
	    having to renumber all the fields.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Display this field
	    ...</emphasis>: you can decide if you want to see this
	    field to appear on the bug submission form for project
	    members and non project members. In general non project
	    members are given access to restricted set of fields when
	    they submit a bug. As an example they are not supposed to
	    know how critical a bug is (&#34;Severity&#34; field), how to
	    prioritize it (&#34;Priority&#34; field) (or whom a bug should be
	    assigned to (&#34;Assigned To&#34; field). Therefore these fields
	    should probably not appear on non project members submission
	    form.</para>

	    <para>Finally, some fields have fixed display settings and
	    they always or never appear on the submission form. For
	    instance the &#34;Artifact ID&#34; field never appears on the bug
	    submission form because by definition a bug not yet
	    submitted has no Artifact ID.</para>
	    
	    <figure id="FigureTrackerFieldUsageSettings">
	      <title>Tracker field usage settings</title>
	      
	      <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata format="PNG"
		    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfieldusagesettings.png" width="14cm" />
		</imageobject>
	      </mediaobject>
	    </figure>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Allow Empty Value</emphasis>:
	    determines whether leaving the field blank in the artifact
	    submission or update form is allowed or not. If unchecked
	    the tracker won't accept the form unless the field is
	    given a value.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Keep Change
	    History</emphasis>: determines whether changes made to
	    this field will be kept in the artifact history (see <xref
		linkend="ArtifactHistory" /> )</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Use this field</emphasis>:
	    This checkbox only appears on the field usage modification
	    screen. When first created a field is automatically given
	    the status &#34;Used&#34; (checkbox marked). Fields becoming
	    unused will simply be hidden from the user view but all
	    data attached to this field in the artifact database
	    remains untouched. In other words, returning a field from
	    unused to used will also restore the field data as they
	    were before. Only the actual deletion of a field destroys
	    the field data (see <xref linkend="TrackerFieldList"
	    />. </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerFieldValuesManagement">
      <title>Field Values Management</title>

      <para>Once fields have been defined for your tracker, the next
	step is to define a set of values for your fields. This mostly
	applies to &#34;Select Box&#34; and &#34;Multi-Select Box&#34; type of fields
	where the list of values you are going to choose will show up
	in the pull-down menus when an artifact is submitted or
	updated. Other field types are simply one-line fields with no
	restricted set of values. For those fields only the default
	value can be defined.</para>

      <section id="TrackerFieldValuesFieldList">
	<title>Field List</title>

	<para>To configure values assigned to the used fields of
	  your tracker select the item &#34;Manage Field Values&#34;
	  on the welcome page of the Tracker Administration screen or
	  select the &#34;Manage Field Values&#34; item from the
	  Tracker Administration menu bar at the top of the
	  screen.</para>

	<figure id="FigureTrackerFieldListWithUserDefinableValues">
	  <title>Tracker field list with user definable values</title>

	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfieldvaluesmgt.png" width="13cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>Information displayed on this page are as follows:</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field Label</emphasis>: the
	    name of the field. Click on this name to view the list of
	    values for this field.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: what
	    this field is about</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>


      <section id="TrackerBrowsingTrackerFieldValues">
	<title>Browsing Tracker Field Values</title>

	<para>A click on any of the fields listed in the Field Value
	  Management screen (see <xref
	    linkend="TrackerFieldValuesManagement" />) brings you to the
	  list of existing values for this field (see <xref
	    linkend="FigureListOfValuesForTrackerFieldStatus"
	    />).</para>

	<para>The table of values shows the following information:</para>


	<itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	  <!--
	  <listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis> (optional): the
	  ID column is only shown for fields which have a &#34;System&#34;
	  scope. For this type of field the ID often carry a
	  semantic meaning and if you redefine the label of a value
	  associated with a given ID it is important that you know
	  about the ID.(FIXME - A cause de severity - est-ce qu'on
	  le maintient?)</para>

	  <para>As an example the &#34;Severity&#34; field has 9 possible
	  values and the bugs with the highest ID are always
	  considered as the most critical bug by the system. So it
	  would be a bad idea to redefine the value label for ID 9
	  to something like &#34;Very Minor&#34; :-) but it is ok to
	  redefine it as &#34;Fatal&#34;</para>
	</listitem>
	  -->
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Value Label</emphasis>: text
	    label of the value as shown in the select box. Click on
	    this label to modify the value settings (see <xref
		linkend="TrackerUpdatingaTrackerFieldValue" />)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>:
	    meaning of the value</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank</emphasis>: defines the
	    order of the field values in the select box. The smaller
	    values appear first at the top of the select box.
</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Active</emphasis>:
		the value is currently visible in the pull-down menus
		and can be assigned to the corresponding artifact
		field.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Hidden</emphasis>:
		the value is currently not visible in the pull-down
		menu. However if this value was used in the past by
		any of your project artifacts, it will continue to
		show up OK for this specific bug.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Permanent</emphasis>:
		this value has been defined for the entire CodeX
		system and it cannot be hidden.  It is active for all
		CodeX projects and will remain as is forever.  Well,
		at least until the CodeX Team decides otherwise.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>
	  
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para><xref linkend="FigureListOfValuesForTrackerFieldStatus"
	    /> shows the list of available values for the Status field of
	tracker managing &#34;Bugs&#34; artifacts. The Status field was chosen
	on purpose. Not only is the Status field a required field of
	the &#34;Bugs&#34; template, but it also comes with set of predefined values
	that are available to all CodeX projects. By default only
	&#34;Open&#34; and &#34;Closed&#34; values are active (and
	permanent in this case) but there is a series of 7 other
	values (Accepted, Analyzed, etc.)  that you can choose from if
	you want to have a finer grain Status field.</para>

	<para>Of course you are free to add your own values to the
	Status field. This is actually what has been done for this
	particular project: the Status value &#34;Assigned&#34; as
	been added to the list of active values. However, in order to
	keep a certain harmony from one CodeX project to another, we
	highly recommend that you use the list of predefined status
	values as much as you can before creating new ones.</para>

	<figure id="FigureListOfValuesForTrackerFieldStatus">
	  <title>List of values for the &#34;Status&#34; field</title>
	  
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfieldvalues.png" width="13cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerDefiningaDefaultFieldValue">
	<title>Defining a Default Field Value</title>
	
	<para>All fields used in a tracker can be assigned a default
	  value. Depending on the field type you will be presented
	  with either a free text field for text, date, integer and
	  float fields or a select box containing all the values
	  already defined for this field for select box and
	  multi-select box fields (not shown on <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerFieldListWithUserDefinableValues" />)
	  . </para>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerCreatingaTrackerFieldValue">
	<title>Creating a Tracker Field Value</title>
	
	<para>To add a value use the value creation form located
	  below the list of field values (not shown on <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerFieldListWithUserDefinableValues"
	    />).</para>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerBindingFieldToValueList">
	<title>Binding a Field to a List of Values</title>
	
	<para>Not only does the CodeX Tracker allow you to create a
	list of values for a select box but it also offers the ability
	to associate a select box with a list of predefined values
	that is actually dynamically generated by the CodeX system. A
	typical example of this is when one would like to create a new
	select box showing the list of project members. You could also
	create it manually but such a list would be tedious to create
	and maintain.</para>

	<para>Rather than creating your own set of values you can
	bind a select box to such a list of predefined values that
	CodeX will keep current for you. Note that if you decide to
	bind a select box to a list of dynamically generated values
	you can no longer create your own values. The following lists
	are currently available (others may be added in the
	future):</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis> :
	    list of people belonging to the project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Administrators</emphasis> :
	    project members who have been granted the status of
	    project administrators.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Artifact
	    Technicians</emphasis>: project members who have been
	    granted the permission to process artifacts (see <xref
		linkend="UserPermissions" /> for more information on user
	    permissions).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Artifact
	    Submitters</emphasis>: the full list of people who once
	    submitted an artifact to the project.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Defined User Groups</emphasis>: 
            you can bind a select box to any of the user groups that
            are defined by the project. To see how to define such
            user groups refer to <xref linkend="UserGroups" />.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	   
	</itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerUpdatingaTrackerFieldValue">
	<title>Updating a Tracker Field Value</title>
	
	<para>From the screen showing the list of values for a given
	  field (see <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerFieldListWithUserDefinableValues" />)
	  you can change the properties of a field value:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis>: change the value
            itself. The value typed here will appear as is in the pull-down
            menu.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Rank</emphasis>: a number that allows
            you to specify where you want this value to appear in the list of
            all active values. The values with smaller rank are displayed
            first. When the &#34;None&#34; value is available for this bug
            field it has a rank number of 10. This number is deliberately
            small because by convention &#34;None&#34; always appear at the
            top of the pull-down menu. Please be a good CodeX citizen and
            choose rank numbers higher than 10 for your own values.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Active or Hidden.
            As explained above going from one to the other in the course of
            the project life has no negative impact on the bug database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: says a bit
            more about the meaning of this value.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureUpdatingATrackerFieldValue">
	  <title>Setting a Bug field value</title>
	  
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerfieldvalueupdate.png" width="12cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: Leave some space between rank
	numbers</title><para>Whether for Fields or Field Values
	remember to use large numbers (in the hundreds or the
	thousands like 100, 200, 300,..) when you create new
	values. By doing so you&#39;ll make your life easier if you
	ever want to insert new values in between existing ones in the
	future and avoid a tedious renumbering of the existing
	items.</para></tip></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="TrackerReportManagement">
      <title>Tracker Report Management</title>

      <para>Knowing that project administrators, project members and other
        CodeX users may have different needs in searching the tracker 
        database, CodeX offers the ability to define project or user specific
        tracker reports.</para>

      <para>Choosing a tracker report consists in deciding what fields
      you want to use as search criteria and what fields you want to
      see in the columns of the table where the results of the search
      are presented. You can also define the order in which the search
      criteria and the columns will appear on the screen.</para>

      <para>Project Administrators have the ability to define tracker
      reports that will be usable by all project members whereas
      non-project administrators can only define reports for their
      personal use.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tracker Reports specifies the report layout
      not the report content</title><para>While configuring Tracker
      reports you will probably notice that the configuration screen
      allows you to define the fields that you are going to use a
      search criteria but not the values of this search criteria. This
      is on purpose. Defining a report template and filling out the
      search template with content (values) are 2 distinct operations
      on CodeX. Once a report template has been defined in the
      administration module (e.g &#39;Simple Report&#39;, &#39;QA
      report&#39;, &#39;Daily report&#39; ...)  you can go to the
      tracker searching and browsing module and use the report
      template for all sorts of queries. Select the report you want
      from the pull-down menu, fill out the search form with the
      values you are interested in and click on the browse
      button. Then you can save the entire query (report plus values)
      with the CodeX bookmarking mechanism (see tip in <xref
	      linkend="ArtifactSelectionCriteria" />). And voila!</para></tip></para>

      <section id="TrackerReportBrowsing">
	<title>Browsing Tracker Reports</title>

	<para>Clicking on the &#34;Manage Reports&#34; item in the Tracker
	Administration menu bar at the top of the page displays the
	list of available reports (see <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerReportBrowsing" />) with the following
	information:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis>: a number that
	    uniquely identify the report. A click on the report ID
	    brings you to the report configuration screen (see <xref linkend="TrackerReportSetting" />).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Report Name</emphasis>: the
	    report short name as it will appear in the report
	    select box when you'll be using the artifact browsing screen
	    (e.g. Simple Report, QA report, Monthly Report&hellip;).</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a longer description of the report.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis>:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="dash" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Project</emphasis>:
		this report will be usable by all project
		members. Only project administrators can define
		project-wide reports.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis
		role="underline">Personal</emphasis>: this report will
		be usable by its creator only.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Delete?</emphasis>: click the
	    trash icon to delete the report. Project-wide reports can
	    only be deleted by project administrators.</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureTrackerReportBrowsing">
	  <title>List of tracker reports from the CodeX project</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerreportbrowsing.png" width="14.3cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerReportSetting">
	<title>Tracker Report Setting</title>

	<para>After you click on a report ID in the report list (see
	<xref linkend="TrackerReportBrowsing" />, the report setting
	screen appears (see <xref linkend="FigureTrackerReportSetting"
	    />). This screen allows you to define what fields you'd like
	to use as search criteria and what fields you'd like to see in
	the list of artifacts retrieved from the database.</para>

	<para>Information available on this screen are as follows:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet"
	  spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>: each report
	    must be given a name. This name must not be too long as it
	    will appear in a select box in the artifact browsing module
	    when you are asked to choose what tracker report you want to
	    use to query your artifact database.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scope</emphasis> (optional):
	    project administrators can define project-wide reports
	    that will be made available to all users. Non project
	    administrators can only define personal report.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>: a longer description of the report.</para>
	  </listitem
	    >
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Field selection</emphasis>:
	    the field table shows all the fields that are
	    currently in use in your tracker. For
	    each field you can set up the following parameters:</para>

	    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Use as a Search
		Criteria</emphasis>: If you check this box the field
		will appear as one of the selection criteria when you
		search the tracker database.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Rank on
		Search</emphasis>: A number can be entered in this
		field. The rank number allows you to place the field
		with respect to the others. The fields with smaller
		values will appear first on the list of selection
		criteria displayed on the screen. These number doesn't
		have to be consecutive numbers.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Use as a Report
		Column</emphasis>: If you check this box the field
		will appear as one of the column in the search results 
		table.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      
	      <listitem>
		<para><emphasis role="underline">Rank on
		Report</emphasis>: A number can be entered in this
		field. The rank number allows you to place the field
		with respect to the others. The fields with smaller
		values will appear first in the search results
		table (from left to right). These number doesn't have
		to be consecutive numbers.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Column
	    Width</emphasis>(optional): In case you want to impose a
	    specific width to the column in the report table you can
	    specify a column width in percentage of the total page
	    width. This is optional and our recommendation is to leave
	    it blank unless your Web browser doesn't make a good job
	    at formatting your table. If you want a column to be as
	    narrow as possible while preserving word boundaries enter
	    a very small percentage like 1 or 2 in the column width
	    field.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: it is
	perfectly OK to use a field as a search criteria and not as a
	column in the tracker report and vice versa. For the fields you don't
	want to use at all in the report leave both check
	boxes.</para></note>

	<figure id="FigureTrackerReportSetting">
	  <title>Setting a  Tracker Report</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackerreportsetting.png" width="14.2cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>
	
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="TrackerEmailNotificationSettings">
      <title>Email Notification Settings</title>

      <para>As explained earlier in <xref
	  linkend="TrackerEmailNotification" /> the CodeX Tracker comes
      with a predefined set of rules to keep relevant people aware of
      the artifact life. The default rules can however be complemented
      or tuned in a number of ways:</para>

      <section id="TrackerGlobalEmailNotification">
	<title>Global Email Notification</title>

	<para>In addition to the default notification rules, the
	project administrators have the ability to specify a list of
	comma separated email addresses to which submissions of new
	artifacts (and optionally artifact updates) will be
	systematically sent. Note that in this case notifications will
	be sent to users regardless of their personal preferences
	defined (see section &#34;<xref
	linkend="TrackerEventRoleBasedEmailNotification" />&#34;
	below).</para>

	<para>This feature is typically used to send submissions of
	new artifacts to a number of well identified persons in the
	team who are in charge of qualifying and dispatching the
	artifacts.</para>

	<para><tip>
	    <title>Tip: Create a Distribution List to notify several people</title>
	    
	    <para>If you want to notify many people at once, we suggest
	  that you use the CodeX Mailing Lists service to create a
	  distribution lists (see <xref linkend="MailingLists"
		/>). Once the Mailing List is up and running type the e-mail
	  address in the Global Email Notification field.</para>

	    <para>Creating a Mailing List on CodeX has several
	  advantages: first individuals can (un)subscribe by
	  themselves and second all messages sent to a CodeX mailing
	  list are kept in an archive that can serve as an audit
	  trail for your tracker.</para>
	  </tip>
        </para>

      </section>


      <section id="TrackerWatchers">
	<title>Tracker Watchers</title>

	<para>The CodeX Tracker offers to all project members the
	ability to be carbon-copied on all email notifications sent to
	some other project members. If you use this feature you'll
	systematically receive a copy of the email notifications sent
	to the people you are watching. </para>

	<para>Here are a couple of examples where the tracker watch
	feature can be extremely useful:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Backups</emphasis>: when a
	    team member is away from the office it is often convenient
	    to delegate her artifact management activity to another
	    person in the team who is acting as a backup. Becoming the
	    backup of another team member is as easy as inserting her
	    name in the Watchers field of the backup person when
	    the team member quits and remove it when the team member
	    returns.</para>

	    <para>As soon as you specify a person name in the 
	    watchers field you'll start receiving all the artifact
	    notification of this person and you can act accordingly on her
	    behalf.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">QA Contacts</emphasis>:
	    another possible use is for the QA team members to fill
	    the tracker watcher field with the names of the software
	    engineers whom QA activity they are responsible for.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<note><para>Remark: The goal of the tracker watch feature is not
	to spy on you. To make sure that you are only watched by
	authorized persons, CodeX always shows you the list of CodeX
	users who are currently watching your email 
	notifications. </para></note>

      </section>

      <section id="TrackerEventRoleBasedEmailNotification" xreflabel="Event/Role Based Notification Settings">
	<title>Event/Role Based Notification Settings</title>

	<para>This is the most sophisticated part of the customization
	process. It allows any user to specify what types of events
	they wants to be notified of by email. Note that these settings
	are project and user specific so you can tune your own email
	notification preferences for each project you are involved
	with.</para>

	<para>The customization matrix (see <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix" />) presents you with a
	series of check boxes. Each check box allows you to specify
	what kind of events you want to be aware of depending on
	the role you play with repect to the artifact.</para>

	<para>There are 4 roles defined with respect to an artifact:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Submitter</emphasis>: you are
	    the person who initially reported the artifact by filling
	    out the artifact submission form.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Assignee</emphasis>: you were
	    assigned the artifact and you are therefore responsible
	    for managing it.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">CC</emphasis>: you are
	    mentioned in the list of CC names.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Commenter</emphasis>: you have
	    once posted a follow-up comment in the artifact.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>For each of these roles you can instruct the CodeX
	Tracker to send email notifications to you only when some
	specific events occur. Nine different events (see the right
	most column on <xref linkend="FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix"
	    />) are monitored by the CodeX Tracker. The description of the
	events is self explanatory and only appeal one comment: the
	first 8 events in the list can only occur on artifact
	updates. Only the last event relates to the submission of a
	new artifact.</para>

	<para>Let's review the sample matrix shown on <xref
	    linkend="FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix" /> and see, step by
	step, how this user has configured her notification
	settings:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>First let's look at the Commenter
	  column. The Commenter column says that this user has decided
	  that if they were involved in an artifact as a Commenter (they just
	  posted a follow-up comment at some point in time) then they
	  are only interested in receiving email notification when the
	  status of the artifact goes to &#34;Closed&#34; or when any of the fields
	  Priority, Status and Severity is modified. All other events
	  will be ignored by the CodeX tracker and no notification
	  will be sent to this user.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Second, looking at the matrix by row, one can see
	  that the user said that when they make a modification to an artifact 
	  themself (Event &#34;I am the author of the change&#34;) they don't
	  want to receive any email notification whatever their role 
	  in this artifact is. Please note that the event &#34;I am the author 
	  of the change&#34; overlaps with other events. So in our example 
	  configuration, the submitter will not get a notification when he adds 
	  a new artifact. Even if the event &#34;A new artifact has been 
	  submitted&#34; is marked</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Finally, the user also said that when a new
	  artifact is submitted to the project and is immediately assigned
	  to her (Assignee role), they want to be notified. However if
	  they are the submitter of the new artifact then they are not
	  interested in receiving the notification.</para>

	    <para>Note that the Commenter role is meaningless for
	      the event &#34;A new artifact has been submitted&#34; because
	      follow-up comments can only be added in update time not
	      at creation time. Also, the event &#34;I'm added or removed 
              from this role&#34; is meaningless for the Submitter and the Commenter. Co</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="FigureTrackerNotificationMatrix">
	  <title>Personal Notification Settings</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata format="PNG"
		fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_trackernotificationmatrix.png" width="12.5cm" />
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>

      </section>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

