<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2002-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="VersionControlWithSubversion">
  <title>Version Control with Subversion</title>

  <para>This chapter is not a Subversion Tutorial. It focuses on the
  integration of Subversion with CodeX and how to use it in an optimal
  way in this context. If you are not familiar with Subversion we
  warmly advise you to first read some of the documentrs listed in the
  references section (see <xref linkend="SubversionReferences" />).</para>

  <para>It is important to note that a version control tool like
  Subversion is just a part of the overall configuration management
  activity. Therefore, Subversion alone does not constitute a complete
  configuration management solution for your project. Depending on the
  maturity of a project, the project may have specific policies
  regarding the use of the software baseline or the integration of bug
  fixes, etc. The Subversion tool may allow you to enforce some of
  these mechanisms but project managers should make sure that these
  policies are documented, maintained and well understood by all
  project members.</para>

  <para> For example, a project may wish both to commit changes daily
  to avoid loss of work, and to also insure that the baseline is
  always unit tested code. Since the end of the day may arrive before
  the code or unit tests are complete, a single baseline cannot
  accommodate both uses, so the project may opt to use Subversion
  branches. Don&#39;t worry if you do not initially know enough to
  write the final configuration management policy for your project -
  this always tends to evolve as the project matures - but do
  communicate regularly with the project members and improve your
  configuration management plan on a regular basis.</para>

  <section id="Subversion:TheNextGenerationCVS">
    <title>Subversion: The Next Generation CVS</title>

    <para>Subversion is an Open Source version control system that
    manages your files and directories history over time. The
    Subversion effort started in early 2000 under the leadership of
    Karl Fogel, a recognized guru of CVS and author of the so-called
    'CVS Black Book'(see <xref linkend="SubversionReferences"
    />). Like millions of developers in the world, Karl had used CVS
    for years and acknowledged the fact that, in spite of its merits,
    it had a number of shortfalls that would be nice to fix.</para>

    <para>From the very beginning the Subversion team, sponsored by
    the CollabNet company, clearly stated that the goal was not to
    produce a revolutionary version control system but rather to build
    on the strengthes of CVS and wipe out all of its weaknesses. As a
    result, like CVS, Subversion belongs to the family of concurrent
    version control system. It means that a team of multiple
    developers can concurrently manage their own version of the same
    source code and gracefully merge the changes brought to the
    software by the various team players.</para>

    <para>But Subversion also comes with a number of enhancements over
    CVS:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Directory versioning</emphasis>:
	because CVS relies on the native file system of the machine it
	runs on it has been impossible to implement the versioning of
	directories. Subversion implements a "virtual" filesystem
	stored in a database that tracks changes to the entire
	directory and file tree.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">True version history</emphasis>:
	moving and renaming files in a CVS repository has some
	limitations mainly due to the fact that versioning is attached
	to individual files. With Subversion you can add, delete,
	rename and copy files or entire directories without doing any
	compromise on the file naming or the file history.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Atomic commits</emphasis>: although
	CodeX provides an additional layer on top of CVS which gives
	an atomic view of the commits, CVS itself has no notion of the
	fact that you may have committed a dozen file at the same time
	to fix a single bug. Subversion on the contrary stamps the
	entire tree with a new revision number each time you make a
	change.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Versioned metadata</emphasis>: Subversion can
	attached any number of properties (in the form of kay/value
	pairs) to files and directories. Properties are themselves
	versioned like the files and directories they are attached
	to.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Various access protocols</emphasis>:
	Like CVS Subversion offers a choice of network protocols to
	access a subversion repository. It can be a local file system
	access or a network access through the Subversion own's
	lightweight protocol (svnserve) or a secured remote access
	through SSH. Additionally and more importantly, Subversion can
	be accessed through the WebDAV protocol which is an extension
	of the HTTP protocol. This has a number of advantages like the
	ability to run all transactions through secure HTTP, go
	through firewalls and take advantage of the HTTP
	authentication methods.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Efficient diff'ing</emphasis>: when
	you create a working copy on your desktop machine, a complete
	version of the original file is kept on your disk which allows
	developers to perform status and diff operations even when working 
	offline.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Efficient branching and
	tagging</emphasis>: in Subversion these 2 operations are performed
	by literally copying (all or part of) the repository. The
	copy is virtual in the sense that the virtual filesystem
	establishes hard links to indicate from which revision the
	copy comes from. As a result branching and tagging takes a
	very small amount of disk space and, above all, it takes a
	constant amount of time regardless of the repository
	size.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Fine grain access control</emphasis>:
	in its CodeX incarnation, your Subversion repository operates
	on top of the HTTP protocol and it therefore take advantage of
	the rich HTTP authentication mechanism. As a result CodeX
	allows you to fine tune who has access to which part of your
	Subversion repository whether for read, write or no access at
	all.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Extensibility</emphasis>: like CVS,
	Subversion comes with a number of facility to hook custom
	processing at the various stage of a commit operation
	(pre-check, post-check,etc.). Unlike CVS, Subversion comes
	with well documented library APIs with bindings available for
	several languages like C/C++, Python and Perl.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Subversion is not a perfect system either and when one has
    to decide whether to use Subversion or CVS, the following points
    must be taken into account:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">No lock/unlock</emphasis>: As
	of version 1.0.x, Subversion has no lock/unlock mechanism. If
	you insist that your project members uses the lock/unlock
	model to make changes then stick to CVS for now. Subversion
	1.1 will have lock/unlock available.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Less graphical client</emphasis>:
	although Subversion already has a number of graphical clients
	available on various platforms it may take some months before
	it is available in your favorite Integrated Development
	Environment.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="SubversionClients">
      <title>Subversion Clients</title>

      <para>Subversion has a client-server architecture. In other
      words, CodeX developers who want to interact with the Subversion
      repository of their project must have Subversion installed on
      their desktop machine, hereafter called client. The CodeX server
      permanently runs a Subversion server in the background to which
      Subversion clients talk to to act upon the Subversion
      repository. Subversion clients come in various flavour for all
      sorts of platforms (Windows and all Unix): command line
      interface, graphical based interface and web based
      interface.</para>

      <section id="SubversionCommandLineInterface">
	<title>Command Line Interface</title>

	<para>Subversion comes with a command line interface that can
	be used on virtually any platform (Linux/Unix, MS Windows,
	Mac...). Even though Subversion has multiple command line
	options, most commands that you normally use have one or two
	command-line options and are very easy to remember and look a
	lot like cvs commands. Refer to <xref
	linkend="SubversionReferences" /> for more information about
	how to use the Subversion command line.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="SubversionGraphicalFront-ends">
	<title>Graphical Front-ends</title>

	<para>Subversion already has a number of graphical
	front-ends. rapidSVN is part of the standard Subversion
	package and runs on Linux and Windows. TortoiseSVN is another
	option for MS Windows users. jSVN is a Java based client that
	can run on any platform. As time goes the list of graphical
	front-ends will certainly grow. Refer to <xref
	linkend="SubversionReferences" /> for more information about
	those graphical clients.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="SettingUprapidSVNforCodeX">
	<title>Setting up rapidSVN for CodeX</title>

        <para>As mentioned above, rapidSVN is the graphical user
        interface that standard with Subversion for Linux and
        Windows. Below are all the instructions needed to get rapidSVN
        running on a CodeX project. In the instructions below,
        "username" is the CodeX user login name, and "projectname" is
        the CodeX short project name the user is working on.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
	  <para>Download rapidSVN from the Subversion Web site and
          install it on your PC.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
	  <para>Launch the rapidSVN application.</para>
        </listitem>
	
        <listitem>
	  <para>Create a new bookmark for your Subversion repository:
	  <literal>Bookmarks->Add Repository...</literal></para>
	  <para>When prompted enter the URL to your repository:
	  <literal>http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
	  <para>Click on the new bookmark corresponding to your
	  repository and type you CodeX user name and password when
	  asked to. You should now be able to browse the repository
	  and see the file status and revision history.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	
        <listitem>
	  <para>To create your own working copy use the menu item
	  <literal>Repository->Checkout...</literal></para>
	  <para>When the dialog box pops up, type the same URL as
	  above and choose where you want your working copy to be
	  created.</para>
        </listitem>
	
        <listitem>
	  <para>A second bookmark corresponding to the new working
	  copy should now appear in the bookmark pane on the left hand
	  side of the screen. On the right hand side appears the list
	  of files and directories of your working copy along with
	  their revision number and status. From there use your
	  favorite editor to modify the source code, hit the refresh
	  button in rapidSVN to see modified files and commit your
	  changes when your are done.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="SubversionReferences">
      <title>Subversion References</title>

      <para>As stated earlier in this chapter, this document is not a
      Subversion Tutorial. If you want to learn more about Subversion
      refer to the following documents:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>The Subversion Book. see <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">http://svnbook.red-bean.com</ulink>).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Another CVS tutorial written by members of the Xerox
	  Wilson Center. See <ulink
	  url="http://techweb.wrc.xerox.com/Get/File-71895/cvs-strategy.html">http://techweb.wrc.xerox.com/Get/File-71895/cvs-strategy.html</ulink></para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para>The Official Subversion Web Site. See <ulink
	  url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">http://subversion.tigris.org/</ulink>
	  This is where you'll find the subversion software including
	  the rapidSVN client.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>TortoiseSVN. A graphical MS Windows and Linux
	  graphical client. See <ulink
	  url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/</ulink>. </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>jSVN. A graphical 100% Java graphical client. See
	  <ulink
	  url="http://jsvn.alternatecomputing.com/">http://jsvn.alternatecomputing.com/</ulink>.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="SubversionIntegrationinCodeX">
    <title>Subversion Integration in CodeX</title>

    <section id="TheSubversionRepository">
      <title>The Subversion Repository</title>

      <para>Whenever a new project is hosted on CodeX, a new
      Subversion repository is automatically created and properly
      initialized. Each project has its own Subversion repository as
      opposed to what happens in most Subversion servers, where
      several projects share the same repository. Having its own
      repository has a certain number of advantages: the Subversion
      logs, history files, and all administrative files (e.g. hook
      scripts) are unique to each project repository.  This allows you
      to fully customize the behavior of Subversion for a given
      project without impacting the others.</para>

      <note><para>All interactions with a Subversion repository should
      normally happen through a Subversion client. However if need be
      and if you know exactly what you are doing you can get access to
      your Subversion repository via your CodeX shell account (see
      <xref linkend="ShellAccount" />). Once the shell session is
      active you'll find your subversion repository under
      <literal>/svnroot/projectname</literal>.</para></note>
    </section>


    <section id="TheSubversionRepositoryStructure">
      <title>The Subversion Repository Structure</title>

      <para>When a new Codex project is created, it comes with a
      virgin subversion repository that the project team must
      populate. Due to the fact that Subversion manages branching and
      tagging through its virtual filesystem (and not through labels
      attached to individual files as in CVS) there is a recommended
      way to organize your repository. The layout suggested below can
      be considered as a de-facto standard and we highly recommend
      that you follow this best practice.</para>


      <para>If you expect your CodeX project to manage only one
      project deliverable then you can create the following top-level
      directories in your repository:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
/trunk
/branches
/tags
      </programlisting>

      <para>where <literal>/trunk</literal> contains the main line of
      development, <literal>/branches</literal> contains branch copies
      and <literal>/tags</literal> contains tag copies of your source
      code that generally correspond to a given release.</para>

      <para>If you expect your CodeX project to manage several
      software deliverables that are managed independently one from
      each other, then it is often a good idea to first create
      top-level directories that carry the name of the sub-project and
      under each of these directories repeat the same structure as
      above. Assuming you have two subprojects named
      <literal>engine</literal> and <literal>client</literal>, the
      initial layout of your repository should look like this:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
/engine/trunk
/engine/branches
/engine/tags
/client/trunk
/client/branches
/client/tags
      </programlisting>

      <para>More on the repository layout is available in the
      Subversion book listed in the References section (see <xref
      linkend="SubversionReferences" />).</para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="SubversionBrowsingInterface">
    <title>The Subversion Browsing Interface</title>

    <para>CodeX offers a number a facilities that allow you to
    interact with your Subversion repository through the Web
    interface. The Subversion Web interface does not intend to replace
    the Subversion client that you should normally use on your desktop
    computer. It rather focuses on providing you with additional
    features not found in Subversion clients.</para>

    <para>The Subversion Web interface can be accessed via the
    &#34;Subversion&#34; item in the Project Main Menu or via the
    Subversion service listed in the Public Area (see <xref
    linkend="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage" />). The CodeX
    Subversion Web interface provides the following features to CodeX
    end-users:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Accessing the Subversion
	repository</emphasis>: The welcome page of the CodeX
	Subversion service gives you all the information you need to
	access the Subversion repository from your Subversion
	client. Among other things it tells you what the Subversion
	root path is and how to checkout the source code. This page
	may also be customized to display project specific
	instructions (see <xref
	linkend="SubversionAdministrationInterface"/>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Browsing the Subversion
	repository</emphasis>: this feature allows you to browse the
	Subversion repository even if you don't have a Subversion
	client installed on your desktop machine. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Querying Subversion </emphasis>:
	If the Subversion tracking feature has been activated for your
	project all Subversion events (commit, file addition or
	deletion) are tracked down in the CodeX database. This audit
	trail can be searched using several criteria.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Subversion Administration
	</emphasis>: this service allows project administrator to
	perform the most common Subversion administration and
	configuration tasks from the CodeX Web interface (for more
	details see <xref
	linkend="SubversionAdministrationInterface"/>).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Let's review some of these features in more details.</para>

    <section id="BrowsingTheSubversionRepository">
    <title>Browsing The Subversion Repository</title>

    <para>In order to interact with the Subversion repository of any
    CodeX-hosted project, you normally need to have Subversion installed on
    your machine.  However CodeX also offers a built-in Web browsing
    interface to the Subversion repository which allows you to navigate in
    the source code, download it, view a file history or compare two
    revisions of the same file.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleSubversionWebSession">
	<title>Browsing the Subversion repository - A sample session</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../slides/en_US/SVN_Web_Session.png" width="12cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="QueryingSubversion">
    <title>Querying Subversion</title>

      <para>If a project has the Subversion Tracking feature activated
      (see <xref linkend="SubversionAdministrationInterface" />), the
      Subversion Web interface will bring very useful features to the
      software engineers:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="dash">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Atomic Subversion commit and
	  unique commit ID</emphasis>: all changes (file modification,
	  addition or removal) that are committed in one go from your
	  Subversion client are assigned a unique commit ID also known
	  as a Subversion revision number.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Commit
	  cross-referencing</emphasis>: the unique commit ID (or
	  revision number) generated at each commit can be referenced
	  in future commits, or in the follow-up comments of project
	  artifacts like bugs/tasks/support requests simply by using
	  the pattern <literal>commit #XXXX</literal>, or
	  <literal>revision #XXXX</literal> or even <literal>rev
	  #XXXX</literal> (where XXXX is the unique ID generated by
	  CodeX). Any reference of that kind will be automatically
	  transformed into an hyperlink to the Subversion tracking
	  database. This mechanism makes it very easy to go from
	  project artifacts like bugs, support requests or tasks to
	  source code changes and vice-versa (more on this mechanism
	  at <xref linkend="Cross-ReferencingSubversionCommits"
	  />).</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Commit search</emphasis>:
	  another side benefit of the Subversion Tracking database is
	  that you can use various search criteria to query the
	  Subversion tracking database. You can search code changes by
	  authors (who made the change), by revision number, by file
	  path or by keywords to be found in the log message. Results
	  can also be sorted by clicking on the headers of the search
	  results (see <xref linkend="FigureSubversionSearch"
	  />).</para>

	  <para>A click on one of the selected commit ID brings you to
	  a complete description of the change, the files that were
	  impacted and the nature of the change with a direct link
	  into the Subversion repository if you want to browse the file or
	  look at the code modification (see <xref
	  linkend="FigureSubversionShowCommit" />).</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
	  
    </section>


      <figure id="FigureSubversionSearch">
	<title>Querying the Subversion tracking database of a given project</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_svnsearch.png" width="15cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

    <section id="Cross-ReferencingSubversionCommits">
    <title>Cross-Referencing Artifacts and Subversion Commits</title>

      <para>While working in the development or the maintenance phase
      of a software project, it is vital to keep track of the changes
      made to the source code. This is what Version Control systems
      like Subversion do. In addition to keeping track of the source
      code change history it is often critical to relate the changes
      to the artifact (a task, a defect or a support request) that led
      the developers to make a change in the code. And conversely,
      when reading the artifact description it is also very helpful to
      immediately see how the change was implemented.</para>

      <para>The integration of Subversion in CodeX precisely provides
      CodeX users with this bi-directionnal cross-referencing
      mechanism. This is achieved through the use of text patterns
      that are automatically detected by CodeX in either the follow-up
      comments of the project artifacts or in the messages attached to
      a Subversion commit.</para>
      
      <para>The text patterns to type in a commit message or a
      follow-up comment are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para> <emphasis role="bold">XXX #NNN</emphasis>: this
	  pattern refers to the artifact XXX number NNN, where NNN is
	  the unique artifact ID, and XXX is the tracker short name
	  (e.g. &#34;bug #123&#34;, &#34;task #321&#34;, &#34;req
	  #12&#34;, etc.).  If you don't know the tracker short name
	  or don't want to specify it, you may simply use &#34;art
	  #NNN&#34;. When browsing a message containing this pattern
	  anywhere in CodeX, the pattern will be automatically
	  transformed into an hyperlink to the artifact
	  description.</para>
      </listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">commit #YYY or rev
	  #YYY</emphasis>: this pattern refers to the commit YYY where
	  YYY is the commit revision number as listed when querying
	  the Subversion tracking database. When browsing a message
	  containing this pattern anywhere in CodeX, the pattern will
	  be automatically transformed into an hyperlink to the commit
	  description which include log messages, impacted files,
	  versions and author of the change(see <xref
	  linkend="FigureSubversionShowCommit" />) .</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <figure id="FigureSubversionShowCommit">
	<title>The detail of an atomic Subversion commit</title>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_svnshowcommit.png" width="15cm" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>


      <para><tip><title>Tip: cross-reference artifacts and Subversion
      commits</title><para>It is considered a best practice to always
      reference a bug, a task or a support request in any of the log
      message attached to a Subversion commit. Similarly when closing
      the related artifact (task, bug,etc.) make sure you mention the
      revision number in the follow-up comment. You will find this
      extremelly convenient while trying to keep track of the changes
      and why they were made.</para></tip></para>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="SubversionAdministrationInterface">
    <title>Subversion Administration Interface</title>

    <para>Through the CodeX Web interface, project administrators can
    perform the most common administration and configuration tasks on
    their Subversion repository. The administration functions can be
    accessed through the <literal>SVN Admin</literal> menu item in the
    Subversion menu bar.</para>
      

    <section id="SubversionGeneralSettings">
    <title>General Settings</title>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Subversion
	    Tracking</emphasis>: Being a version control system
	    Subversion is, of course, natively taking care of all your
	    file history and is able to tell you what changes were
	    made by whom and at what date. The file history is
	    something you can look at either through your Subversion
	    client or through the Subversion Web Browsing
	    interface.</para>

	    <para>If you activate the Subversion tracking (default)
	    for your project CodeX will also keep track of all the
	    code changes in the CodeX database. This will give you
	    extra capabilities on your Subversion repository as
	    explained in <xref linkend="QueryingSubversion" />.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Subversion
	    Preamble</emphasis>: In some cases (e.g. when your project
	    already has its own subversion server in place), the
	    project Subversion repository might not be hosted by the
	    CodeX server. In this case, the Subversion information
	    displayed in the welcome page of the CodeX Subversion
	    service are inadequatet. Fortunately, the project
	    administrator can customize the Subversion Information
	    page here.</para>
	  </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>


      <section id="SubversionAccessControl">
	<title>Subversion Access Control</title>
	

      <section id="DefaultSubversionAccessPermissions">
	<title>Default Access Permissions</title>

	<para>When CodeX first creates the subversion repository of a
	project, distinct level of access permissions are granted to
	CodeX users depending upon the class of citizen (see <xref
	linkend="ClassesOfCitizens" />) they belong to:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Anonymous Users</emphasis>:
	    users who have not registered with CodeX (or are not
	    logged in) have <emphasis role="underline">no access at
	    all</emphasis> to the Subversion repositories.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Registered Users</emphasis>:
	    have read-only access to Subversion repositories. In other
	    words they can checkout a working copy of the software but
	    they are not allowed to commit any changes they have made
	    to the source code. Source code contributions (bug fix,
	    enhancements&hellip;) from this class of user must return
	    to the project team via the Patch Manager (see <xref
	    linkend="PatchManager" /> ).</para>

	    <note><para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: all
	    source code accesses are recorded by CodeX. Project
	    administrators always have access to the list of people
	    who accessed the source code (see <xref
	    linkend="SourceCodeAccessLogs" />).</para></note>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis>:
	    members of a CodeX hosted project are granted a password
	    protected read/write access.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Project
	  Administrators</emphasis>: same as project members.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="CustomizedSubversionAccessPermissions">
	<title>Customized Access Permissions</title>

	<para>Thanks to the integration of Subversion in the CodeX
	environment, project administrators can redefine access
	permissions for some or all CodeX users.</para>

	<para>This can be achieved by specifying access permission
	rules that will complement or even override the default
	settings. The syntax of the access permission rules follows
	the following pattern:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
[path]
name = permission
      </programlisting>

	<para>where: </para>
	<itemizedlist mark="dash">

	  <listitem><para><literal>path</literal> is the path to the
	  directory or to the filename (relative to
	  <literal>/svnroot/projectname</literal> in your repository
	  for which you want to redefine access
	  permissions.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><literal>name</literal> is either a CodeX login name
	    or group name. The name * (star) means any registered
	    user.</para>

	    <para>If it is a group name it must precededed with the @
	    character. The line <literal>name = permission</literal>
	    can be repeated as many times as necessary for a given
	    path. To define groups of users use the following
	    block statement:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
[groups]
groupname = username1,username2,...
      </programlisting>

	  </listitem>

	  <listitem><para><literal>permission</literal> is either
	  <literal>r</literal> for read-only access,
	  <literal>rw</literal> for read-write access or blank if
	  access is forbidden.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>As an illustration, the default permission settings of a
	CodeX explained in the previous section are expressed through
	the following set of rules:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
[groups]
members = member1,member2,...,memberN

[/]
* = r
@members = rw
      </programlisting>

	<para>where <literal>member1,member2,...,memberN</literal> are
	the CodeX login name of the CodeX project members.</para>

	<para>For more information about the format of this file you
	should refer to the Subversion Book (see <xref
	linkend="SubversionReferences" />).</para>

      </section>

    </section>

      <section id="SubversionEmailNotification">
	<title>Subversion Email Notification</title>

	<para>In addition to tracking the changes in the CodeX
	database, CodeX can also send a nicely formatted email message
	to individual email addresses or mailing lists each time there
	is a change in the source code. The email message contains
	the log message, the author of the change, the list of
	impacted files and pointers to the Subversion repository
	showing what changes were made. </para>

	<para>Project Administrators can configure the following
	settings for email notification:</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Email addresses</emphasis>: a
	    comma separated list of email addresses of people to whom
	    the email notification must be sent can be given. If your
	    want to notify a large group of people then we strngly
	    advise you to create a mailing list first (see
	    below).</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para><emphasis role="bold">Subject Header</emphasis>: is
	    a piece of text that will appear as a trailer in the
	    Subject of all the email notifications sent to the
	    addressees. This trailer is supposed to help the addressee
	    to quickly spot the messages in their Inbox or to put
	    filters in place to route the email notification to a
	    given folder.</para>
	  </listitem>

	</itemizedlist>

	<para><tip><title>Tip: create a specific mailing list for
	Subversion events notification</title><para>If you intend to
	generate email notification for the changes made in your
	Subversion repository, it is a good practice to create a
	specific mailing list called
	<literal>projectname-svnevents</literal>. By doing so, CodeX
	users and project members interested in receiving the email
	notification just need to subscribe to the mailing list. In
	addition, the CodeX mailing list manager will archive all the
	email messages which can prove very useful for future
	reference.  See <xref linkend="MailingLists" /> for mailing
	list creation.</para></tip></para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="ATypicalSubversionLifeCycle">
    <title>A Typical Subversion Life Cycle</title>

    <para>As staed earlier, the intent of this chapter is not to give
    a formal Subversion training but rather to explain what are the
    steps a project team typically goes through when using Subversion
    and, more generally, all the CodeX tools involved in a Software
    release process.</para>

    <para>It also deals with the problem of contributing source code
    when you are not part of a project team. In this section all
    examples are given in the form of Subversion command lines but
    transposing them to graphical front-ends should be relatively
    straightforward.</para>

    <figure id="FigureATypicalSubversionSoftwareDevelopmentLifeCycleOnCodeX">
      <title>A Typical Software Development Life Cycle on CodeX</title>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata format="PNG"
	    fileref="../../slides/en_US/SVN_Life_Cycle.png" width="14cm" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="SubversionLoggingIn">
      <title>Logging In</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>Unlike CVS when used with the pserver protocol there is no
      explicit login command to issue to start working with a
      Subversion repository. Subversion will ask for your login name
      and password only when performing an operation (e.g. commit)
      that requires authentication.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="SubversionImportingExistingSourceCode">
      <title>Importing Existing Source Code</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>As the happy administrator of a new CodeX project, the
      first thing to do is to populate your freshly brewed Subversion
      repository with your project source code. To do so, first create
      a new directory <literal>topdirectory</literal> on your
      workstation and populate this top level directory with the
      recommended directory layout documented earlier (see <xref
      linkend="TheSubversionRepositoryStructure" />).</para>

      <para>Place yourself into the <literal>topdirectory</literal> and  type the following command (in one line):</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn --username loginname import . 
http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname 
--message "Initial repository layout"
        </programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>projectname</literal> is the
            project short name</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>loginname</literal> is your CodeX login (all
	  lowercase). The --username option is only needed if your
	  CodeX login name is different from the Unix or Windows login
	  name you are currently working with.</para>
	</listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: made a mistake while importing your
      source code?</title><para>It is not unusual to make a mistake
      when importing your source code into a fresh Subversion
      repository especially for new users.  Typical mistakes are
      directories placed at the wrong level or with the wrong
      name. Nothing to fear though... If you want to start again from
      a fresh Subversion repository contact the CodeX Team to get your
      Subversion repository reinitialized. Alternatively you can
      easily delete or move directories and files with any subversion
      client afterwards.</para></tip></para>

      <note><para>Note that if you already have a Subversion
      repository available, the CodeX Team can help you migrate this
      repository on CodeX and preserve all of your project history. We
      just need a dump of your Subversion tree generated with the
      <literal>svnadmin dump</literal> command. With this dump the
      CodeX Team will re-install everything for you on the CodeX
      server. Contact us for more information.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="SubversionCheckingCodeOut">
      <title>Checking Code Out</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>Once a Subversion repository has been populated other
      CodeX users can checkout the source code and place it on their
      own workstation. The result is called a working copy in the
      Subversion jargon. Note that &#39;checkout&#39; in the
      Subversion world does not mean that the user has acquired any
      sort of lock on the file. The Subversion paradigm is: anyone
      (with the right permissions) can retrieve a working copy for
      editing; changes are reconciled or flagged for conflict
      resolution when the file is committed. Unlike other tools (RCS,
      SCCS, ClearCase...) Subversion is a concurrent version control
      system.</para>

      <para>A working copy is NOT an image of the Subversion
      repository. It is rather a snapshot of the source tree at some
      point in time and, by default, it&#39;s the latest version at
      the time the working copy is created or updated. One of the
      interesting features of a working copy is that it is a
      self-contained entity. In other words, a working copy contains
      all the necessary information for Subversion to know exactly
      which Subversion server and repository it is coming from and the
      corresponding moment in the history of the source tree . This is
      also why you won&#39;t see the URL option pointing to the
      Subversion repository in all subsequent Subversion commands
      presented here. These commands run from within a working copy,
      so Subversion knows exactly where the Subversion repository
      is.</para>

      <para>To create a working copy of the entire project type the
      following command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn checkout http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname
</programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"	spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>projectname</literal> is the
            project short name</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="SubversionUpdatingtheSourceCode">
      <title>Updating the Source Code</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>Running an update command from within a working copy has
      the effect of updating the working copy (or a subpart of it)
      with the latest version of each source file from the
      repository. To update a working copy type:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn update
        </programlisting>

    </section>

    <section id="SubversionExaminingyourChanges">
      <title>Examining your Changes</title>

      <para>If you want to know what files have changed on the
      Subversion repository since your last update or which ones have
      been modified in your own working copy, you can run following
      command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn status
        </programlisting>

      <para>The output will show you a list of files which undergo
      some changes either because they were modified, added or
      deleted.</para>

      <para>To compare your locally modified version of a file with
      the original version in the Subversion repository, you can use
      the diff command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn diff filename
        </programlisting>

      <para>If no <literal>filename</literal> is specified the diff
      operation is applied recursively on all the files and
      sub-directories.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="SubversionCommittingyourChanges">
      <title>Committing your Changes (project team)</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>Project members involved in development activities will
      likely want to contribute the changes made in their own working
      copy back to the Subversion repository. In Subversion
      terminology this is called a commit operation.</para>

      <para>To commit changes you have made in your working copy, type
      the following command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn commit -m&#34;Explain the nature of the change here...&#34; filenames
        </programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>The -m option is followed by a text message explaining what
            changes you have made.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>The <emphasis>filenames</emphasis> argument is
	  optional. It can be individual files or directories. If
	  there isn&#39;t any files mentioned Subversion will
	  automatically commit all the modified files in the directory
	  where you are located and all sub-directories
	  recursively.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Include a bug or task number in your
      commit messages</title><para>In the ideal world, all
      modifications made to the source code of a project should be
      related to either a bug logged or to a task assign to a
      developer. If your project team lives in this wonderful world
      :-) then don&#39;t forget to include the related bug or task ID
      number at the beginning or at the end of your commit
      message. The Subversion hook scripts can help you enforce this
      rule by checking the format of all the submitted commit messages
      and reject them if it does not follow the recommended
      pattern.</para></tip></para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: update before you commit</title>

	  <para>If you try to commit a modified file that was also
	  modified on the Subversion repository in the meantime, the
	  Subversion server will refuse to execute the <literal>svn
	  commit</literal> command. You must first execute a
	  <literal>svn update</literal> command to bring your own
	  working copy up to date with latest version, merge your
	  changes with those from others (Subversion does it
	  automatically in most cases) and then only commit your own
	  changes back to the Subversion repository. If you want to be
	  immune from others&#39; changes then create a Subversion
	  branch and work with it in isolation.</para>
	</tip></para>

    </section>

    <section id="SubversionContributingyourChanges">
      <title>Contributing your Changes (other users)</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is a variant of the previous section for those of you
      who do not have write access to the Subversion repository of a
      project and, therefore, cannot commit their modifications to the
      Subversion repository.</para>

      <para>The variant explained here is actually a method that is
      universally used in the Open Source world to contribute source
      code modification to the project team. It consists in the
      generation of a text file containing the differences between
      your modified version of the source code and the original one
      that you initially checked out.  This file is often refered to
      as "diff file".</para>

      <para>The reason why diff files are so popular is because they
      follow a well-documented format. Diff files are sent to the
      original project team which, upon reception, is going to use
      another universal tool called <literal>patch</literal> to
      automatically merge the contributed changes with the master copy
      of the source code. This is why, by extension, a diff file is
      also often refered to as a <emphasis>patch</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Diff files can be generated either with the
      <emphasis>diff</emphasis> tool (part of the GNU tools) that is
      available on all platforms including Windows or directly from
      within a Subversion working copy.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">The Diff way:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>Use the diff way when you obtained the original source
	  code from a File Release and not from the project Subversion
	  repository.  Let&#39;s assume the original source file is
	  under the directory <literal>project-0.1/</literal> and that
	  your modified version is under
	  <literal>project-0.1-new/</literal></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can generate a diff file with the following
	  command (all files in subdirectories will be checked
	  recursively for changes)</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
diff -rc project-0.1/ project-0.1-new/
</programlisting>

	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">The Subversion way:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>This is the preferred way when you obtained the source
	  code by creating your own Subversion working copy. Let&#39;s
	  assume that you are at the top level of the working
	  copy.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>You can generate a diff file between your version and
	  the very latest version in the Subversion repository for the
	  entire source tree by typing with the following Subversion
	  command:</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn diff
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If you want to generate a diff against a specific
	  version of the source tree, then specify the revision number
	  in the command line (revision #9398 in the example below):</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn diff -r 9398
</programlisting>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In both cases, you should redirect the output of the diff
      or svn diff command in a text file. Compress the output file if
      it&#39;s a large one and use the CodeX Patch Manager (see <xref
      linkend="PatchManager" />) to submit your patch to the project
      team.</para>

      <para>And thanks for contributing some code!</para>
    </section>

    <section id="SubversionExportingandPackaging">
      <title>Exporting and Packaging</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>There is a quick and easy way to release a pre-packaged
      version of your source file and make it available to all CodeX
      users through the File Release mechanism (see <xref
      linkend="FileRelease" />).</para>

      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <para>Make sure all the project members involved in software
	  development have committed the changes that were supposed to
	  appear in this new release.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Update your own working copy with the changes
	  committed by all other project members with the following
	  command:</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn update
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Update the ChangeLog, Release Notes and README file at
	  the top of your source tree and commit the changes for these
	  3 files.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Create a tagged copy of your source code from the main
	  development line with the appropriate version
	  number. Assuming that the name of the release is
	  <literal>myproject-1.4</literal> the creation of the new
	  release is as follows:</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn copy
http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname/trunk
http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname/tags/myproject-1.4
-m "Tagging the 1.4 release"
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Your software release is now ready. Export a clean
	  image of the release 1-4 from the Subversion repository byt
	  typing:</para>

	  <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
svn export
http://svn.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/svnroot/projectname/tags/myproject-1.4
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Create a ZIP or tar archive with the entire
	  <literal>myproject-1.4/</literal> directory</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Deliver this archive through the File Release service.</para>
	</step>

	<step>
	  <para>Done! Nice job...Take a break. And remember to
	  announce the availability of your new version via the CodeX
	  News service (see <xref linkend="NewsService" />).</para>
	</step>
      </procedure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="SubversionforProjectAdministrators">
    <title>Subversion for Project Administrators</title>


    <section id="SubversionHookScripts">
      <title>Subversion Hook Scripts</title>

      <para>CodeX offers an easy to use Web interface to administrate
      the common settings of your Subversion repository like access
      control and email notification. In case project administrators
      want to go deeper in customizing the behavior of their CodeX
      repository, they can get access to the Subversion hook
      scripts.</para>

      <para>In order to access those hook scripts, you must be
      granted the right to log into the CodeX server with your Shell
      Account (see <xref linkend="ShellAccount" />)<footnote><para>The
      Shell Account may have been deactivated by your CodeX site
      administrators.</para></footnote>.</para>.

      <para>Once logged in, type the following commands at the shell
      prompt:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>newgrp projectname</literal> (where <literal>projectname</literal> is the
            short project name)</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>cd /svnroot/projectname/hooks</literal></para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If the hook scripts you want to customize does not yet
	  exist in the <literal>hooks</literal> directory, first
	  create them by copying the corresponding template file
	  provided by Subversion (<literal>.tmpl</literal>
	  extension). Then edit the hook scripts in place.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para><literal>exit</literal> (Logout)</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>***Important Note***: Mind the CodeX
      Hooks!</title><para>If you decide to customize the Subversion
      hook scripts for your repository make sure to preserve the
      statements that could have been inserted by CodeX in the first
      place. The CodeX statements are clearly marked with a
      recognizable header and trailer. </para></tip></para>

    </section>

  </section>

  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

