<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2002-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Laurent Julliard and Stephane Bouhet 2002, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->
  <chapter id="VersionControlWithCVS">
  <title>Version Control with CVS</title>

  <para>This chapter is not a CVS Tutorial. It focuses on the integration of
    CVS with CodeX and how to use it in an optimal way in this context. If you
    are not familiar with the CVS version control system look at the CVS
    references (see <xref linkend="CVSReferences" />).</para>

  <para>It is important to note that version control is just a part of the
    overall configuration management activity. Therefore, CVS alone does not
    constitute a complete configuration management solution for your project.
    Depending on the maturity of a project, the project may have specific
    policies regarding use of the CVS baseline or the integration of bug
    fixes, etc. Projects should make sure that project members know and follow
    these policies. For example, a project may wish both to commit changes
    daily to avoid loss of work, and to also insure that the baseline is
    always unit tested code. Since the end of the day may arrive before the
    code or unit tests are complete, a single baseline cannot accommodate both
    uses, so the project may opt to use CVS branches. Don&#39;t worry if you
    do not initially know enough to write the final policy for your project -
    this always tends to evolve as the project matures - but do communicate
    regularly with the project members and improve your configuration
    management plan on a regular basis.</para>

  <section id="CVS:ConcurrentVersionControl">
    <title>CVS: Concurrent Version Control</title>

    <para>CVS stands for Concurrent Versions System. It allows a team of
      multiple developers to concurrently manage their own version of the same
      source code and gracefully merge the changes brought to the software by
      the various team players. CVS can help you track the changes in the
      history of your project.</para>

    <para>No good software project should be started without making a
    decision on which version control tool is going to be used. CVS
    and Subversion (see <xref linkend="VersionControlWithSubversion"
    />) are the two possible choices offered by CodeX
    <footnote><para>There are many version control software available
    on the market whether Free Software (SCCS, RCS, PKS, Arch,
    Monotone......) or Commercial (SourceSafe, ClearCase,
    TeamWare...)</para></footnote>.  Although Subversion is a more
    modern version control system, using CVS is a very valid choice
    for several reasons:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>It has an elegant and efficient client/server architecture
          that makes it usable from anywhere on the Intranet.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It runs on almost every hardware platforms and Operating
          Systems available on the market today (Linux, Unix, Windows,
          MacOS...).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It is a bullet proof version control system that is being used
          by literally hundreds of thousands of software projects, whether
          Open Source or commercial throughout the world.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It can be used in a command-line mode or through one of the
          many graphical user interface front-ends.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It is very good at minimizing disk storage space on the server
          side and network bandwidth consumption between the client and the
          server. Working with CVS over a modem connection is perfectly
          feasible.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Out of the box it can support small to mid-size projects well,
          and can be configured and extended to support most any size project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>And last but not least, it is a fully Open Source software
          distributed under the GNU GPL License.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="CVSClients">
      <title>CVS Clients</title>

      <para>CVS has a client-server architecture. In other words,
      CodeX developers who want to interact with the CVS repository of
      their project must have CVS installed on their desktop machine,
      hereafter called client. The CodeX server permanently runs a CVS
      server in the background to which CVS clients talk to to act
      upon the CVS repository. CVS clients come in various flavour for
      all sorts of platforms (Windows, Mac and all Unix): command line
      interface, graphical based interface and web based
      interface.</para>

      <section id="CommandLineInterface">
        <title>Command Line Interface</title>

        <para>CVS originates from the Unix world and therefore all the
        CVS functions can be controlled from a command line
        interface. Even though CVS has multiple command line options,
        most commands that you normally use have one or two
        command-line options and are very easy to remember. Refer to
        <xref linkend="CVSReferences" /> for more information about
        how to use CVS.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="GraphicalFront-ends">
        <title>Graphical Front-ends</title>

        <para>Many CVS graphical front-ends can be used on your client
        workstation. There are clients for all platforms: Windows,
        Linux, Unix and Mac. WinCVS and Tortoise seem to be two of the
        most well known clients for Windows platform (see below). On
        Linux, gCVS and Cervisia are the most popular.</para>

        <para>There is also a 100% Java client called jCVS that runs on any
        machine supporting JDK (or JRE). And finally, for those of you who use
        Emacs or Xemacs as an editor you&#39;ll probably want to use the
        excellent pcl-cvs package, which provides full CVS integration on
        these editors. Many commercial text editors also offer tight
        integration with CVS.</para>

        <para>Finally it's worth noticing that most integrated
        development environment on the market (MS Visual Studio,
        Visual Age, IntelliJ IDEA, Eclipse,&hellip;) comes with CVS
        plugins either provided natively or by 3rd party companies.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="SettingUpWinCVS">
        <title>Setting up WinCVS for CodeX</title>

        <para>As mentioned above, WinCVS is one of the most popular CVS clients
        on Windows. Below are all the instructions needed to get WinCVS running on
        a CodeX project. In the examples, "username" is the user login name, and "projectname"
        is the short project name.</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Download WinCVS from  <ulink
          url="http://www.wincvs.org">http://www.wincvs.org</ulink> and
          install it on your PC.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run WinCVS: <literal>Start->Programs->WinCvs</literal>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Setup the connection to the Codex project: 
          <literal>Admin->Preferences</literal>
          </para><para>Enter the CVSROOT:</para><para>
          <literal>:pserver:username@cvs.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/cvsroot/projectname</literal>
          </para><para>Make sure the Authentication is set to: 
          <literal>"passwd" file on the cvs server</literal></para>
          <para>Then hit OK.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Log in to CVS: <literal>Admin->Login...</literal> Enter your password.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Identify the place where you are going to install the source code: 
          <literal>View->Browse Location->Change...</literal>
          </para>
        </listitem> 
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Checkout the source code from the CVS repository of your Codex project:</para>
          <para><literal>Create->Check out module</literal></para>
          <para><literal>Enter the module name and path on the server:</literal></para>
          <para>type the path of the source code you want to extract. In general it's the name of the top directory of your CVS repository.</para>
          <para>then hit OK.</para>
          <para>Note that this may take a while for large projects
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Now that you have the source code of the project on
          your machine you can start modifying the code, update it
          with new modifications from the repository, etc.  WinCVS
          keeps track of changed files by marking them with a red
          icon.</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Other things to know about WinCVS:</para>

        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>If someone modifies a text file at the same time you
          do, and checks it in first, then when you go to check yours
          in, the lines that you both changed independent of the other
          will automatically get updated to the latest changes. If any
          lines conflict, you'll get an error message letting you know
          that there were conflicts, and that your version of the file
          will need to be modified to resolve the conflicts. You'll
          also find lines in your version with
          "&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;" and "&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;"
          delimiting the conflicts. Edit the conflicts, then
          re-commit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Be careful with the "remove selected" (the big black
          X), which doesn't delete your local version of the file, it
          queues the file for removal from CVS.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="CVSReferences">
      <title>CVS References</title>

      <para>As stated earlier in this chapter, this document is not a
      CVS Tutorial. It focuses on the integration of CVS in CodeX and
      how to use CVS in the CodeX context. If you want to learn more
      about CVS refer to the following documents:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>A CVS Tutorial (Powerpoint): see <ulink
          url="http://codex.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/slides/CVS_Tutorial.ppt">http://codex.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/slides/CVS_Tutorial.ppt</ulink>). An
          HTML version (compressed) is also available at <ulink
          url="http://codex.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/slides/slideCVS_HTML.zip">http://codex.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;/slides/slideCVS_HTML.zip</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open Source Development with CVS : excellent book also
          known as "The CVS Black Book". Also available
          in printed form from Coriolis Press. See <ulink url="http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/">http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The official CVS Manual. Otherwise known as the
          "Cederqvist" after the name of the author. See <ulink
          url="http://www.cvshome.org/docs/manual/index.html">http://www.cvshome.org/docs/manual/index.html</ulink>This
          document is also contained in the CVS software releases -
          see below.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Various CVS Docs and FAQs. See <ulink
          url="http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs-index.html">http://www.loria.fr/~molli/cvs-index.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Official CVS Web Site. See <ulink
          url="http://www.cvshome.org/">http://www.cvshome.org/</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="CVSIntegrationinCodeX">
    <title>CVS Integration in CodeX</title>

    <section id="TheCVSRepository">
      <title>The CVS Repository</title>

      <para>Whenever a new project is hosted on CodeX, a new CVS
      repository is automatically created and properly
      initialized. Each project has its own CVS repository. Having its
      own repository has a certain number of advantages: your CVS
      logs, history files (<literal>CVSROOT/history</literal>), and
      all administrative files are unique to your repository.  This
      allows you to fully customize the behavior of your CVS
      repository.</para>

      <note><para>All CVS repositories are available under the
      <literal>/cvsroot/projectname</literal> directory on the CodeX
      server. All interactions with the CVS repository take place from
      a CVS client through the cvs program. If need be and if this
      feature is active on your server, you can also use your shell
      account (see <xref linkend="ShellAccount" />) to interact with
      the CVS repository directly but you should never do that unless
      you know exactly what you are doing.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="CVSAccessControl">
      <title>CVS Access Control</title>
      
      <para>CVS access permission depends upon the project status
      (private or public) and the class of citizen a user belongs to
      (see <xref linkend="ClassesOfCitizens" />).</para>

      <para>Regarding private projects, only project members have
      access to the CVS repository. By default they all have read and
      write access. This can be modified by adding in the
      <literal>CVSROOT/readers</literal> file the name of the project
      member for which only read access is granted. It is currently
      not possible to deny access to the CVS repository to a member of
      a private project. If you want to do so or want to setup more
      sophisticated access control permission we highly recommend that
      you use Subversion instead of CVS (see <xref
      linkend="VersionControlWithSubversion" />).</para>

      <para>With respect to the public projects, the default access
      permissions are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Anonymous Users</emphasis>:
          users who have not registered with CodeX (or are not logged
          in) have <emphasis role="underline">no access at
          all</emphasis> to the CVS repositories. Depending on the
          configuration of the CodeX server, anonymous user may even
          be denied access to the entire site.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Registered Users</emphasis>:
          have read-only access to CVS repositories. In other words
          they can checkout a working copy of the software but they
          are not allowed to commit any changes they have made to the
          source code. Source code contributions (bug fix,
          enhancements&hellip;) from this class of user must return to
          the project team via the Patch Tracker (see <xref
              linkend="PatchTemplate" /> ).</para>

          <note><para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: all source code
          accesses are recorded by CodeX. Project administrators
          always have access to the list of people who accessed the
          source code (see <xref linkend="SourceCodeAccessLogs" />).</para></note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Members</emphasis>:
          members of a CodeX hosted project are granted a password
          protected read/write access. As mentionned above in the
          section about private projects, it is also possible to grant
          read-only access to the project members.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Project
          Administrators</emphasis>: same as project members.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="CVSWebInterface">
    <title>The CVS Web Interface</title>

    <para>CodeX offers a number of facilities that allow you to
    interact with your CVS repository through the Web interface. The
    CVS Web interface does not intend to replace the CVS client that
    you should normally use on your desktop computer. It rather
    focuses on providing you with additional features not found in cvs
    clients. The CVS Web interface can be accessed via the
    &#34;CVS&#34; item in the Project Main Menu or via the CVS service
    listed in the Public Area (see <xref
    linkend="FigureASampleProjectSummaryPage" />). The CodeX CVS Web
    interface provides the following features:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Accessing the CVS
        repository</emphasis>: The welcome page of the CodeX CVS
        service gives you all the information you need to access the
        CVS repository from your CVS client. Among other things it
        tells you what the CVS root path is and how to log in and
        checkout the source code. This page may also be customized for 
        specific needs (see <xref linkend="CVSAdministration" />).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Browsing the CVS
        repository</emphasis>: this feature allows you to browse the
        CVS repository even if you don't have a CVS client installed
        on your desktop machine. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Querying CVS </emphasis>: if the
        CVS tracking feature has been activated for your project
        (default) all CVS events (commit, file addition or deletion)
        are tracked down in the CodeX database. This audit trail can
        be searched using several criteria.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS Administration </emphasis>:
        this service allows you to activate the CVS tracking for your
        project, to activate email notification for all CVS
        events, and to customize the CVS welcome page (CVS Preamble).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Let's review some of these features in more details:</para>

    <section id="BrowsingTheCVSRepository">
    <title>Browsing The CVS Repository</title>

    <para>In order to interact with the CVS repository of any
    CodeX-hosted project, you normally need to have CVS installed on
    your machine.  However CodeX also offers a built-in Web browsing
    interface to the CVS repository which allows you to navigate in
    the source code, download it, view a file history or compare two
    revisions of the same file.</para>

      <figure id="FigureASampleCVSWebSession">
        <title>Browsing the CVS repository - A sample session</title>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="../../slides/en_US/CVS_Web_Session.png" width="12cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="QueryingCVS">
    <title>Querying CVS</title>

      <para>If a project has the CVS Tracking feature activated (see
      <xref linkend="CVSAdministration" />), the CVS Web interface
      will bring very useful features to the software
      engineers:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="dash">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Atomic CVS commit and unique
          commit ID</emphasis>: all changes (file modification,
          addition or removal) that are committed in one go from your
          CVS client will be assigned a unique commit ID. All file
          revisions modified during this commit will be stored
          atomically in the CVS Tracking database under this unique
          commit ID.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Commit
          cross-referencing</emphasis>: the unique commit ID that is
          generated at each commit can be referenced in future
          commits, or in the follow-up comments of project artifacts
          like bugs/tasks/support requests simply by using the pattern
          <literal>commit #XXXX</literal> (where XXXX is the unique ID
          generated by CodeX). Any reference of that kind will be
          automatically transformed into an hyperlink to the CVS
          tracking database. This mechanism makes it very easy to go
          from project artifacts like bugs, support requests or tasks
          to source code changes and vice-versa. (see below for more details)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Commit search</emphasis>:
          another side benefit of the CVS Tracking database is that
          you can use various search criteria to query the
          database. You can search code changes by authors (who made
          the change), by commit ID, by tag or by keywords to be found
          in the log message. Results can also be sorted by clicking
          on the headers of the search results (see <xref
          linkend="FigureCVSSearch" />).</para>

          <para>A click on one of the selected commit ID brings you to
          a complete description of the change, the files that were
          impacted and the nature of the change with a direct link
          into the CVS repository if you want to browse the file or
          look at the code modification (see <xref
          linkend="FigureCVSShowCommit" />).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
          
    </section>


      <figure id="FigureCVSSearch">
        <title>Querying the CVS tracking database of a given project</title>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_cvssearch.png" width="15cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure id="FigureCVSShowCommit">
        <title>The detail of an atomic CVS commit</title>
        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="../../screenshots/en_US/sc_cvsshowcommit.png" width="15cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

    <section id="Cross-Referencing CVS Commits">
    <title>Cross-Referencing Artifacts and CVS Commits</title>

      <para>While working in the development or the maintenance phase
      of a software project, it is vital to keep track of the changes
      made to the source code. This is what Version Control systems
      like CVS do. In addition to keeping track of the source code
      change history it is often critical to relate the changes to the
      artifact (a task, a defect or a support request) that led the
      developers to make a change in the code. And conversely, when
      reading the artifact description it is also very helpful to
      immediately see how the change was implemented.</para>

      <para>The integration of CVS in CodeX precisely provide the
      CodeX users with this bi-directionnal cross-referencing
      mechanism. This is achieved through the use of reference patterns
      that are automatically detected by CodeX in either the follow-up
      comments of the project artifacts or in the messages attached to
      a CVS commit.</para>
      
      <para>The text patterns to type in a commit message or a follow-up comment are as follows:</para>

   <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para> <emphasis role="bold">XXX #NNN</emphasis>: this pattern
        refers to the artifact XXX number NNN, where NNN is the unique 
        artifact ID, and XXX is the tracker short name (e.g. &#34;bug
        #123&#34;, &#34;task #321&#34;, &#34;req #12&#34;, etc.).
        If you don't know the tracker short name or don't want to specify it, you
        may simply use  &#34;art #NNN&#34;. When browsing a message containing this
        pattern anywhere in CodeX, the pattern will be automatically
        transformed into an hyperlink to the artifact
        description.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">commit #YYY</emphasis>: this
        pattern refers to the commit YYY where YYY is the commit unique
        ID as listed when querying the CVS tracking database. When
        browsing a message containing this pattern anywhere in CodeX,
        the pattern will be automatically transformed into an
        hyperlink to the commit description (log messages,
        impacted files, versions and author of the change.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The CodeX reference mechanism allows cross-referencing with any CodeX object: artifacts, documents, files, etc.  Please refer to <xref linkend="ReferenceOverview" /> for more details on CodeX references.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para><tip><title>Tip: cross-reference artifacts and CVS
   commits</title><para>It is considered a best practice to always
   reference a bug, a task or a support request in any of the log
   message attached to a CVS commit. Similarly when closing the
   related artifact (task, bug,etc.) make sure you mention the commit
   ID in the follow-up comment. You will find this extremelly
   convenient while trying to keep track of the changes and why it was
   made.</para></tip></para>


    </section>

    <section id="CVSAdministration">
      <title>CVS Administration</title>
      <para>Through the Web interface, CodeX allows you to configure the following settings:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS Tracking</emphasis>: Being a
          version control system CVS is, of course, natively taking
          care of all your file history and is able to tell you what
          changes were made by whom and at what date. The file history
          is something you can look at either through your CVS client
          or through the CVS Web Browsing interface.</para>

          <para>If you activate the CVS tracking for your project
          CodeX will also keep track of all the code changes in the
          CodeX database. This will give you extra capabilities on
          your CVS repository as explained in <xref
          linkend="QueryingCVS" /></para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS E-mail
        Notification</emphasis>: In addition to tracking the changes
        in the CodeX database, CodeX can also send a nicely formatted
        email message to individual email addresses or mailing lists
        each time there is a change in your source code. The email
        message contains the log message, the author of the change,
        the list of impacted files and pointers to the CVS repository
        showing what changes were made. </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">CVS Preamble</emphasis>: In some
          cases (e.g. for legacy projects), the project CVS repository
          might not be hosted by the CodeX server. In this case, the
          CVS information displayed in the welcome page of the CodeX
          CVS service is incorrect. Fortunately, the project
          administrator can customize the CVS preamble here.</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: create a specific mailing list for CVS
      events notification</title><para>If you intend to generate email
      notification for the changes made in your CVS repository, it is a
      good practice to create a specific mailing list called
      <literal>projectname-cvsevents</literal>. By doing so, CodeX
      users and project members interested in receiving the email
      notification just need to subscribe to the mailing list. In
      addition, the CodeX mailing list manager will archive all the
      email messages which can prove very useful for future reference. 
      See <xref linkend="MailingLists" /> for mailing list
      creation.</para></tip></para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="ATypicalCVSLifeCycle">
    <title>A Typical CVS Life Cycle</title>

    <para>Again the intent of this section is not to give formal CVS
      training but rather to explain what are the steps a project team
      typically goes through to efficiently use CVS and, more generally, all
      the CodeX tools involved in a Software release process.</para>

    <para> It also deals with the problem of contributing source code
    when you are not part of a project team. In this section all
    examples are given in the form of CVS command lines but
    transposing them to graphical front-ends should not be a
    problem.</para>

    <figure id="FigureATypicalSoftwareDevelopmentLifeCycleOnCodeX">
      <title>A Typical Software Development Life Cycle on CodeX</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="../../slides/en_US/CVS_Life_Cycle.png" width="14cm" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="LoggingIn">
      <title>Logging In</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>The first step when dealing with a CodeX-hosted CVS repository
        is to authenticate yourself with the CVS server. In CodeX, anonymous
        users cannot access the source code of any project whether be it
        through the CVS repository or through the File Release mechanism. So
        make sure you have created your own account on CodeX before
        interacting with a CVS repository.</para>

      <para>Assuming that you have your CodeX login/password ok, you can now
        use them to authenticate yourself with the CVS repository. To connect
        to the CVS repository of a given project type the following command
        (in one line):</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -d:pserver:loginname@cvs.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/cvsroot/projectname
login
        </programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The -d argument is called the CVS root path. This path is a
            sort of URL to locate your CVS repository on the net. CVS
            graphical front-ends will also ask you for this root path.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>projectname</literal> is the
            project short name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>loginname</literal> is your
            CodeX login</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>CVS keeps track of the password associated with a given CVS root
        path. So as long as you do not logout there is no need to authenticate
        yourself in subsequent working sessions. If you don&#39;t want to
        leave your CVS connection &#34;open&#34; when you leave your office,
        use the &#34;<literal>cvs logout</literal>&#34; command.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ImportingExistingSourceCode">
      <title>Importing Existing Source Code</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>As the happy administrator of a new CodeX project, the
      first thing to do is to populate your freshly brewed CVS
      repository with your project source code. To do so, first create
      a new directory <literal>topdirectory</literal> on your
      workstation and place your source code under this top directory
      (keep the exact same directory structure you are used to under
      topdirectory). Then type the following commands (the second
      command in one line):</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
$ cd topdirectory
$ cvs -d:pserver:loginname@cvs.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/cvsroot/projectname
import topdirectory vendor_tag start
        </programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The -d argument is called the CVS root path. This path is a
            sort of URL to locate your CVS repository on the net. CVS
            graphical front-ends will also ask you for this root path.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>projectname</literal> is the
            project short name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>loginname</literal> is your
            CodeX login (all lowercase)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>topdirectory</literal> is the
            name of the top level directory to import</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>vendor_tag</literal> is a
            special tag. For now replace it with your own name  or your company name (without space).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: made a mistake while importing your source
        code?</title><para>It is not unusual to make a mistake when importing
        your source code into a fresh CVS repository especially for new users.
        Typical mistakes are directories placed at the wrong level or with the
        wrong name. Nothing to fear though... if you want to start again on a
        new CVS repository contact the CodeX Team and we&#39;ll do that for
        you.</para></tip></para>

      <note><para>Note that if you already have a CVS repository
        available, the CodeX Team can help you transfer this repository on
        CodeX and preserve all of your project history. We just need an
        archive (zip or tar) of your entire CVS tree including the CVSROOT
        directory. From there we&#39;ll re-install everything for you on the
        CodeX server. Contact us for more information.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section id="CheckingCodeOut">
      <title>Checking Code Out</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>Once a CVS repository has been populated project members
      (or CodeX users at large if they are granted access) can
      checkout the source code and place it on their own
      workstation. The result is called a working copy in the CVS
      jargon. Note that &#39;checkout&#39; in the CVS world does not
      mean that the user has acquired any sort of lock on the
      file. The CVS paradigm is: anyone (with the right permissions)
      can retrieve a working copy for editing; changes made by
      different users are then reconciled or flagged for conflict
      resolution whenever the modified files are locally updated. As
      its name says it and unlike other tools (RCS, SCCS,
      ClearCase...) CVS is a concurrent version control system.</para>

      <para>A working copy is NOT an image of the CVS repository. It is
        rather a snapshot of the source tree at some point in time and, by
        default, it&#39;s the latest version at the time the working copy is
        created or updated. One of the interesting features of a working copy
        is that it is a self-contained entity. In other words, a working copy
        contains all the necessary information for CVS to know exactly which
        CVS server and repository it is coming from and the corresponding
        moment in the history of the source tree . This is also why you
        won&#39;t see the -d command-line option in all subsequent CVS
        commands presented here. These commands run from within a working
        copy, so CVS knows exactly where the CVS repository is.</para>

      <para>To create a working copy type the following command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -d:pserver:loginname@cvs.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/cvsroot/projectname
checkout directory
</programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The -d argument is called the CVS root path. This path is a
            sort of URL to locate your CVS repository on the net. CVS
            graphical front-ends will also ask you for this root path.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>projectname</literal> is the
            project short name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>loginname</literal> is your
            CodeX login (all lowercase)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>directory</literal> is the
            path to the directory that you want to checkout. To learn more
            about the directory structure of the CVS repository you are
            working with, first browse the CVS repository via the CVS Web
            Interface (see <xref linkend="CVSWebInterface" />)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="UpdatingtheSourceCode">
      <title>Updating the Source Code</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>Running a &#34;<literal>cvs update</literal>&#34; command
      from within a working copy has the effect of updating the
      working copy (or a subpart of it) with the latest version of
      each source file from the CVS repository. To update a working
      copy with terse output mode type:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -q update
        </programlisting>

      <para>If you simply want to know what files have changed on the CVS
        repository since your last update but don&#39;t want to update your
        working, you can run the cvs command with the
        &#34;show-me-but-don&#39;t-do&#34; flag (-n):</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -n -q update
        </programlisting>

      <para>Remark: The CVS update command is among the most semantically
        rich in the CVS command set. It is used not only as described above,
        but also to merge your working copy with another version of the
        software, possibly changing the branch to which your working copy
        points. Refer to your CVS documentation for complete details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="CommittingyourChanges">
      <title>Committing your Changes</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>Project members involved in development activities will likely
        want to contribute the changes made in their own working copy back to
        the CVS repository. In CVS terminology this is called a commit
        operation.</para>

      <para>To commit changes you have made in your working copy, type the
        following command:</para>

      <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs commit -m&#34;Explain the nature of the change here...&#34; [filenames]
        </programlisting>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The -m option is followed by a text message explaining what
            changes you have made</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <emphasis>filenames</emphasis> argument is optional. It
            can be individual files or directories. But if there isn&#39;t any
            argument cvs will automatically commit all the files that have
            changed in the directory where you are located and all
            sub-directories recursively.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Include a bug or task number in your
      commit messages</title><para>In the ideal world, all
      modifications made to the source code of a project should be
      related to either a bug logged in the CodeX BTS or to a task
      assign to a developer. If your project team lives in this
      wonderful world :-) then don&#39;t forget to include the related
      bug or task ID number at the beginning or at the end of your
      commit message (see <xref linkend="ArtifactCrossReferencing"
      />). The CVS administrative files can help you enforce this rule
      by checking the format of all the submitted commit messages and
      reject them if it does not follow the recommended
      pattern.</para></tip></para>

      <para>As a project member, make sure you understand and follow your
        project policy before you commit any changes to your CVS repository.
        For example some projects require that only working, build-able, code
        that passes automatic unit tests be checked into the main branch. Thus
        the baseline can automatically be built and unit tested nightly.</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: update before you commit</title><para>If you
        try to commit a modified file that was also modified on the CVS
        repository in the meantime, the CVS server will refuse to execute the
        <literal>cvs commit</literal> command. You must first execute a
        <literal>cvs update</literal> command to bring your own working copy
        up to date with latest version, merge your changes with those from
        others (CVS does it automatically in most cases) and then only commit
        your own changes back to the CVS repository. If you want to be immune
        from others&#39; changes then create a CVS branch and work with it in
        isolation.</para></tip></para>

    </section>

    <section id="ContributingyourChanges">
      <title>Contributing your Changes (other users)</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: all CodeX users</emphasis></para>

      <para>This is a variant of the previous section for those of you who
        do not have write access to the CVS repository of a project and,
        therefore, cannot commit their modifications to the CVS repository.</para>

      <para>The variant explained here is actually a method that is
      universally used in the Open Source world to contribute source
      code modification to the project team. It consists in the
      generation of a text file containing the differences between
      your modified version of the source code and the original one
      that you initially downloaded.  This file is called a
      <emphasis>diff file</emphasis> because there is a tool called
      diff that can automatically do that for you.</para>

      <para>The reason why diff files are so popular is because they
      follow a well-documented format. Diff files are sent to the
      original project team which, upon reception, is going to use
      another universal tool called <litteral>patch</litteral> to
      automatically merge the contributed changes with the master copy
      of the source code. This is why, by extension, a diff file is
      also known as a <emphasis>patch</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Diff files can be generated either with the
        <litteral>diff</litteral> tool (part of the GNU tools) that is
        available on all platforms including Windows or directly with CVS if
        you have been hacking on a CVS working copy.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">The <litteral>diff</litteral> way:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the diff way when you obtained the original source code
            from a File Release and not from the project CVS repository.
            Let&#39;s assume the original source file is under the directory
            <literal>project-0.1/</literal> and that your modified version is
            under <literal>project-0.1-new/</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can generate a diff file with the following command (all
            files in subdirectories will be checked recursively for changes)</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
diff -rc project-0.1/ project-0.1-new/
</programlisting>

        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">The CVS way:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the preferred way when you obtained the source code
            by creating your own CVS working copy. Let&#39;s assume that you
            are at the top level of the working copy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can generate a diff file between your version and the
            very latest version in the CVS repository for the entire source
            tree by typing with the following CVS command:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs diff -c
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you want to generate a diff against a specific version of
            the source tree, then specify the tag for this version (version V1
            in the example below) in the command line:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs diff -c -r V1
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In both cases, store the output of the diff or cvs diff
      command in a text file. Compress the output file if it&#39;s a
      large one and use the CodeX Patch Tracker (see <xref
      linkend="PatchTemplate" />) to submit your patch to the project
      team).</para>

      <para>And thanks for contributing some code!</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ExportingandPackaging">
      <title>Exporting and Packaging</title>

      <para><emphasis>Audience: project members</emphasis></para>

      <para>There is a quick and easy way to release a pre-packaged version
        of your source file and make it available to your users through
        the File Release mechanism (see <xref linkend="FileRelease" />).</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Make sure all the project members involved in software
            development have committed the changes that were supposed to
            appear in this new release.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Update your own working copy with the changes committed by
            all other project members with the following command:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -q update
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Update the ChangeLog, Release Notes and README file at the
            top of your source tree and commit the changes for these 3 files.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Tag (mark) the CVS repository with the appropriate version
            number. This version number will be attached to the most recent
            revision of all committed files. From your working copy type
            (V_1_2 is a tag name that represents version 1.2 of your project):</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -q tag V_1_2
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Your software release is now ready. Export a clean image of
            the CVS source tree in a fresh directory. By clean image we mean
            an image without any CVS specific files in it. Just source files.
            Assuming that you wish to export version 1.2 (tagged with label
            V_1_2) and that you want the exported software to be rooted under
            the <literal>projectname-1.2</literal> directory, type:</para>

          <programlisting format="linespecific" linenumbering="unnumbered" width="80">
cvs -d:pserver:loginname@cvs.projectname.&SYS_DEFAULT_DOMAIN;:/cvsroot/projectname
export projectname-1.2
</programlisting>
          <para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Create a ZIP or tar archive with the entire
            <literal>project-1.2/</literal> directory</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Deliver this archive through the File Release service (see <xref linkend="FileReleaseDelivery" />).</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Done! Nice job...Take a break. And remember to announce the
            availability of your new version via the CodeX News service (see
            <xref linkend="NewsService" />).</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="CVSforProjectAdministrators">
    <title>CVS for Project Administrators</title>

    <para>There are a few things that Project Administrators must absolutely
      be aware of to manage their CVS repository well.</para>

    <section id="MoreonCVSAccessControl">
      <title>More on CVS Access Control</title>

      <para>As explained in <xref linkend="CVSAccessControl" /> CVS
        is setup in such a way that write access is granted to all project
        members (and project members only).</para>

      <para>It is, however, possible for a project administrator to
        deny CVS write access to certain project members. Revoking CVS
        write access for project members is not (yet!) feasible from
        the Web interface. You must use your Shell Account to log into
        the CodeX server (see <xref linkend="ShellAccount" />) and
        type the following commands at the shell prompt:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>newgrp projectname</literal> (Where <literal>projectname</literal> is the
            short project name)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>cd /cvsroot/projectname/CVSROOT</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Edit the <literal>readers</literal> file and add the login
            name of the project members with read-access only (one login name
            per line)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>exit</literal> (Logout)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="CVSAdministrativeFiles">
      <title>CVS Administrative Files</title>

      <para>Each CVS repository comes with a number of administrative
      files that are all located in the <literal>CVSROOT</literal>
      directory.  These files gives project administrators all sorts
      of interesting capabilities like the creation of virtual modules
      from a collection of files and directories, trigger e-mail
      notification on certain events like commit or add (note: CodeX
      already does it for you - see below), check the format of a CVS
      tag before accepting it, etc. (See the CVS Documentation cited
      in <xref linkend="CVSReferences" /> for more information about
      CVS administrative files).</para>

      <para><tip><title>Tip: Never edit CVS Administrative files in place</title><para>Never-ever
        edit any CVS administrative files directly in the CVS repository by
        using your CodeX Shell Account (except for <literal>readers</literal>
        and <literal>writers</literal> files). Always use CVS itself to manage
        the changes you want to apply to these files. Proceed as usual by
        checking out a working copy of the CVSROOT directory. Edit the
        appropriate files and commit the changes to the repository.</para></tip></para>

      <note><para>When making changes to the administrative files make
      sure you preserve the CodeX specific settings in the following
      files: <literal>config</literal>, <literal>writers</literal> and
      <literal>loginfo</literal>. Also be very careful not to change
      directory or file ownership unless you know exactly what you are
      doing.</para></note>
    </section>

  </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

