<!--
//
// CodeX: Breaking Down the Barriers to Source Code Sharing inside Xerox
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, CodeX, 2001-2004. All Rights Reserved
// This file is licensed under the CodeX Component Software License
// http://codex.xerox.com
//
// $Id$
//
// Originally written by Nicolas Guerin 2005, CodeX Team, Xerox
//
-->

  <chapter id="WikiService">
  <title>Wiki Service</title>

  <para>CodeX offers a Wiki service to each project. The wiki
  available in CodeX is based on a popular wiki tool called <ulink
  url="http://phpwiki.sourceforge.net">phpWiki</ulink>.</para>


  <section id="WikiOverview">
    <title>Wiki Overview</title>

    <section id="WikiDefinition">
      <title>Wiki Definition</title>

      <para>A Wiki is a website that allows anyone to easily add
      content or to edit the content that is already in place.</para>

      <para>A wiki enables documents to be written collectively in a
      simple markup language using a web browser. A single page in a
      wiki is referred to as a "wiki page," while the entire body of
      pages, which are usually highly interconnected via hyperlinks,
      is called "the wiki.". CodeX offers an intermediate
      representation called a "Wiki Document": it is a wiki page that
      is directly accessible from the project wiki main page.</para>

      <para>A defining characteristic of wiki technology is the ease
      with which pages can be created and updated. There is no review
      or approval process before modifications are accepted, and CodeX
      wikis are open to all CodeX registered users.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WikiPageFormatting">
      <title>Wiki Page Formatting</title>

      <para>In CodeX wikis, there are three representations for each
      page: the HTML code, the web page resulting from rendering that
      code by a web browser, and the user-editable source code, from
      which the server produces the HTML. The latter format, known as
      "wikitext", is written in a simplified markup language.</para>

      <para>The reasoning behind this design is that HTML, with its
      large library of nested tags, is too complicated to allow
      fast-paced editing, and distracts from the actual content of the
      pages. It is also viewed as beneficial that users cannot use all
      the functionality that HTML allows, such as JavaScript and
      Cascading Style Sheets, because of the consistency in look and
      feel that is thereby enforced, and for security reasons.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WikiLinkingandCreatingPages">
      <title>Linking and Creating Pages</title>

      <para>Wikis are a true hypertext medium, with non-linear
      navigational structures. Each page typically contains a large
      number of links to other pages. Links are automatically created using a
      specific syntax, the so-called "link pattern."</para>

      <para>CodeX wikis use CamelCase as a link pattern, produced by
      capitalizing words in a phrase and removing the spaces between
      them (the word "CamelCase" is itself an example of
      CamelCase). The term CamelCase comes from the uppercase "bumps"
      in the middle of the compound word, suggesting the bumps of a
      camel.</para>

      <para> CodeX wikis also allow other ways of creating wiki links
      by putting anything into square brackets. This allows the
      creation of page titles containing blank characters.</para>

      <para>New pages in a wiki are created simply by creating the
      appropriate links on a topically related page. If the link does
      not exist, it is emphasized as a "new" link. Following that link
      opens an edit window, which then allows the user to enter the
      text for the new page. This mechanism ensures that so-called
      "orphan" pages (which have no links pointing to them) are rarely
      created.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WikiSearching">
      <title>Searching</title>

      <para>CodeX wikis offer a title search, as well as a full text
      search.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="CodeXWikis">
    <title>CodeX Wikis</title>

    <para>CodeX wikis are project-specific. So two different projects may use the same page names without conflict.</para>

    <section id="WikiCreation">
      <title>Wiki Creation</title>

      <para>The wiki has to be initialized by a project administrator
      before use: simply click on the "Wiki" link in the service bar,
      select the wiki language, press 'Create', and wait for the
      creation process to complete.</para>

      <para>Please note that the language of the wiki is initialized
      once and for all: it cannot be changed later, and it is viewed
      in the selected language, whatever the user preferences. </para>

      <para>The wiki creation phase creates a default set of useful
      wiki pages: a welcome page, a sandbox to play with, the PhpWiki
      documentation, etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WikiPermissions">
      <title>Wiki Permissions</title>

      <para>By default, CodeX wikis are viewable and editable by any
      CodeX registered user.</para>

      <para>While this is usually the best policy, some wikis should
      not be public. For those cases, CodeX offers a permission
      mechanism based on user groups, as for file releases and
      documents (see <xref linkend="UserGroups"/>, <xref
      linkend="FileAccessPermissions"/> and <xref
      linkend="DocAccessPermissions"/>). Permissions may be set at
      the wiki level, and apply to all pages, or at the page level, so
      that only selected pages are protected.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="ExamplesofWikiPages">
      <title>Examples of Wiki Usage</title>

      <para>Project Wikis hosted on CodeX may typically be used for
      many different purposes. The following examples are just
      suggestions:</para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Meeting minutes</emphasis>:
	  wikis are very convenient places to hold meeting
	  minutes. Simply type the meeting name as a wiki link, click
	  on this new link and type the minutes. Additionally, anybody
	  can edit and correct the content later.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Project Calendar</emphasis>:
	  CodeX wiki pages may include a shared calendar, that every
	  team member can access and edit (see the CalendarPlugin
	  page).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis role="bold">Documentation</emphasis>: a wiki
	  is a convenient way of providing project documentation (user
	  guide, administration guide, FAQ, etc.). This documentation
	  can be updated at any time by any team member, partners or
	  even customers if they have been granted proper access
	  permissions.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="MoreWikiDocumentation">
      <title>More Documentation</title>

      <para>All CodeX wikis are initialized with some default pages,
      including the PhpWiki documentation. See the
      PhpWikiDocumentation page for a description of all the PhpWiki
      features: syntax, plugins, etc.</para>
    </section>

  </section>
  </chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("CodeX_User_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

