<!--
//
// Copyright (c) Xerox Corporation, Codendi 2007-2008.
// This file is licensed under the GNU General Public License version 2. See the file COPYING. 
//
// Originally written by Nicolas Guerin 2004, Codendi Team, Xerox
//
-->
<chapter id="SubmittingYourCode">
  <title>Submitting your Code</title>
  <para></para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Why submit your code?</title>
    <para>
        If you develop on the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; software, there are good reasons 
        for submitting your code to the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; team. In particular, 
        if your code is merged into &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; SVN tree, then:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Your code will be supported by the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; team... but of 
            course, you can still help!</para>
      </listitem>
    
      <listitem>
        <para>
            There is no need to merge your changes or resolve conflicts when 
            updating from SVN. Since your code is already in there, updating should 
            be straightforward.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Many people will benefit from your work!
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        However, if your code is very specific to your needs, or it does not 
        interfere with the rest of the source, then you might prefer to keep it 
        for yourself. Nevertheless, remember that &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; code is 
        subject to the GNU GPL license.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Before you submit new code</title>
    <para>
        If you want to develop a new feature, please get in touch with the 
        &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team to talk about it first. By doing so, we can 
        mutualize our development resources and make your effort beneficial to 
        the entire community of users.
    </para>
    <para>
        Also, don't forget that &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; is deployed in many different 
        places in different organizations. So make sure that your specifications
        are generalized enough to fit the needs of many.
    </para>
    <para>
        Please test your code. Today, there is no code validation tool or regression 
        tests on &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME;, so please make sure your code is consistent 
        and fully tested before you submit it.
    </para>
    <para>
        Last, the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; Team is here to help! We can provide you with 
        useful guidelines and tips, so don't hesitate to talk to us.
    </para>


  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Code Submission</title>
    <para>
        The simpler way to submit your code to the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; team is to 
        provide a patch, via the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; patch manager!
    </para>
    <para>
        To create a patch, you can do the following: go in the 'httpd' directory, 
        and type: <literal>cvs diff -c * > my_cvs_patch</literal>. 
        You may also only select the files that concern the patch. Then make a 
        'tar' including the cvs diff and potentially new files you added, then 
        compress it.
    </para>
    <para>
        Once it is created, you can submit the patch with the Patch manager of 
        the &SYS_PRODUCT_NAME; project.
    </para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>

<!--
Local Variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("Codendi_Programmer_Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->
